<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-11-21T19:07:42+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sean Elvidge</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Levelling the Playing Field, Adjusting Goal Records in International Football</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2024/Adj_Eng_Goals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Levelling the Playing Field, Adjusting Goal Records in International Football"/><published>2024-11-20T17:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-20T17:13:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2024/Adj_Eng_Goals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2024/Adj_Eng_Goals/"><![CDATA[<p>In recent years, we’ve witnessed a surge in international football records being shattered. Modern players are scoring at unprecedented rates, and while this is undoubtedly exciting for fans, it raises an important question: Are today’s goal-scoring feats truly comparable to those of past legends?</p> <p>The landscape of international football has evolved significantly. The expansion of FIFA membership has introduced many new, smaller nations into the competitive arena. This influx has led to more matches where traditional football powerhouses face off against developing teams, often resulting in lopsided scorelines. Consequently, contemporary players have more opportunities to inflate their goal tallies against weaker opposition.</p> <p>This shift poses a challenge when attempting to compare the goal-scoring records of current players with those from previous eras. The legends of the past often played fewer matches against a more consistent level of competition, making their goal tallies a reflection of performances against relatively equal opponents.</p> <p>So, how can we level the playing field and make fair comparisons across different football eras?</p> <h2 id="introducing-a-weighted-goal-system">Introducing a Weighted Goal System</h2> <p>To address this disparity, I embarked on a project to adjust goal records by accounting for the relative strength of the opposition. The idea is to assign a weighting to each goal based on the difficulty of scoring against a particular team at the time of the match. This method aims to provide a more nuanced evaluation of a player’s goal-scoring achievements.</p> <h3 id="utilizing-elo-ratings">Utilizing ELO Ratings</h3> <p>The foundation of this approach lies in the ELO rating system, a method originally devised for ranking chess players but now widely adopted across various sports, including football. ELO ratings provide a dynamic measure of a team’s strength, updating after each match based on the result and the quality of the opposition.</p> <p>By leveraging historical ELO ratings, we can assess the relative strength of any two teams at the time they played. This allows us to calculate a weighting factor for each goal scored, reflecting the challenge posed by the opponent.</p> <h3 id="the-weighting-formula">The Weighting Formula</h3> <p>The weighting for each goal is determined using the following formula:</p> \[\text{Weight} = 1 - k\times\frac{E-O}{E}\] <p>Where, $E$ is the ELO rating of England before the match, $O$ is the ELO rating of the opposition before the match and $k$ a scaling constant that adjusts the sensitivity of the weighting to the difference in ELO ratings.</p> <p>This formula adjusts the weight of a goal based on how much stronger or weaker the opposition is relative to England:</p> <ul> <li>If England faces a stronger team ($O &gt; E$), the weighting increases above 1, acknowledging the greater difficulty.</li> <li>If England faces a weaker team ($O &lt; E$), the weighting decreases below 1, reflecting the relatively easier challenge.</li> <li>The constant $k$ controls how much the difference in ratings affects the weighting.</li> </ul> <h3 id="interpreting-the-weighting">Interpreting the Weighting</h3> <p>Adjusting the $k$ value alters the impact of the opposition’s strength:</p> <ul> <li>A higher $k$ value (e.g., 2) amplifies the effect, giving more weight to goals against stronger teams and less to those against weaker ones.</li> <li>A lower $k$ value (e.g., 1) minimizes the effect, resulting in a more uniform weighting across different opponents.</li> </ul> <p>By experimenting with different $k$ values, we can fine-tune the system to balance fairness and sensitivity, ensuring that exceptional performances against top-tier teams are appropriately recognized while maintaining a reasonable value for consistent scoring against all opponents.</p> <p>For the rest of this post we use a value of $k=2$.</p> <h3 id="results">Results</h3> <p>When I last wrote a post similar to this, Wayne Rooney had just <a href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2015/Rooney-50/">broke the England National team goal record with 50 goals</a>. Since then Kane has broke this record again (at the time of writing) with 69 goals. Using the above approach the updated top 10 of England goal scorers are:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center">Ranking</th> <th style="text-align: center">Name</th> <th style="text-align: center">Adjusted Goals</th> <th style="text-align: center">Goals</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> <td style="text-align: center">Harry Kane</td> <td style="text-align: center">45</td> <td style="text-align: center">69</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> <td style="text-align: center">Gary Lineker</td> <td style="text-align: center">37</td> <td style="text-align: center">48</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> <td style="text-align: center">Bobby Charlton</td> <td style="text-align: center">36</td> <td style="text-align: center">49</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> <td style="text-align: center">Jimmy Greaves</td> <td style="text-align: center">35</td> <td style="text-align: center">44</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> <td style="text-align: center">Wayne Rooney</td> <td style="text-align: center">34</td> <td style="text-align: center">53</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> <td style="text-align: center">Michael Owen</td> <td style="text-align: center">30</td> <td style="text-align: center">40</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">7</td> <td style="text-align: center">Alan Shearer</td> <td style="text-align: center">23</td> <td style="text-align: center">30</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">8</td> <td style="text-align: center">Tom Finney</td> <td style="text-align: center">23</td> <td style="text-align: center">30</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">9</td> <td style="text-align: center">Nat Lofthouse</td> <td style="text-align: center">22</td> <td style="text-align: center">30</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">10</td> <td style="text-align: center">Frank Lampard</td> <td style="text-align: center">21</td> <td style="text-align: center">29</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>You can see that whilst Kane is still number 1 - his number of goals are significantly less. (Note that the adjusted number of goals here have been rounded to the nearest goal for ease of reading).</p> <p>As may be expected Kane has the biggest change between actual goals scored (69) and the weighted number of goals (45) with a difference of 24, perphaps reaffirming the theory that modern day players are scoring a significant amount of their goals against weaker opposition than in the past. Gary Lineker moves from 4th in the all time list to 2nd.</p> <p>At the other end of the table we end up with a number of people (41) who (because of the rounding as well) move from having scored at least 1 for England to being on 0 goals, but only four who go from more than 1 to zero:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center">Name</th> <th style="text-align: center">Goals</th> <th style="text-align: center">Adjusted Goals</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">Tammy Abraham</td> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> <td style="text-align: center">0</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">Paul Ince</td> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> <td style="text-align: center">0</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">Tyrone Mings</td> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> <td style="text-align: center">0</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">James Ward-Prowse</td> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> <td style="text-align: center">0</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Unfortuntaely Tammy Abraham’s 3 goals for England were scored against very much weaker opposition in the form of Montenegro (England won 7-0 on 14/11/19), Andorra (England won 0-5 on 09/10/21) and San Marino (England won 0-10 on 15/11/21).</p> <p>If you want to have a look at the data you can access it all <a href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/assets/files/england_elo_goal_data.csv">here</a>) (which also includes the “Adjusted Total” which weights Friendlies as 0.5 and “finals” as 2x (as per the description <a href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2015/Rooney-50/">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><category term="football"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By weighting international goals by strength of the opposition we can compare goal scoring prowess across the decades.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 and Virtual Quizzes</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2020/COVID_19_and_virtual_quizzes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 and Virtual Quizzes"/><published>2020-05-29T23:19:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-29T23:19:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2020/COVID_19_and_virtual_quizzes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2020/COVID_19_and_virtual_quizzes/"><![CDATA[<p>It is pretty easy to tell what the UK has been upto during the coronavirus lockdown, virtual pub quizzes!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/covid_quiz-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/covid_quiz-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/covid_quiz-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/covid_quiz.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Obviously the scale of the two units, Google search hits (as a fraction of the most hits) and COVID-19 are very different. So I’ve taken a simple <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Z-transform" target="\_blank">Z-transform</a> to plot the data on the same scale. I’ve also taken the rolling 7-day average to see the overall trend.</p> <p>Clearly the most popular day to prepare your quiz is a Saturday!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><category term="internet"/><category term="misc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is pretty easy to tell what the UK has been upto during the coronavirus lockdown, virtual pub quizzes!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pointless Scoring England Goalkeepers</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2019/Pointless_scoring_GKs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pointless Scoring England Goalkeepers"/><published>2019-02-26T11:19:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-26T11:19:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2019/Pointless_scoring_GKs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2019/Pointless_scoring_GKs/"><![CDATA[<p>The TV show “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pointless" target="\_blank">Pointless</a>” is based around correctly guessing obscure answers to questions. Season 5, Episode 48 had a question about England goalkeepers.</p> <p>Specifically the question was:</p> <blockquote> <p>We gave 100 people 100 seconds to name as many goalkeepers who have played for England men’s team as they could. (anyone who’s played in goal for England between 1966 and 2011 – no unused substitutes)</p> </blockquote> <p>Well this falls right into an area of something I am interested in, quizzes and football! The strategy seems obvious, the more caps a goalie received likely the more well known he would be and the more points you would score. So we want to find a player with as few caps as possible.</p> <p>Obviously I wanted to check the hypothesis.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/pointless_gk-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/pointless_gk-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/pointless_gk-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/pointless_gk.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The theory holds – the fewer caps, the better the score in Pointless.</p> <p>There are two interesting players to mention. Robert Green – who for relatively few caps scores highly (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9AWLpjhwu0c" target="\_blank">it’s not hard to guess why</a>) and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Springett" target="\_blank">Ron Springett</a> who played 33 games for England, and was even part of the 1966 World Cup winning squad, but seems fairly unknown.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><category term="football"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We gave 100 people 100 seconds to name as many goalkeepers who have played for England men's team as they could.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Penalty Shootouts are Stressful!</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Penalty_shootouts_are_stressful/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Penalty Shootouts are Stressful!"/><published>2018-07-04T22:47:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-07-04T22:47:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Penalty_shootouts_are_stressful</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Penalty_shootouts_are_stressful/"><![CDATA[<p>It is fair to say that during England’s (fantastic) World Cup win over Colombia <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football/44610244" target="\_blank">last night</a> I had my “heart in my mouth”. It was rather nerve-racking!</p> <p>Fortunately I was wearing my Fitbit and was able to download the timestamped data.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/football_HR-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/football_HR-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/football_HR-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/football_HR.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The celebration when Dier scored was epic.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="football"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is fair to say that during England’s (fantastic) World Cup win over Colombia last night I had my “heart in my mouth”. It was rather nerve-racking!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">World Cup 2018 Predictions</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/World_Cup_2018_Predictions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="World Cup 2018 Predictions"/><published>2018-06-14T15:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-06-14T15:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/World_Cup_2018_Predictions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/World_Cup_2018_Predictions/"><![CDATA[<p>The World Cup is almost upon us and so it’s time to make some predictions…</p> <p>My model, like a lot of others, is based on the <a href="https://www.eloratings.net/" target="\_blank">World Football Elo ratings (WFER)</a>. Which is a system that uses the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elo_rating_system" target="\_blank">Elo rating system</a>. You can read all about Elo on those two links, but basically after every game a team gains or loses points. The change in points is dependent on the two rankings of the teams. If there is a large difference between the two teams and the lower ranking team wins then they would gain a lot more points than if the higher ranking team won (since it is expected that they should win).</p> <p>The rating system gives different weightings for the tournaments that games take place in. They rank them in the following order:</p> <ol> <li>World Cup finals,</li> <li>Continental championship finals and major intercontinental tournaments,</li> <li>World Cup and continental qualifiers and major tournaments,</li> <li>All other tournaments,</li> <li>Friendly matches.</li> </ol> <p>The WFER site takes into account all games that results could be found for (so goes all the way back to the first official International football game, between Scotland and England on 30 November 1872, 0-0).</p> <p>My model uses a combination of ensemble machine learning methods for classification problems, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Random_forest" target="\_blank">random decision forests</a>. Each <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decision_tree" target="\_blank">decision tree</a> in the ensemble is taken from a bootstrap sample of some training set where observations about an item (represented in the branches) can be used to drawn conclusions about the item’s target value (represented in the leaves). It is a standard technique which has a wide range of uses, including the evaluation of Wikipedia articles <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007%2F978-3-319-46254-7_50" target="\_blank">quality and importance</a>.</p> <p>The model uses the WFER data for training, where all friendly matches have been removed (because very often sides don’t play a full strength team in those matches). Different combinations of training data results in different resulting models. Specifically, giving the model the rankings between the two teams and the result of the match (win, draw, loss) gives different results than if you just give the two teams rankings, but only results from major tournaments. For the final results the model has been trained using 76 decision trees with three different datasets:</p> <ol> <li>All (non-friendly) fixtures,</li> <li>All (non-friendly) fixtures since 1980,</li> <li>Fixtures from the World Cup, European Championships, Africa Cup of Nations and Copa America.</li> </ol> <p>The final results are then an average of the output of each of the three trained models.</p> <p>To test the success of the model part of the data (15% in this case) is held back and then compared against. After training the model, the accuracy of the model predictions are compared to the held back data. In this case the model was shown to be 94.8% accurate in predicting a win, draw or loss.</p> <p>The World Cup can then be simulated running the model for each match. The model returns probabilities of each of the outcomes so the same results don’t happen each time. The simulations are ran 10,000 times in order to get success probabilities for each team:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>ou can see the model predicts that Brazil have by far the greatest chance of winning the World Cup, over twice as much as the next most likely team, Germany.</p> <p>As I mentioned earlier in the post, a lot of people are making predictions of the World Cup results. A selection of those by <a href="https://eightyfivepoints.blogspot.com/2018/05/what-can-we-expect-from-21st-fifa-world.html" target="\_blank">EightyFivePoints</a>, <a href="https://www.ubs.com/content/dam/assets/wm/global/cio/doc/investing-in-emerging-markets-en.pdf" target="\_blank">UBS</a>, Gracenotes and Bet365 are compared below:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot_comb_part-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot_comb_part-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot_comb_part-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot_comb_part.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>These models (apart from Bet365’s, which is more mysterious and in the above plot is found by taking the odds for each team from the Bet365 website) all use the Elo ranking system in someway (click on the links to find more about each one). Modelling theory would suggest that, without any further details and assuming each of the above models are “good”, the best model would be the combination of them:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot_up-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot_up-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot_up-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/wc2018/WC_plot_up.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Which gives Brazil a 19.6% chance, followed by Germany (15.0%) and Spain (11.6%; although this doesn’t take into account that they sacked their manager 2 days before their first game of the tournament!).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><category term="football"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The World Cup is almost upon us and so it’s time to make some predictions…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Number of Days Between Easter’s</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Num_Days_Between_Easter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Number of Days Between Easter’s"/><published>2018-04-17T14:51:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-04-17T14:51:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Num_Days_Between_Easter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Num_Days_Between_Easter/"><![CDATA[<p>My three year old asked me a pretty interesting question this morning, “how many sleeps is it until next Easter?”</p> <p>Okay, on the one hand the question is pretty straight forward. Easter this year (2018) was on April 1st, next year (2019) Easter falls on April 21st, so 385 days. But what is more interesting is what is the range and distribution of the possible number of days between consecutive Easter’s?</p> <p>I’ve previously <a href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2017/Distr_Pancake_Day/" target="\_blank">written about the distribution of pancake day/Shrove Tuesday</a>. In that article I discussed the (very) complicated way that Easter is calculated and provide a computus for finding Easter Sunday. Looping through the years 1 to 9999 (the extreme limits of <a href="https://docs.python.org/2/library/datetime.html" target="\_blank">Python’s datetime module</a>) we actually find that there are only 4 possible options for the number of days until next Easter: 350, 357, 378 and 385 days.</p> <p>Given that Easter can fall on any day between March 22nd and April 25th I think this is quite a surprising result. The four options are not evenly distributed:</p> <ul> <li>350 days – 24.5%</li> <li>357 days – 38.7%</li> <li>378 days – 5.1%</li> <li>386 days – 31.7%</li> </ul> <p>and we won’t have a 378 day Easter gap until 2021/22 and then 2048/49 after that.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><category term="python"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How many sleeps is it until next Easter?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Was there room on the door for two?</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Was_there_room_on_the_door_for_two/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Was there room on the door for two?"/><published>2018-04-06T10:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-04-06T10:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Was_there_room_on_the_door_for_two</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Was_there_room_on_the_door_for_two/"><![CDATA[<p>Could Jack Dawson (Leonardo DiCaprio) and Rose DeWitt Bukater (Kate Winslet) from the motion picture ‘Titanic’ both have survived by both floating on the door? (Clearly there are a load of spoilers in this article – but the film did come out over 20 years ago so I’m <a href="https://letmegooglethat.com/?q=film+spoilers+statute+of+limitations" target="\_blank">not going to worry</a> too much about it).</p> <p>[Note: This is a copy of an article I wrote in 2011, which is no longer available online so I’ve repeated it here for prosperity]</p> <h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>During the <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120338/">1997 motion picture ‘Titanic’</a> by James Cameron there is a famous scene involving the two main characters, Jack Dawson (as played by Leonardo DiCaprio) and Rose DeWitt Bukater (Kate Winslet) towards the end of the film. The scene involves Jack in the ocean and Rose floating on a wooden object, Jack dies and Rose survives, however the question we ask is, need Jack of died? Was there room (and spare buoyancy) for two? This is a question which appears repeatedly (e.g. <a href="#1">[1]</a> and <a href="#2">[2]</a>) on the internet but with varying answers, but hopefully this article can draw a conclusion to the discussion.</p> <p>The first point to settle is that Rose is not floating on a door and is instead floating on a piece of wood panelling. The panelling in the film is based upon a recovered piece, homed at the <a href="https://maritimemuseum.novascotia.ca/" target="\_blank">Maritime Museum of the Atlantic, in Halifax, Nova Scotia</a> <a href="#3">[3]</a>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 1. Screenshot from `Titanic’. Rose is on the panelling, Jack floats nearby. Image from a copyrighted film, the use of this image for critical commentary and/or discussion of the film and its contents qualifies as fair usage under copyright law.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>There are two main issues that need to be resolved:</p> <ol> <li>Could they both have fit on the panelling?</li> <li>Would their combined weight have been greater than the upward force due to buoyancy (i.e. would they have sank)?</li> </ol> <h2 id="eureka">Eureka!</h2> <p>In this section we introduce the basics of buoyancy, which will be crucial in the later sections.</p> <p>The history of buoyancy is a long one, and has provided one of the most famous stories in science. Archimedes supposedly exclaimed “Eureka!” when he discovered a fundamental principle of buoyancy, which relates buoyancy to displacement. Indeed this principle is still named after him, and first appears as Proposition 5 in <a href="#4">[4]</a>.</p> <blockquote> <p>Archimedes Principle: Any solid lighter than a fluid will, if placed in the fluid, be so far immersed that the weight of the solid will be equal to the weight of the fluid displaced.</p> </blockquote> <p>This tells us that the buoyancy force, \(F_B\), is equal to the weight, \(W\), of the object placed in the fluid, so \(F_B=W\). Weight is equal to the mass of the object times gravity, \(g\), and mass is equal to density, \(\rho\), times volume, \(V\), giving rise to the more well known equation:</p> \[F_B=\rho Vg.\] <h2 id="could-they-both-fit">Could they both fit?</h2> <p>The first question to resolve is, “Could Rose and Jack have both fit on the panelling?”.</p> <p>The solution to this problem has been ‘demonstrated’ previously:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/fitondoor-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/fitondoor-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/fitondoor-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/fitondoor.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 2. Jack and Rose could have fit on the panel together [[5]](#5).</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>However, both of them fitting on the panel is not where the problem lies.</p> <h2 id="variables">Variables</h2> <p>Before we can dive into the problem of buoyancy we first need to consider a number of variables which will need to be approximated. Namely:</p> <ol> <li>What is the size of the panel?</li> <li>What is the density of the panel (what is it made from)</li> <li>What is the mass of Rose?</li> <li>What is the mass of Jack?</li> <li>What is the density of the water</li> </ol> <h3 id="panel-size">Panel Size</h3> <p>First off we approximate the size of the panelling. A common mistake (or at least a common oversight) when approaching this problem is taking the panelling to be a rectangle. This is obvious from the overhead shot of the panelling and so I’ve created a more reasonable approximation of the panelling:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 3. The approximate shape of the panel.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Now that we have the shape of the panelling we need to find the correct dimensions. All that is required is the length of one of the sides, and everything else can be calculated from that scale. From personal communication with the Maritime Museum of the Atlantic the size of the actual panel which the fictional one is based on is 150 cm by 105 cm by (~)3 cm (“the thickness of this panel is not recorded in the record, it is currently behind glass and is estimated at 3 cm”). However we can quickly see that the panelling in the film is larger than this, we can see this by comparing it with Rose’s height.</p> <p>It is a pretty safe assumption that Rose’s height is equal to Kate Winslet’s height, and she is quoted as saying she is 5 foot 6 inches (167.6 cm) <a href="#6">[6]</a>. This now gives the scale factor for the panelling (comparing the height of Rose to the length of the panel):</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_arrow-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_arrow-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_arrow-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_arrow.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 4. Using the height of Rose to calculate the size of the panelling.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Using this scaling factor gives the visible area of the panelling to be \(1.91 m^2\).</p> <p>This leaves the question of the depth of the panelling, something which is considerably harder to find. There are very few images that provide a clue of the depth, and they are not conclusive:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 5. Screenshot from 'Titanic'. Side on view of panelling.</figcaption> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 6. Screenshot from 'Titanic'. Side on view of panelling.</figcaption> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon3-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_sideon3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 7. Screenshot from 'Titanic'. Side on view of panelling.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>There are a multitude of issues with getting the scale from these images, mainly due to the angle of the camera. The first image seems to imply a depth of approximately 0.1 metres, which we find, via scaling, from Jack’s hand. However we can see that the edge which is above the water is clearly thicker than the rest of the door. Something that should be considered (especially when calculating the mass of the door). In the other figures we see that the panelling gets considerably thicker (about twice as thick again) further down (the section is underwater in the first figure). We are left to speculate whether this extra depth covers the whole of the panel, as in:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_sideon2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_sideon2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_sideon2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_sideon2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 8. One possibility of the side on view of the panelling.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>or just a small section as in:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_sideon1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_sideon1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_sideon1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_sideon1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 9. Another possibility of the side on view of the panelling.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>or anything in between. In both of these cases the head on view of the panelling is the same:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_headon-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_headon-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_headon-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/door_drawing_headon.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 10. Head on view of the panelling.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>There can be no way of knowing for sure which possibility is the correct one. However the first option would result in a considerable mass, which would probably result in the panelling not being able to float, which we know is a fallacy. So for the rest of the document we consider that we are in the second case.</p> <h3 id="roses-mass">Rose’s Mass</h3> <p>Again, let us assume that Rose’s mass is the same as Kate Winslet’s. This is hard to pin down, but via various internet sources this appears to be between 54 and 59kg <a href="#7">[7]</a> <a href="#8">[8]</a>, so, for an approximation, we take the midpoint and use 56.5kg. It is also worth noting that the wet clothes that Rose was wearing would have added a considerable mass to this total. However, for simplicity, we ignore this factor.</p> <h3 id="jacks-mass">Jack’s Mass</h3> <p>For Jack’s mass we use Leonardo DiCaprio’s mass, which is between 72.5 and 75kg <a href="#9">[9]</a>. So, for our calculations, we use 74kg. Again this would have been greater due to the wet clothes.</p> <h3 id="panel-density">Panel Density</h3> <p>The density of the wood panelling is key in our study as this will determine the mass of the panel, which is an important factor on whether the panelling will sink or float. We can immediately deduce some bounds on the density, thanks again to the Maritime Museum of the Atlantic in Halifax. According to the museum the piece of panelling is made of oak. Then from <a href="#10">[10]</a> the density of oak varies between 600 and 900 \(kg m^{−3}\). Initially a value of 750 \(kg m^{−3}\) (the midpoint) is used and then later look at what values of panel density would require which panel depths.</p> <h3 id="panel-mass">Panel Mass</h3> <p>Using the panel density the mass of the panel can be calculated.</p> <p>The volume of the panel in Figure 9 can be found by calculating the volume of the three individual sections which make up the panel. The ‘top’ section has a volume of \(0.013 m^3\). The ‘middle’ section \(0.19 m^3\) and finally the ‘bottom’ section is \(0.011 m^3\). This gives a total volume of \(0.214 m^3\). Which, using the density value from the previous section, equates to a mass of \(160.5 kg\).</p> <h3 id="water-density">Water Density</h3> <p>The density of water depends on two main factors, its temperature and the water salinity.</p> <p>On the night of the Titanic’s sinking the water temperature was reported to be 31 degrees Fahrenheit <a href="#11">[11]</a> <a href="#12">[12]</a>, which is approximately −0.56C.</p> <p>The salinity of ocean water varies with location. The Atlantic Ocean, where the Titanic sank, varies between 33 and 37 parts per thousand. According to NASA <a href="#13">[13]</a> the approximate salinity value of the Atlantic at the location where the Titanic sank (41.725, -130.05) is 36 parts per thousand. We can then use the water density calculator provided at <a href="#14">[14]</a> with the above values to find a calculated water density of $1029 kg m^{−3}$.</p> <h2 id="buoyancy">Buoyancy</h2> <p>We now come to the crux of the problem. Could the panelling have supported both Jack and Rose?</p> <p>First we consider the case which occurred in the film, Rose lying on the panelling. To do this we consider the forces acting upon the panelling, the downward force due to weight, and the upward force due to buoyancy. The only variable we do not know is the displaced volume. Since we know the area of the panel which is in contact with the water we are left to find the height that makes up the submerged portion of the panelling. Thus we actually find the depth to which the panelling sinks, clearly we require this to be greater than the total depth of the panel, in order for some of it to remain above water. We equate the buoyancy force, \(F_B\), with the total weight in the system. We use \(M_R\), \(M_P\) and \(M_J\) to represent the mass of Rose, the panel and Jack respectively.</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} F_B &amp;=&amp; W, \\ \rho Vg &amp;=&amp; (M_R+M_P)g,\\ \rho V &amp;=&amp; M_R+M_P,\\ 1029\times 1.9\times H &amp;=&amp; 56.5+160.5,\\ 1955H &amp;=&amp; 217,\\ H &amp;=&amp; 0.111. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>Which says that the door sinks 11.1cm, but we only assumed a panel depth of 10cm! Thus, using our assumptions, Rose could not have floated on top of the panel and been completely above the water. However, since the only real knowledge of this system is that Rose can float on the panel we must adjust our assumptions.</p> <p>The first assumption to try changing would be our choice of wood density, since this was chosen to be the midpoint of a fairly large range. By rearranging Equation 5 we can plot a graph of densities against how much the panelling would sink:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/graph_density-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/graph_density-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/graph_density-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/graph_density.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 11. Graph of wood density against depth the panel would sink to.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>This shows that the least the panel would sink is approximately 0.095 metres, which is less than the current assumed depth of the panel. Thus, if we assume a wood density of $600 kg m^{−3}$ then Rose could, like in the film, float on the panelling.</p> <p>This value of wood density gives a panel mass of 128.4 kg. Using this panel mass we can calculate that the panelling would sink 0.066 metres if nothing was on it, i.e. there would be approximately 3.5 centimetres floating above the water. This is a reasonable value, especially when you consider the Figure below:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/Off_door-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/Off_door-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/Off_door-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/Off_door.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 12. Screenshot from `Titanic’. Rose swimming away from the panelling, you can see the panel, floating, in the background.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>If we now repeat the above process, using the new panel mass, but also include Jack’s mass we can see whether Jack could also have floated on the panel.</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} \rho Vg &amp;=&amp; (M_R+M_P+M_J)g,\\ \rho V &amp;=&amp; M_R+M_P+M_J,\\ 1029\times 1.9\times H &amp;=&amp; 56.5+128.4+74,\\ 1955H &amp;=&amp; 258.9,\\ H &amp;=&amp; 0.132. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>So the panel would have sank 0.132 metres, or just over 13 centimetres, some 3 centimetres greater than the depth of the panelling.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>In summary, both Jack and Rose could have fitted on the piece of wooden panelling, but had they both have got on, the panel would have been submerged under water by 3.2 centimetres. However, it is likely that should they both have been on the panelling, they both would have survived (especially if they had sat). This is since the cooling rate is directly related to the amount of exposed surface area and body parts immersed in the water and the best chance of surviving accidental immersion in cold water (&lt;20C) is to keep as much of the body as possible out of the water at all times <a href="#12">[12]</a>. Jack certainly would have had a much better chance of survival, compared to the almost zero percent chance he had by staying in the water:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/titanicSpace/survival_time-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/survival_time-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/titanicSpace/survival_time-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/titanicSpace/survival_time.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Figure 13. Human survival time in cold water.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The curves in the Figure indicate the expected survival times at different levels of body insulation in cold water. Low insulation is light or no clothing, medium is wet suit, and high is dry suit. Dashed lines indicated ranges at low or high body mass [12]. This shows that the length of time Jack could have survived in the water would have been approximately 30 minutes. Indeed, only one person who entered the water after the sinking of the Titanic, and was in it for more than a few minutes, survived the ordeal [12].</p> <p>So there was room on the door (panelling) for two.</p> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <p><a id="1">[1]</a> <a href="https://funypicforyou.blogspot.co.uk/2012/05/titanic-floating-door-facts-explained.html" target="\_blank">https://funypicforyou.blogspot.co.uk/2012/05/titanic-floating-door-facts-explained.html</a></p> <p><a id="2">[2]</a> <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/funny/comments/sf1v2/ill_never_let_go_the_titanic_door_experiment/" target="\_blank">https://www.reddit.com/r/funny/comments/sf1v2/ill_never_let_go_the_titanic_door_experiment/</a></p> <p><a id="3">[3]</a> <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120338/trivia?tab=tr&amp;item=tr1076740" target="\_blank">http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120338/trivia?tab=tr&amp;item=tr1076740</a></p> <p><a id="4">[4]</a> Archimedes of Syracuse (1897) The Works of Archimedes, edited in modern notation, with introductory chapters by T.L. Heath</p> <p><a id="5">[5]</a> <a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/2012/04/18/%20jack-and-rose-titanic-plank-of-wood_n_1434092.html" target="\_blank">https://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/2012/04/18/%20jack-and-rose-titanic-plank-of-wood_n_1434092.html</a></p> <p><a id="6">[6]</a> <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/2751869.stm" target="\_blank">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/2751869.stm</a></p> <p><a id="7">[7]</a> <a href="https://www.celebheights.com/s/Kate-Winslet-109.html" target="\_blank">https://www.celebheights.com/s/Kate-Winslet-109.html</a></p> <p><a id="8">[8]</a> <a href="http://www.bangla2000.com/entertainment/celebrities/kate_winslet.shtm" target="\_blank">http://www.bangla2000.com/entertainment/celebrities/kate_winslet.shtm</a></p> <p><a id="9">[9]</a> <a href="https://starsunfolded.com/leonardo-dicaprio/" target="\_blank">https://starsunfolded.com/leonardo-dicaprio/</a></p> <p><a id="10">[10]</a> <a href="https://www.engineeringtoolbox.com/wood-density-d_40.html" target="\_blank">https://www.engineeringtoolbox.com/wood-density-d_40.html</a></p> <p><a id="11">[11]</a> Haisman D. (2009) Titanic: The Edith Brown Story. AuthorHouse, Bloomington, Indiana.</p> <p><a id="12">[12]</a> Piantadosi, Claude A. (2003) The Biology of Human Survival: Life and Death in Extreme Environments. Oxford University Press, Oxford, United Kingdom.</p> <p><a id="13">[13]</a> <a href="https://salinity.oceansciences.org/" target="\_blank">https://salinity.oceansciences.org/</a></p> <p><a id="14">[14]</a> <a href="http://www.csgnetwork.com/h2odenscalc.html" target="\_blank">http://www.csgnetwork.com/h2odenscalc.html</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><category term="internet"/><category term="misc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Could Jack Dawson and Rose DeWitt Bukater both have survived by both floating on the door?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Was there room on the door for two?</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Not_Pi_Day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Was there room on the door for two?"/><published>2018-04-06T10:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-04-06T10:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Not_Pi_Day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Not_Pi_Day/"><![CDATA[<p>Today everyone celebrates being confused why the 14th March (14/3) is celebrated as Pi Day. Instead let us celebrate what it should really be: Feigenbaum Delta Day.</p> <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitchell_Feigenbaum" target="\_blank">Mitchell Feigenbaum</a> is an award winning mathematical physicist who’s research has made possible the systematic study of chaotic systems. Systems which are very sensitive to their initial conditions.</p> <p>Consider the double pendulum which is an example of chaotic motion. Minor changes in the initial position of the pendulum give totally different paths that are then mapped out.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/pendulum-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/pendulum-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/pendulum-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/pendulum.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </figure> </div> </div> <p>(Chaos theory is also often described using “a butterfly flapping its wings in Brazil can cause a hurricane in Texas”. There are issues with this analogy, but the fundamental idea is right, in chaotic systems small changes can have big impacts).</p> <p>Part of Feigenbaum’s groundbreaking work was in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bifurcation_theory" target="\_blank">bifurcation theory</a>. In dynamical systems a bifurcation occurs when a small smooth change made to a parameter of that system causes a sudden qualitative change in its behaviour. That means that at a bifurcation the stable properties of the thing you’re interested in (e.g. equilibria, periodic orbits) can change (locally). The easiest way (I find) to think of this is to consider a “period-doubling bifurcation”: doubling, quadrupling, octupling, …</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Bifurcation-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Bifurcation-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Bifurcation-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Bifurcation.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Image (credit [Wolfram](https://mathworld.wolfram.com/Bifurcation.html){:target="\_blank"}) of a logistic map (nicely described [here](http://www.kierandkelly.com/what-is-chaos/logistic-map/){:target="\_blank"}). The blue lines highlight the bifurcations where the red line is splitting, this is the onset of chaos.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Feigenbaum looked at the ratio of the interval between bifurcations (in the period-doubling example we had above) and noticed something intriguing about it: it tends to a constant.</p> <p>If \(a(n)\) is the location of a (the nth) period-doubling bifurcation and a(n-1) is the location of the one before then:</p> \[R1 = a(n) – a(n-1)\] <p>is the distance between them. Similarly,</p> \[R2 = a(n-1) – a(n-2)\] <p>describes the distance between the previous bifurcations.</p> <p>The ratio we are interested in is then simply \(R2\) divided by \(R1\) (\(frac{R2}{R1}\)).</p> <p>You can calculate this ratio of intervals for any 3 consecutive bifurcations. For example, in the logistic map case (our earlier image) let’s read straight off the diagram three consecutive bifurcations:</p> \[a(n-2) = 3.5644073 [furthest left blue line],\\ a(n-1) = 3.5440903,\\ a(n) = 3.4494897\] <p>Calculating the ratio of the interval length gives us a value of 4.6562. If we did the same calculation for the next set of bifurcations we get a value of 4.6683, then 4.6686, then 4.6680, …</p> <p>This list of ratios goes on forever. If we could (somehow) look right at the end of the list we would see that this ratio (called \(\delta\) [delta]) is a constant: 4.669201609102990671853203821… (Mathematically speaking we are looking at the limit as \(n\) tends to infinity)</p> <p>But \(\delta\) doesn’t just appear for these period-doubling bifurcations. The same value arises for all 1D maps with a single quadratic maximum.</p> <p>Headline: <strong>all chaotic systems which meet this description bifurcate at the same rate!</strong></p> <p>\(\delta\) in bifurcation theory, is like \(\pi\) in geometry and \(e\) in calculus. Fundamental. \(\delta\) to 3 significant figures is 4.67. Today’s date, 14/3, is 4.67.</p> <p>Today is Feigenbaum Delta Day.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><category term="internet"/><category term="misc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Could Jack Dawson and Rose DeWitt Bukater both have survived by both floating on the door?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Impact of Form in Fantasy Football</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Impact_of_form_in_fantasy_football/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Impact of Form in Fantasy Football"/><published>2018-04-06T10:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-04-06T10:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Impact_of_form_in_fantasy_football</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Impact_of_form_in_fantasy_football/"><![CDATA[<p>I am a keen player of <a href="https://fantasy.premierleague.com/" target="\_blank">Fantasy Football</a>. Not only is the game huge fun (and <strong>very</strong> addictive) it also provides an excellent opportunity to play around with a whole host of mathematics. I posted a controversial thread on Twitter which has been reasonably popular (and even inspired a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/FantasyPL/comments/d4wtdc/theres_no_such_thing_as_player_form/" target="\_blank">few Reddit threads</a> and mentioned in three podcasts [that I am aware of]). The focus was on the impact of “form” on points scored in fantasy football.</p> <p>I will assume if you are reading on you understand, at least the basics, of how fantasy football (from herein, FPL), works. Put simply: a manager picks a team of 15 players with a limit of at most 3 from anyone team and budget constraints, players actions during the games get converted into points, most points at the end of the season and you win! This one version of the game (the “official version”) is played by over 7.5M people!</p> <p>Another action you have as a manager is the ability to transfer players in and out of your team. Obviously you want to make the right choice, bringing in a player just before he (for example) scores, is a great feeling. A lot of discussion about who to bring in is often based around “form”.</p> <h2 id="my-hypothesis-is-in-fpl-there-is-no-such-thing-as-form">My hypothesis is, “in FPL there is no such thing as form”.</h2> <p>The problem comes from Apophenia. The tendency to perceive connections and meaning between unrelated things. This is also commonly thought of as the “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gambler%27s_fallacy" target="\_blank">Gambler’s fallacy</a>”. The other issue, especially when considering form, is that people are very poor at thinking about ‘random’ patterns. Ask a group of people to spread themselves out randomly in a room and they inevitably place themselves evenly.</p> <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clustering_illusion" target="\_blank">In practice, randomness comes in ‘clumps’. These clumps are then mistakenly thought to be non-random</a>.</p> <p>Take for example a player which scores 15 goals in a season. A random shuffle of these goals throughout the GWs may look like this:</p> <p>1,1,1,1,0,1,0,0,1,0,0,1,0,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,1,1,0,1,1,0,0,1,0,0,1,0,0,0,1,0,0</p> <p>(this random sequence was generated in Python). Where ‘1’s are goals. If this was a striker in FPL would everyone be transferring in in those first 6 weeks citing fantastic form thanks to a good rest over the summer and bemoaning the run of 7 games without a goal in the middle of the season? Perhaps during the busy festive periods?</p> <p>Perfectly reasonable, but we’re just finding patterns in randomness. We know this for certain since this pattern was generated randomly!</p> <p>Now, lets try to quantify the above with data. First, lets make our dataset. Consider every player over the last 2 seasons and for their points we will use the ‘adjusted’ points [AP] model (points with the appearance points removed).</p> <p>Further to this I have also removed any bonus points scored and tried to account for fixture difficulty. To account for fixture difficulty I have calculated the average AP scored and conceded by a team respectively.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/formFPL/avgPts_con-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/formFPL/avgPts_con-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/formFPL/avgPts_con-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/formFPL/avgPts_con.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/formFPL/avgPts_scored-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/formFPL/avgPts_scored-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/formFPL/avgPts_scored-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/formFPL/avgPts_scored.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </figure> </div> </div> <p>A (reasonable?) way to account for the difficulty is then removing these 2 numbers.</p> <p>For example, consider Man City v Watford. City players score on average 1.12 AP points per game and Watford concede 0.61. So in that match City players have 1.73 points removed. However Watford score 0.26 and Man City concede -0.02 so Watford players have 0.24 points removed.</p> <p>Then for each player, for each season, the average (mean) of their scores are removed. That leaves us with this kind of thing:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/formFPL/AP_Sterling-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/formFPL/AP_Sterling-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/formFPL/AP_Sterling-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/formFPL/AP_Sterling.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Time series of avg. removed adjusted points for Sterling for the 2018/19 season, the gaps are games where he played no part.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Looking across the whole dataset we have 20,875 data points. Of those 7,180 are positive (above the mean) and 13,767 are negative (below the mean).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/formFPL/FPL_ptDist-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/formFPL/FPL_ptDist-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/formFPL/FPL_ptDist-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/formFPL/FPL_ptDist.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="text-align: center; margin-top: 8px;">Distribution of points from this analysis.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>So, overall, there is a 34% chance that a player will exceed their average points in a given GW. Note this doesn’t vary hugely depending on the player. For 2 examples: in 2018/19 Sterling exceeded his average 38% of the time, in 2017/18 Maguire exceeded his 37% of the time.</p> <p>Using this value as a basis, we can work out how this compares with the number of “above mean” weeks in weeks following one above the mean. E.g. the impact of form. If form exists we would expect there to be groupings of “above mean” weeks rather than them being random.</p> <p>To draw this conclusion we need to know what the statistically expected values would be. To calculate those we assume that the scores are distributed by a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binomial_distribution" target="\_blank">binomial distribution</a>.</p> <p>This is a distribution for calculating the number of successes (in this case above mean weeks) in a sequence of trials. Using a base rate of 34% (if we randomly pick a player and a GW there is a 34% chance that it is above the mean) we can compare stats with the actual data.</p> <p>First we look at “3 week form” that is, if a player scores above their mean in a given GW, what is the chance that they score above the mean <strong>at least once</strong> in the next 2 weeks?</p> <p>From the statistical distribution, we would expect there to be a 57% chance of this happening, and if we look at the cold hard numbers from the last 2 seasons then it happened 52% of the time. Pretty close!</p> <p>If we do the same for “4 week form” (following an above mean score the player posts another above mean score at least once in the next 3 weeks). The binomial distribution says that we should expect that 71% of the time, the data? 61%.</p> <p>“5 week form” stats says: 81%, our data: 72% and finally “6 wk form”, stats: 88%, data: 78%.</p> <p>So what conclusions can we draw from that? If a player scores above average (for that player) in a given GW, it has no impact on their expected returns in any of the following 5 weeks.</p> <p>Similarly if you look at something like the chance of “2 above mean weeks in 4”, or “3 above in 5” or any such combo, the same thing happens. The empirically calculated results are (very much) in line with the statistically expected values.</p> <h2 id="dare-i-conclude-there-is-no-such-thing-as-form-in-fpl">Dare I conclude: There is no such thing as form in FPL.</h2> <p>Clearly there are other short term factors which can impact a player, which keen FPL players should focus on. For example a short term injury to a key player could have a large impact on another (e.g. an injury to Kane might be a good time to bring in Moura/Son).</p> <p>Perhaps different positions or prices would experience it differently? Here is a plot showing that analysis. Values above the diagonal line are when we observe returns in the data more than expected (form).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/formFPL/pt_analysis-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/formFPL/pt_analysis-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/formFPL/pt_analysis-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/formFPL/pt_analysis.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Whilst this shows a number of values above the line (suggesting form) they are not statistically significant (when breaking it down by position and price there are far fewer data points) and there doesn’t seem to be any clear patterns.</p> <p>For example whilst forwards between 9-10M show a deviation between observed and expected (they experience form) the opposite is seen for forwards between 8-9M and 10M+.</p> <p>Overall, this extra bit of analysis helps to support the conclusion that there is no observable impact of form in FPL.</p> <p>For more discussion checkout either the original <a href="https://twitter.com/FPLHAL/status/1173356501328703488?s=20" target="\_blank">Twitter thread</a>, or the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/FantasyPL/comments/d4wtdc/theres_no_such_thing_as_player_form/" target="\_blank">Reddit comments</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><category term="football"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Does "form" impact player points in fantasy football?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unblock IP address from connecting via SSH</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Unblock_IP_on_Linux/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unblock IP address from connecting via SSH"/><published>2018-03-08T11:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-08T11:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Unblock_IP_on_Linux</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2018/Unblock_IP_on_Linux/"><![CDATA[<p>I manage a small cluster at work and occasionally students get their IP address banned by entering the wrong password when logging into the cluster. I don’t fix the problem often enough to remember how to do it, so I thought I’d jot it down here for future reference.</p> <p>The blocking of IPs is controlled by <a href="https://www.fail2ban.org/wiki/index.php/Main_Page" target="\_blank">Fail2ban</a>, which scans log files for IPs which look malicious (e.g. too many password failures, looking for exploits, etc.) and bans them. It does this by updating firewall rules to reject the specific IP.</p> <p>To see the list of what is being blocked run (in a terminal):</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>iptables <span class="nt">-L</span> <span class="nt">--line-numbers</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>That will give you something like:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Chain INPUT <span class="o">(</span>policy ACCEPT<span class="o">)</span>
num  target     prot opt <span class="nb">source               </span>destination
1    ACCEPT     udp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             udp xxx:xxxxxx
2    ACCEPT     tcp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             tcp xxx:xxxxxx
3    ACCEPT     udp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             udp xxx:xxxxxx
4    ACCEPT     tcp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             tcp xxx:xxxxxx
5    f2b-sshd   tcp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             multiport dports ssh
6    REJECT     tcp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             tcp spts:xxxxxx:xxxxxx dpt:ulistproc reject-with icmp-port-unreachable
7    REJECT     udp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             udp spts:xxxxxx:xxxxxx dpt:ulistproc reject-with icmp-port-unreachable
8    ACCEPT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere
9    ACCEPT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere
10   ACCEPT     tcp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             tcp xxx:xxxxxx state NEW
11   ACCEPT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             state RELATED,ESTABLISHED
12   ACCEPT     tcp  <span class="nt">--</span>  xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx/24   anywhere             tcp xxx:xxxxxx state NEW
13   ACCEPT     tcp  <span class="nt">--</span>  xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx/24   anywhere             tcp xxx:xxxxxx state NEW
14   REJECT     udp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             udp xxx:xxxxxx reject-with icmp-port-unreachable
15   REJECT     tcp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             tcp xxx:xxxxxx reject-with icmp-port-unreachable
16   REJECT     tcp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             tcp xxx:xxxxxx reject-with icmp-port-unreachable
17   REJECT     tcp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             tcp xxx:xxxxxx:0:1023 reject-with icmp-port-unreachable
18   REJECT     udp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             udp xxx:xxxxxx:0:1023 reject-with icmp-port-unreachable

Chain FORWARD <span class="o">(</span>policy DROP<span class="o">)</span>
num  target     prot opt <span class="nb">source               </span>destination
1    ACCEPT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx/24     ctstate RELATED,ESTABLISHED
2    ACCEPT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx/24   anywhere
3    ACCEPT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere
4    REJECT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             reject-with icmp-port-unreachable
5    REJECT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             reject-with icmp-port-unreachable
6    ACCEPT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             state RELATED,ESTABLISHED
7    ACCEPT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere

Chain OUTPUT <span class="o">(</span>policy ACCEPT<span class="o">)</span>
num  target     prot opt <span class="nb">source               </span>destination
1    ACCEPT     udp  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere             udp dpt:bootpc

Chain f2b-sshd <span class="o">(</span>1 references<span class="o">)</span>
num  target     prot opt <span class="nb">source               </span>destination
1    REJECT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx      anywhere             reject-with icmp-port-unreachable
2    REJECT     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  199.188.177.166      anywhere             reject-with icmp-port-unreachable
3    RETURN     all  <span class="nt">--</span>  anywhere             anywhere
</code></pre></div></div> <p>What we are interested in is the ‘Chain f2b-sshd’ part at the bottom of the list. Here we can see the (made up) IP address 199.188.177.166 is being banned (“REJECT”). That means that any user trying to SSH into the machine from that IP address will fail. If you have verified that that is the IP address you are expecting and know it is safe to unblock then we can delete the rule using the Chain name (f2b-sshd) and line number (2) using “iptables -D CHAIN LINE_NUMBER” so in this specific case:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>iptables <span class="nt">-D</span> f2b-sshd 2
</code></pre></div></div> <p>To make the change permanent you must save your changes:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>iptables-save
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="linux"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I manage a small cluster at work and occasionally students get their IP address banned by entering the wrong password when logging into the cluster. I don’t fix the problem often enough to remember how to do it, so I thought I’d jot it down here for future reference.]]></summary></entry></feed>