<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-02T21:12:39+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sean Elvidge</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Velocity Required for Loop-the-Loop</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/loop-the-loop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Velocity Required for Loop-the-Loop"/><published>2013-02-21T16:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-02-21T16:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/loop-the-loop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/loop-the-loop/"><![CDATA[<p>In this post we are going to work out (approximately) the minimum speed required to complete a loop-the-loop, we’ll do this via an energy argument. However, for ease, we are going to ignore friction! First we need to find the minimum speed required at the top of the loop.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/loop-the-loop-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/loop-the-loop-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/loop-the-loop-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/loop-the-loop.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>To get the minimum required speed to make the loop-the-loop, at the top of the loop we require the normal force (\(N\)) to be \(0\). Equating the forces at the top of the loop we have the weight of the car (\(mg\)) plus the normal force (\(N\)) equal to the centrifugal force (\(F\)), which is given by \(F=\frac{mv^2}{r}\) where \(r\) is the radius of the circle. Thus,</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} \frac{mv_t^2}{r} &amp;=&amp; N+mg, \\ \frac{v_t^2}{r} &amp;=&amp; g,\\ v_t^2 &amp;=&amp; gr,\\ v_t &amp;=&amp; \sqrt{gr}. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>Giving us a minimum velocity at the top of the loop, \(v_t\). We now proceed with the energy argument.</p> <p>The total energy at the top of the loop is equal to the potential energy at the top plus the kinetic energy at the top, respectively these are:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} PE_t &amp;=&amp; mgh = 2mgr,\\ KE_t &amp;=&amp; \frac{1}{2}mv_t^2 = \frac{1}{2}mgr. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>Thus the total energy at the top is:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} E_t &amp;=&amp; 2mgr+\frac{1}{2}mgr,\\ &amp;=&amp; \frac{5}{2}mgr. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>We now find the total energy at the bottom, since there is no potential energy, this is simply the kinetic energy,</p> \[E_b = \frac{1}{2}mv_b^2.\] <p>Where \(v_b\) is the speed we are looking for. With our assumptions, the energy at the top (\(E_t\)) equals the energy at the bottom (\(E_b\)) giving</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} E_b &amp;=&amp; E_t,\\ \frac{1}{2}mv_b^2 &amp;=&amp; \frac{5}{2}mgr,\\ mv_b^2 &amp;=&amp; 5mgr,\\ v_b^2 &amp;=&amp; 5gr,\\ v_b &amp;=&amp; \sqrt{5gr}. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>Thus we have found the speed required to complete a loop the loop of radius \(r\). For example, if the loop had a 4 metre diameter (2 metre radius) then the velocity required to complete the loop would be \(v = \sqrt{5\times g\times 2}=\sqrt{10g}\approx 9.9\).</p> <p>For convience we can approximate \(\sqrt{5gr}\) as:</p> \[\sqrt{5\times 9.81\times r}=\sqrt{49.05r}\approx 7\sqrt{r}.\]]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is the velocity required to complete a loop-the-loop]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s Snowing Outside</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/snowing-outside/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It’s Snowing Outside"/><published>2013-01-19T16:35:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-01-19T16:35:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/snowing-outside</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/snowing-outside/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m sitting in my office, at home, watching the snow falling outside and it got me thinking….</p> <p>As is well known, chemically, water is made from hydrogen and oxygen (H2O), specifically, each water molecule is made from two hydrogen atoms bonded with an oxygen atom. In this bonding there are two left over pairs of electrons, and the whole molecule creates a rough tetrahedron.</p> <p>“Luckily” (from the point of view of this post) when dealing with hexagonal ice (ice Ih) (i.e. natural ice /snow) we get a perfect tetrahedron (see here and here for more details of this), hence the six-fold symmetry in snowflakes.</p> <p>Now we know this, we can work out just how unique the snow outside is, or the ice in your cup (perhaps you’re reading this in a warmer climate!) is. How many possible ways are there to create a tetrahedral structure like hexagonal ice?</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/water_molecule-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/water_molecule-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/water_molecule-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/water_molecule.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>With a little bit of thinking, and twisting the above image in your head, hopefully you’ll agree with me that there are 6 ways of arranging the water molecule in the ‘ice tetrahedron’. However, not every one of these possibilities is possible. Read the Wikipedia page on hydrogen bonds and then you’ll see that in fact only \(\frac{3}{2}\)  possible orientations are allowed. That is, for a crystal of N molecules, there are \(\left(\frac{3}{2}\right)^N\) ways to arrange the molecules inside that crystal.</p> <p>So, let us consider a snowball, say of 3 cm radius. How many molecules are there in that much snow?</p> <p>There are a number of ways of arriving at the number of molecules, but I’m going to go for the way which came to me first (rather than perhaps the best / most elegant solution (not that I know what that is!)). I considered the snow as water (because I know the molar mass of water!), so for that we just need to know the density of snow. Not so easy, it depends on various factors; as you have no doubt experienced, new snow feels a lot less dense then snow that has been sitting around for a week. Typically the densities vary between 8% and 50% the density of water. Once the snow is on the ground it settles under its own weight to a density of around 30%. Since the snow that got me thinking about this is fairly new, we’ll go for a density of 20%. That means 30 cm of snow would make 6 cm of water.</p> <p>So our 3 cm radius snow ball has a volume of \(\approx 113\,cm^3\) which would be \(22.6\, cm^3\) of water. A cubic centimetre of water weights 1 grams so the water content of our snowball would weigh 22.6 g.</p> <p>The molar mass of water is \(18.01528\, g\cdot mol^{-1}\) so there is</p> \[22.6 \times\frac{1}{18.01528}\approx 1.25 \mbox{ moles}.\] <p>Multiplying this number by Avogadro’s number (\(6.02\times 10^{23}\)) yields the number of molecules in the snowball:</p> \[1.25 \times 6.02\times 10^{23} \approx 7.5\times 10^{23}.\] <p>That means the possible number of orientations of the water molecules is</p> \[\left(\frac{3}{2}\right)^{7.5\times 10^{23}} \approx 10^{10^{23}}.\] <p>So how big is that number? Well it is stupidly big. We estimate that there is something like \(10^{80}\) atoms in the universe which isn’t even close to that number. So it is safe to say that every snowball that has ever been made, or ever will be made by people all over the Earth for the rest of the history of this planet, will always have a unique arrangements of water molecules!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Investigating the number of unique snowballs]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Crawshaw Method (for Quadratics)</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/the-Crawshaw-method/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crawshaw Method (for Quadratics)"/><published>2012-05-01T20:49:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-05-01T20:49:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/the-Crawshaw-method</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/the-Crawshaw-method/"><![CDATA[<p>Something all High School students (and above) need to know is how to factorize quadratic equations. However I am amazed how few people know a decent (and easy) way of doing this!</p> <p>I’ll keep this as simple as possible, and just show you how to use the method.</p> <p>First we consider a simple case (and sadly this is where a lot of the problems arise from!), we want to factorize the quadratic equation,</p> \[x^2+5x+6.\] <p>Now, as far as I know, it is universally taught that to factorize this you have to “find” two numbers that times together to make \(+6\) (the constant term) and add to make \(+5\) (the linear term). This is pretty easy, we choose the numbers \(+2\) and \(+3\), and then we simply write down the answer,</p> \[x^2+5x+6=(x+2)(x+3).\] <p>Easy.</p> <p>The problem is when you arrive at a question like,</p> \[3x^2-7x-6.\] <p>If we proceed in the same way as we were `taught’ above we need to find two numbers which times together to make \(-6\) and add to make \(-7\). We then need to try and work out what on Earth to do with these numbers, the problem is, it is not in any way obvious and quite a lot of guess work, or at least trial and error, is required.  The answer we would be looking for was</p> \[3x^2-7x-6=(3x+2)(x-3).\] <p>I think what is clear is that we need a concise, dare I say easy, method to solve any quadratic equation.</p> <p>Let me introduce the <em>Crawshaw method</em>.</p> <p>We first will apply the method to the ‘easy’ quadratic formula (the method is identical for all quadratics), you only need to remember that \(x=1x\), only we don’t write the \(1\). So the quadratic to solve is \(x^2+5x+6\).</p> <p>The first step of the method tells us that we need to find two numbers which add together to make \(+5\) and times to make \(1\times 6=6\), that is, the coefficient of the quadratic term (\(1\)) multiplied by the constant term (\(6\)). These numbers are \(2\) and \(3\).</p> <p>The second step is to rewrite the linear term as a combination of the numbers we have just found. So for this question the linear term is \(+5x\) the numbers we found were \(2\) and \(3\) so we will replace \(+5x\) in the quadratic with \(+2x+3x\). So our quadratic is now:</p> \[x^2+2x+3x+6.\] <p>Which is of course the exact same equation but now we can continue with the method.</p> <p>We now draw an imaginary line down the middle of the equation:</p> \[x^2+2x\quad/\quad+3x+6.\] <p>Next we factorize the left hand side, getting:</p> \[x(x+2)\quad/\quad+3x+6.\] <p>We then need to factorize the right hand side, but making sure that the bracket terms are the same, i.e.</p> \[x(x+2)\quad/\quad+3(x+2).\] <p>Then finally we get our two brackets (for the factorized answer) as the one bracket we already have, and the two terms that are on the outside of the brackets (i.e. in this case \(x\) and \(+3\)). Thus our answer becomes</p> \[(x+2)(x+3).\] <p>This method does seem more difficult for this ‘easy’ equation (i.e. one where the coefficient of the quadratic term is \(1\)) but the beauty of the Crawshaw method is that it works exactly the same for all quadratic equations.</p> <p>Now let us consider the second equation, that is \(3x^2-7x-6\). We approach it in exactly the same way.</p> <p>First find two numbers which times together to make \(3\times -6 = -18\) (that is the coefficient of the quadratic term multiplied by the constant term) and add together to make \(-7\). Such numbers are \(-9\) and \(+2\). So we now rewrite the linear term with these numbers (i.e. replacing \(-7x=-9x+2x\)) so we get:</p> \[3x^2-9x+2x-6.\] <p>Now we draw an imaginary line down the middle and factorize both sides of the equation:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} 3x^2-9x \quad &amp;/&amp; \quad 2x-6,\\ 3x(x-3) \quad &amp;/&amp; \quad +2(x-3). \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>So we then have our factorized solution,</p> \[3x^2-7x-6=(3x+2)(x-3).\] <p>See, wasn’t that easier?</p> <p>I present to you, the Crawshaw method.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to solve quadratic equations using the Crawshaw method]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Short History of Nearly Everything - Some Corrections</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/a-short-history/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Short History of Nearly Everything - Some Corrections"/><published>2012-03-31T12:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-03-31T12:38:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/a-short-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/a-short-history/"><![CDATA[<p>I have just finished the book “A Short History of Nearly Everything” by Bill Bryson and I thought it was absolutely fantastic. There were a couple of mistakes that I noticed (and I am sure others that I did not - by ‘noticed’ I mean ‘didn’t believe the numbers and so checked them out’) that I thought I should correct. This post just provides a few scientific corrections, and is meant in <strong>no way as disrespect to what I believe to be a truly brilliant book</strong>.</p> <blockquote> <p>On a diagram of the solar system to scale, with Earth reduced to about the diameter of a pea, Jupiter would be over a thousand feet away and Pluto would be a mile and a half distant (and about the size of a bacterium, so you wouldn’t be able to see it anyway).</p> </blockquote> <p>Okay, assume that the radius of a pea is about \(4\) millimetres, or \(4 \times 10^{-3}\) metres. The mean radius of the Earth is \(6.371 \times 10^3\) metres, or the peas radius is \(\frac{1}{1592750000}\) of the Earth’s. We will use this fraction as the scale for the rest of the system. The distance between the Earth and Jupiter is \(5.808\) AU so on our scale that turns out to be \(1790\) feet. Pluto (which is \(32.15\) AU away) would be \(1.88\) miles away. So in this sense Bryson underestimated their distances (slightly). However, as for the size of Pluto, it has a mean radius of \(1.173 \times 10^6\) metres, so on our scale that would become \(7.4 \times 10^{-4}\) metres, i.e. a total diameter of 1.5 millimetres, very visible and about 75 times larger than a median bacterium!</p> <blockquote> <p>Protons are so small that a little dib of ink like the dot on this i can hold something in the region of 500,000,000,000 of them, rather more than the number of seconds contained in half a million years.</p> </blockquote> <p>I think the approximate size of a ‘dot’ is about \(0.5\) millimetres, so that means the area, in metres, of such a dot is: \(\pi\cdot 0.00025^2=1.963\times 10^{-7}\). The size of a proton is \(8.77 \times 10^{-16}\) metres, and so the number of protons that would fit in such a dot is \(223,887,732\). Or \(2233\) times less than the Bryson stated number. As for the number of seconds in half a million years: \(1 \mbox{ year } = 31556926 \mbox{ seconds}\) and \(500,000 \mbox{ years } = 15,800,000,000,000 \mbox{ seconds}\). Quite a lot more than what was stated, in fact, \(500,000,000,000\) seconds is only 15844 years.</p> <blockquote> <p>Even so, it [the Voyager spacecraft] took them nine years to reach Uranus and a dozen to cross the orbit of Pluto.</p> </blockquote> <p>Actually, Voyager 1 never got to Uranus nor cross the orbit of Pluto, only Voyager 2 did.</p> <blockquote> <p>[Betelgeuse is] fifty thousand light years away.</p> </blockquote> <p>Betelgeuse is around \(643 \pm 143\) light years away.</p> <blockquote> <p>It is thought that our entire planet may contain, at any given moment, fewer than twenty francium atoms.</p> </blockquote> <p>There is almost certainly a lot more than twenty francium atoms, according to <a href="https://perey.org/genealogy/MP%202.pdf">Adloff and Kauffman</a>, there is 550 grams in the Earth’s crust.</p> <blockquote> <p>It took thousands of workers to clear 1.8 billion tonnes of debris from the 6.5 hectares of the World Trade Center site.</p> </blockquote> <p>1.8 million tonnes.</p> <blockquote> <p>It rises exponentially, so that a 7.3 quake is fifty ties more powerful than a 6.3 earthquake and 2,500 time more powerful than a 5.3 earthquake.</p> </blockquote> <p>Exactly what the mistake is here depends slightly on what you interpret the word <em>powerful</em> means. The <em>size</em> of an earthquake increases by a factor of 10 as magnitude increases by one whole number. So a magnitude 7.3 earthquake is <strong>10 times</strong> larger than a 6.3, and <strong>100 times</strong> larger than 5.3. The amount of <em>energy released</em> increases by a factor of 31.6 \(\left(10^{1.5}\right)\). So a 7.3 earthquake releases roughly 32 times more energy than a magnitude 6.3; and about 1,000 times more energy than a 5.3.</p> <blockquote> <p>It has been calculated that if you sunk a well to the center [of the Earth] and dropped a brick into it, it would take only 45 minutes for it to hit the bottom.</p> </blockquote> <p>The terminal velocity of an object falling through the air is the maximum speed that the object will reach when the resistance of the medium through which it falls (in this case, air) prevents further acceleration. This velocity depends on various factors, including the mass and aerodynamic properties of the object (such as its shape and surface area), as well as the density of the air. For a brick, calculating its terminal velocity involves considering its drag coefficient, cross-sectional area perpendicular to the direction of motion, and mass. Using sensible estimates for this value we could calculate the terminal velocity of a house brick to be approximately 45 meters per second. Given that the Earth’s radius is approximately 6371 km, the brick would take about 39 hours to fall to the centre (given all the other difficulties with this thought experiment!).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some corrections in A Short History of Nearly Everything]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1 = 2</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/1-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1 = 2"/><published>2012-02-17T14:07:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-02-17T14:07:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/1-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/1-2/"><![CDATA[<p>Many people have seen “proofs” that \(1 = 2\). However there are always a rather obvious fallacy - a division by 0.</p> <p>A classic such example is:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} a &amp;=&amp; b, \\ a^2 &amp;=&amp; ab, \\ a^2 - b^2 &amp;=&amp; ab - b^2, \\ (a+b)(a-b) &amp;=&amp; b(a-b), \\ (a+b) &amp;=&amp; b, \\ a+a &amp;=&amp; a, \\ 2a &amp;=&amp; a, \\ 2 &amp;=&amp; 1. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>This is a decent “trick” to show people, but as I said above, the mistake simply comes from the division by 0 on the 5th line.</p> <p>However, here is a different “proof”, can you see the mistake?</p> <p>Consider the equation, \(2=x^{x^{x^{\ldots}}}\), with an infinite number of \(x\)’s. If we add some brackets to the equation we get, \(2=x^{\left(x^{x^{\ldots}}\right)}\) and then we can substitute the first equation in to get:</p> \[2=x^2.\] <p>So \(x=\sqrt{2}\), and hence</p> \[2=\sqrt{2}^{\sqrt{2}^{\sqrt{2}^{\ldots}}}.\] <p>Then if we repeat the exact same above process with the equation \(4=x^{x^{x^{\ldots}}}\) we see that \(4=x^4\) and so again \(x=\sqrt{2}\). So this time,</p> \[4=\sqrt{2}^{\sqrt{2}^{\sqrt{2}^{\ldots}}}.\] <p>And so \(2=4\) and thus \(1=2\)!</p> <p>Where is the mistake?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1 = 2]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sine Rule on a Sphere</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/sine-rule-on-a-sphere/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sine Rule on a Sphere"/><published>2012-01-04T15:35:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-01-04T15:35:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/sine-rule-on-a-sphere</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/sine-rule-on-a-sphere/"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of days ago I wrote about how to find the <a href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/cosine-rule-on-a-sphere/">cosine rule on a sphere</a>. In this post I’ll show you the sine rule on a sphere.</p> <p>Consider the following triangle on a sphere:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Law-of-haversines-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Law-of-haversines-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Law-of-haversines-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Law-of-haversines.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The cosine rule (on a sphere) is:</p> \[\cos(c)=\cos(a)\cos(b)+\sin(a)\sin(b)\cos(C).\] <p>The sine rule is then, where \(A\) is the angle at \(\textbf{w}\) (opposite side \(a\)) and \(B\) is the angle at \(\textbf{v}\) (opposite side \(b\)):</p> \[\frac{\sin(A)}{\sin(a)}=\frac{\sin(B)}{\sin(b)}=\frac{\sin(C)}{\sin(c)}.\] <p>The proof is a simply a rearranging exercise from the cosine rule, with the formula \(\cos^2(C)+\sin^2(C)=1\). You can find the proof below, but I do recommend having a go yourself.</p> <p>Rearrange \(\cos(c)=\cos(a)\cos(b)+\sin(a)\sin(b)\cos(C),\) to get:</p> \[\cos(C)=\frac{\cos(c)-\cos(a)\cos(b)}{\sin(a)\sin(b)}.\] <p>Now we use \(\sin^2(C)=1-\cos^2(C)\) substituting the above in for \(\cos^2(C)\):</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} \sin^2(C) &amp;=&amp; 1-\left(\frac{\cos(c)-\cos(a)\cos(b)}{\sin(a)\sin(b)}\right)^2,\\ \sin^2(C) &amp;=&amp; \frac{\sin^2(a)\sin^2(b)-(\cos(c)-\cos(a)\cos(b))^2}{\sin^2(a)\sin^2(b)}. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>Now again use \(\sin^2(C)=1-\cos^2(C)\) but for \(a\) and \(b\) to get:</p> \[\sin^2(C)=\frac{(1-\cos^2(a))(1-\cos^2(b))-(\cos(c)-\cos(a)\cos(b))^2}{\sin^2(a)\sin^2(b)}.\] <p>Times everything out and cancel to get:</p> \[\sin^2(C)=\frac{1-\cos^2(a)-\cos^2(b)-\cos^2(c)+2\cos(a)\cos(b)\cos(c)}{\sin^2(a)\sin^2(b)}.\] <p>Finally divide everything by \(\sin^2(c)\) to get the required form:</p> \[\frac{\sin^2(C)}{\sin^2(c)}=\frac{1-\cos^2(a)-\cos^2(b)-\cos^2(c)+2\cos(a)\cos(b)\cos(c)}{\sin^2(a)\sin^2(b)\sin^2(c)}.\] <p>Which is what we wanted, since the right hand side is symmetrical in \(a\), \(b\) and \(c\), i.e.</p> \[\frac{\sin^2(A)}{\sin^2(a)} = \frac{\sin^2(B)}{\sin^2(b)} = \frac{\sin^2(C)}{\sin^2(c)}.\] <p>But since our angle must be between \(0\) and \(\pi\), all the terms are positive, so we can take the square root to get the sine rule on a sphere:</p> \[\frac{\sin(A)}{\sin(a)}=\frac{\sin(B)}{\sin(b)}=\frac{\sin(C)}{\sin(c)}.\]]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to use the cosine rule on a sphere]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosine Rule on a Sphere</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/cosine-rule-on-a-sphere/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosine Rule on a Sphere"/><published>2012-01-02T14:43:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-01-02T14:43:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/cosine-rule-on-a-sphere</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/cosine-rule-on-a-sphere/"><![CDATA[<p>As all (well, at least those that can remember) 15+ year olds know, to find the length of a side of a non-right angled triangle you can’t use Pythagoras’ theorem and instead require the so called ‘Cosine Rule’.</p> <p>Simply, the cosine rule is used to find (for example) the length of side \(c\) in:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Triangle_with_notations_2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Triangle_with_notations_2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Triangle_with_notations_2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Triangle_with_notations_2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>You use the following formula:</p> \[c^2 = a^2 + b^2 - 2ab\cos(\gamma).\] <p>But what happens if we move away from Euclidean Geometry and that our triangle is now sitting on a sphere? I.e.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Law-of-haversines-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Law-of-haversines-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Law-of-haversines-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Law-of-haversines.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Logic tells us that of course the same cosine rule can not be applied to find the side \(c\). Instead we use an alternative formula, namely:</p> \[\cos(c)=\cos(a)\cos(b)+\sin(a)\sin(b)\cos(C).\] <p>The proof is relatively straight forward, try having a go before looking below:</p> <p>Let \(\textbf{u}\), \(\textbf{v}\) and \(\textbf{w}\) be unit vectors from the middle of the sphere to the points \(u\), \(v\) and \(w\) of our triangle. The lengths of the sides are then give by the dot product:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} \cos(a) &amp;=&amp; \textbf{u}\cdot\textbf{v},\\ \cos(b) &amp;=&amp; \textbf{u}\cdot\textbf{w},\\ \cos(c) &amp;=&amp; \textbf{v}\cdot\textbf{w}. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>The angle \(C\) is the inverse cosine of two tangents, say \(\textbf{t}_a\) and \(\textbf{t}_b\), which are along the sides \(a\) and \(b\), i.e.</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} C &amp;=&amp; \cos^{-1}(\textbf{t}_a\cdot\textbf{t}_b),\\ \cos(C) &amp;=&amp; \textbf{t}_a\cdot\textbf{t}_b. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>But we know more information about these tangent vectors. For instance we know that the they are perpendicular to \(\textbf{u}\) which is given by the component of \(\textbf{v}\) perpendiculat to \(\textbf{u}\).</p> <p>This gives (once normalized):</p> \[\textbf{t}_a=\frac{\textbf{v}-\textbf{u}(\textbf{u}\cdot\textbf{v})}{|\textbf{v}-\textbf{u}(\textbf{u}\cdot\textbf{v})|} = \frac{\textbf{v}-\textbf{u}\cos(a)}{\sin(a)}.\] <p>Similarly,</p> \[\textbf{t}_b=\frac{\textbf{w}-\textbf{u}(\textbf{u}\cdot\textbf{w})}{|\textbf{w}-\textbf{u}(\textbf{u}\cdot\textbf{w})|} = \frac{\textbf{w}-\textbf{u}\cos(b)}{\sin(b)}.\] <p>So substituting these values into the above equation we get:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} \cos(C) &amp;=&amp; \frac{\textbf{v}-\textbf{u}\cos(a)}{\sin(a)}\cdot \frac{\textbf{w}-\textbf{u}\cos(b)}{\sin(b)},\\ \cos(C) &amp;=&amp; \frac{\textbf{v}\cdot\textbf{w}-(\textbf{v}\cdot\textbf{u})\cos(b)-(\textbf{u}\cdot\textbf{w})\cos(a)+(\textbf{u}\cdot\textbf{u})\cos(a)\cos(b)}{\sin(a)\sin(b)},\\ \cos(C) &amp;=&amp; \frac{\cos(c)-\cos(a)\cos(b)}{\sin(a)\sin(b)}. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>Which when rearranged gives the required cosine rule:</p> \[\cos(c)=\cos(a)\cos(b)+\sin(a)\sin(b)\cos(C).\] <p>Follow this link if you want to see the <a href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/sine-rule-on-a-sphere/">sine rule on a sphere</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to use the cosine rule on a sphere]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Batch Process in Bash</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2011/batch-process-in-bash/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Batch Process in Bash"/><published>2011-03-18T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-03-18T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2011/batch-process-in-bash</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2011/batch-process-in-bash/"><![CDATA[<p>I am writing this at 0230 because Joe just asked me how to do it, hence someone else in the world might also want to do it. The task is to do something (the same something) to a large group of files in linux. For example convert a folder of wma files to mp3’s (for this example you will need to have ffmpeg installed). We add the condition that we want to keep the file names as they are, and just convert them.</p> <p>It is fairly simple, we will write a script to do this (although you could do it straight from the terminal), for this example we will write a script called <em>wma2mp3</em>:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>gedit wma2mp3
</code></pre></div></div> <p>(Obviously change gedit for your favourite editor). Now add to that:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">for </span>i <span class="k">in</span> <span class="k">*</span>.wma<span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">do
</span><span class="nv">filename</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">i</span><span class="p">%.*</span><span class="k">}</span>
ffmpeg <span class="nt">-i</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$filename</span><span class="s2">.wma"</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$filename</span><span class="s2">.mp3"</span>
<span class="k">done</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Then all you need to do is place that file in the folder where you want to run it, then run it, and then you’re done! Again this is just an example and you can modify this to anything you want. If you actually want to change wma’s to mp3’s there are a few more options you may want to use, but I thought this would be a better ‘template’.</p> <p>For one more example, say you want to convert all your ps files in a folder to pdf’s (here you will need to have ps2pdf installed) we would use:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">for </span>i <span class="k">in</span> <span class="k">*</span>.ps<span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">do
</span><span class="nv">filename</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">i</span><span class="p">%.*</span><span class="k">}</span>
ps2pdf <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$filename</span><span class="s2">.ps"</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$filename</span><span class="s2">.pdf"</span>
<span class="k">done</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Hope that helps!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="code"/><category term="bash"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to do the same process on a large number of files in Bash]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">God’s Number is 20</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2011/gods-number-is-20/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="God’s Number is 20"/><published>2011-02-15T23:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-02-15T23:25:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2011/gods-number-is-20</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2011/gods-number-is-20/"><![CDATA[<p>The Rubik Cube was invented by one Erno Rubik in 1974 and has gone one to be one of the most popular puzzles in the world, having sold over 350 million units worldwide, even though many people can not solve it! Although perhaps that isn’t overly surprising given the vast number of possible positions that the cube can take, some 43,252,003,274,489,856,000 (that is approximately 43 quintillion) with only 1 correct solution, i.e. if you want to solve it, randomly turning the cube almost certainly won’t get you there. To put that number in perspective, imagine 43 quintillion standard size (5.7cm) Rubik’s cubes stacked on top of each other. This would cover a distance of about 260 light years, or the distance from Earth to our next nearest star (i.e. Proxima Centauri, not the Sun) and back 30 times!</p> <p>But where does this number come from?</p> <p>A standard 3x3x3 Rubik’s cube has 8 corner pieces, 12 edge pieces and 6 centres. Since the centre pieces are fixed, there is nothing we can do to move them, so they do not enter our calculation to the number of possible positions. As there are 8 corner pieces we have \(8!\) (that is 8 factorial or \(8!=8 \times 7 \times 6 \times 5 \times 4 \times 3 \times 2 \times 1=40320\)) ways of positioning them, and we are free to place the first 7 where ever we want, however once these 7 are positioned, the 8th is clearly forced to be in a particular place, so we have \(3^7\) (\(3^7=2187\)) possibile positions for these \(8!\) options. The 3 arises since each corner piece has 3 colours on it. So far we have counted</p> \[8! \times 3^7 = 88179840.\] <p>Now, for the 12 edges, you may imagine that we have \(12!\) options, however we have to note that an odd permutation of corners results in an odd permutation of the edges, thus there are only \(\frac{12!}{2}\) options. Then in the same ways as the corners we count how many possible positions we can have, this time each piece only has 2 colours on it, but in a similar way once we have chosen where the first 11 go, the 12th piece is fixed, thus giving \(2^{11}\) options. So in total we have</p> \[8! \times 3^7 \times \frac{12!}{2} \times 2^{11} = 43,252,003,274,489,856,000\] <p>possible positions, which is what we wanted to show.</p> <p>Possibly one of the reason for the Rubik’s cube continued success is the fact that when you have solved it once, you want to mix it up and start again but this time do it quicker! This process just repeats and since 1981 there have been World Championships for ‘speedsolving’, plus a variety of other competitions. The current fastest recorded time of solving a Rubik’s cube is 6.65 seconds, solved by Feliks Zemdegs, a truly unbelievable feat. (Update: as of July 2023 the record is 3.13 seconds, achieved by Max Park). But should we care about Rubik’s cube? Are they just for fun? Well from a mathematical point of view, they are very interesting:</p> <p>For starters, Rubik’s cube are really very useful for examples and considering finite group theory, in fact the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Group_theory">Group Theory Wikipedia page</a> has a picture of a Rubik cube at the very start. <a href="http://geometer.org/">Tom Davis</a> has written a very good document on Group Theory via Rubik’s Cubes which if you are interested in such things I would recommend you <a href="http://geometer.org/rubik/group.pdf">check it out</a>. However the point of this blog post is actually to do with the question: ‘what is the maximum number of moves it takes to solve a Rubik’s cube’?</p> <p>The real quest is to find an algorithm which will solve any Rubik cube in the minimum number of moves, this is called ‘God’s Algorithm’. The number of moves that this algorithm takes, in the worst case, is called ‘God’s Number’. The first work on this was done in 1980s and in 1981 Thistlethwaite proved that God’s number must be greater than or equal to 18 and less than or equal to 52. Over time these bounds were tightened, and it was in 1995 that the lower bound was first proved to be 20, this was done by Michael Reid (he had previously shown that the upper bound is less than or equal to 29). In the late 2000s Tomas Rokicki did some great work on tightening the upper bounds, culminating in this paper showing the upper bound to be less than or equal to 22.</p> <p>But, given the title of this blog, I hope you have worked out that the upper bound has since be refined to 20, that is both the lower bound and upper bound are 20, thus God’s Number is 20! And who is to thank for this? Well it is thanks to Morley Davidson, John Dethridge, Herbert Kociemba and Tomas Rokicki, not to mention Google, who donated idle computer time. They completed the solution to the problem, by first writing a computer program that could solve the position of any Rubik’s cube in about 20 seconds (not necessarily an optimal solution, but one that took less than 20 moves), and reduced the number of cases they actually needed to solve, via a variety of methods, including considering symmetry, this reduced the number of possible considerations to 55,882,296. To check this number of possibilities would have taken approximately 35 years with a high end computer, and this is where Google came in. The job was spread across a number of computers at Google which then completed the task in a few weeks. Proving that in fact every possible Rubik’s cube position can be solved in 20 moves or less! So ‘God’s Number’ is 20, quite a remarkable fact.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You never need more than 20 moves to solve a Rubik cube]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hilbert’s Hotel</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2010/HilbertHotel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hilbert’s Hotel"/><published>2010-08-26T22:47:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-08-26T22:47:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2010/HilbertHotel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2010/HilbertHotel/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Hilbert">David Hilbert</a> was a greatly influential mathematician born in 1862. He worked in a variety of areas including infinite sets and it is in this area that he presented his ‘Hotel’, or his ‘paradox of the Grand Hotel’. Which helps the reader consider the infinite., so lets give it a go:</p> <p>Consider a hotel with a <em>countably infinite</em> number of rooms. Countably infinite is a set which has the same number of elements (cardinality) of the set of natural numbers (the counting numbers: 0, 1, 2, 3, …, there is no fixed decision on whether 0 is a natural number or not, it isn’t important here but I thought I would mention it). Now consider that all of the rooms in the hotel are currently occupied, you may think that the manager should put up a ‘No Vacancy’ sign, but perhaps not…</p> <p>Suppose that a guest turns up looking for a room. What should the manager say? Well that is easy, he gets every guest already in the hotel to move up one room. So the person in room 1 should move to room 2, the person in room 2 moves to room 3 etc. etc. We know this can continue since there is an infinite number of rooms in the hotel. So then we get that room 1 is empty, and we can put the guest in that room. This same method will work for any finite number of guests that show up at the hotel!</p> <p>Now how about if countably infinite number of people turn up asking for a room in the hotel. Can we fit infinitely more people into the hotel? Once again the manager has no problems, he asks the guests to move rooms. He asks the person in room 1 to move to room 2, the person in room 2 to room 4, the person in room 3 to room 6 and in general the person in room \(n\) to \(2n\). Again we can do this because there is an infinite number of rooms in the hotel! Now \(2n\) is always even, so all the odd numbered rooms are free, and the number of odd numbers is the same as the number of natural numbers, so there are countably infinite spaces. The fact that the odd numbers and natural numbers have the same cardinality itself is counter-intuitive, but hopefully I can convince you that it is true very quickly:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} 1 &amp;\longrightarrow &amp; 1 \\ 3 &amp;\longrightarrow &amp; 2 \\ 5 &amp;\longrightarrow &amp; 3 \\ 7 &amp;\longrightarrow &amp; 4 \\ 9 &amp;\longrightarrow &amp; 5 \\ 11 &amp;\longrightarrow &amp; 6 \\ \vdots &amp;\longrightarrow &amp; \vdots \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>So there is a clear mapping between the natural numbers and the odd numbers. Hence the infinite number of guests can fit in the hotel.</p> <p>The final case to consider, what if a countably infinite number of coaches turn up, each with a countably infinite number of passengers. Is there room for all of them in the hotel? You’ve guessed it, there is! As long as the seats on the coaches are numbered (we can avoid this condition if we can use the beast which is the ‘<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Axiom_of_choice">Axiom of Choice</a>’) we can find everyone a room. First we want to empty all of the odd rooms again, we do this the same as above, move everyone in room \(n\) to room \(2n\). Now take the 1st coach, say the seats are numbered \(1, 2, 3, \ldots\) then we can place the person in coach 1, seat 1 in room \(3^1\), seat 2 in room \(3^2\), seat 3 in room \(3^3\) etc. etc. Now for coach 2, again with seats numbered \(1, 2, 3, \ldots\) we place the person in seat 1 in room \(5^1\), seat 2 to room \(5^2\) etc. etc. So in general for coach \(i\) and the person in seat \(n\) we can place them in room \(p^n\) where \(p\) is \(i+1\)th prime number, and there we have it! We have taken our hotel, with a countably infinite number of rooms, each of which is occupied, and managed to find space for an infinite number of coaches, each with an infinite number of passengers.</p> <p>This is a great concept to test your understanding of infinity. The reason that this all works is because in a hotel with infinitely many rooms the statements ‘every room is occupied’ and ‘no more guests can stay in the hotel’ are not the same.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Use Hilbert's hotel to rethink about infinity]]></summary></entry></feed>