<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-05-16T09:45:51+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sean Elvidge</title><entry><title type="html">Pour Over Brewing Recipe Generator</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2025/Pour_over_brewing_recipe_generator/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pour Over Brewing Recipe Generator"/><published>2025-03-31T18:41:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-31T18:41:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2025/Pour_over_brewing_recipe_generator</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2025/Pour_over_brewing_recipe_generator/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently purchased a <a href="https://amzn.to/4j7ni2U">Fellow Aiden Precision Coffee Maker</a> which is a pour over coffee brewer. Able to brew individual cups to whole batches this machine is fantastic, and gives you complete control of the recipe it uses. From the bloom time and temperature to the number of pulses and the ability to control the temperature of each individual pulse.</p> <p>There are a number of default reciepes included and through the <a href="https://fellowproducts.com/pages/fellow-drops">Fellow Drops</a> programme you can get a number of tuned recipes for those coffees. Whilst, at the end of the day, coffee all coems down to personal preference, and any provided reciepe will need fine tuning, there are some fundamentals which provide a good starting point. To try and capture that information I have made the following recipe generator:</p> <p><a href="https://seanelvidge.com/brewcoffee">seanelvidge.com/brewcoffee</a></p> <p>If you visit that page, with the details of the coffee bean you have, you can have a look at what the reciepe generator says you should use. If you would like (a lot) more detail of the decisions that I have made to create the generator then read on.</p> <h1 id="roast-level-adjustments">Roast Level Adjustments</h1> <p>Roast level significantly influences extraction dynamics. Light roasts, dense and less porous, require extended blooming (initial wetting) and multiple pulses of hot water at precise intervals to fully unlock their flavors. Consequently, the recipe defaults for light roasts feature higher bloom ratios and longer bloom times, ensuring sufficient CO₂ release for consistent extraction.</p> <p>Conversely, dark roasts, due to their brittleness and faster extraction tendency, need lower extraction ratios and fewer pulses to avoid bitterness. The recipe parameters for darker roasts emphasize shorter bloom times and higher initial bloom temperatures to develop complexity without over-extraction.</p> <h3 id="specifics">Specifics</h3> <p>Light Roast:</p> <ul> <li>Brew Ratio: Increased to 17 for lighter body.</li> <li>Bloom Ratio: Increased to 3.5 to aid degassing.</li> <li>Bloom Time: Extended to 60 seconds for thorough extraction.</li> <li>Pulse Count: Increased to 6, ensuring complete flavor extraction.</li> </ul> <p>Dark Roast:</p> <ul> <li>Brew Ratio: Reduced to 15 to intensify body and reduce bitterness.</li> <li>Bloom Ratio: Decreased to 1.5 due to easier extraction.</li> <li>Bloom Time: Shortened to 40 seconds to prevent over-extraction.</li> <li>Pulse Count: Reduced to 3, limiting extraction bitterness.</li> </ul> <h1 id="bean-origin-influence">Bean Origin Influence</h1> <p>Beans from different regions exhibit unique physical traits influencing their extraction behavior. East African coffees, typically denser with higher solubility, require gentler bloom phases—lower ratios, shorter times, and reduced temperatures—to mitigate over-extraction and accentuate their bright, vibrant acidity.</p> <p>Latin American coffees often demand a longer bloom and higher temperatures to thoroughly degas and enhance sweetness and body. Indonesian coffees, known for their robust character, are best extracted with moderate bloom parameters that balance intensity with clarity.</p> <h3 id="specifics-1">Specifics</h3> <p>East African (Ethiopia, Kenya, etc.):</p> <ul> <li>Bloom Ratio: Decreased by 0.5 to minimize over-extraction.</li> <li>Bloom Time: Shortened by 5 seconds.</li> <li>Bloom Temperature: Reduced by 3°C.</li> <li>Pulse Count: Decreased by 1 to control acidity.</li> </ul> <p>Latin American (Brazil, Colombia, Guatemala):</p> <ul> <li>Bloom Ratio: Increased by 0.5 for effective degassing.</li> <li>Bloom Time: Increased by 5 seconds.</li> <li>Bloom Temperature: Raised by 3°C.</li> <li>Pulse Count: Increased by 1 to promote even extraction.</li> </ul> <p>Indonesian (Sumatra, Java):</p> <ul> <li>Bloom Ratio set to 2.5, Bloom Time standardized at 50 seconds.</li> <li>Pulse Count: Increased by 1 to maximize extraction clarity.</li> </ul> <h1 id="altitude-considerations">Altitude Considerations</h1> <p>High-altitude coffees, denser due to slower maturation, need more aggressive extraction parameters—finer grind, stronger brew ratios, and longer bloom durations—to achieve optimal flavor development. In contrast, lower-altitude beans benefit from coarser grinds and gentler extraction processes to preserve balance and avoid bitterness.</p> <h3 id="specifics-2">Specifics</h3> <p>High Altitude (&gt;1500m):</p> <ul> <li>Brew Ratio: Reduced by 0.5 for stronger extraction.</li> <li>Bloom Ratio: Increased by 0.5 to assist degassing.</li> <li>Bloom Time: Increased by 5 seconds.</li> <li>Grind Size: Finer by 2 increments.</li> </ul> <p>Low Altitude (&lt;1200m):</p> <ul> <li>Brew Ratio: Increased by 0.5 for gentler extraction.</li> <li>Bloom Ratio: Decreased by 0.5.</li> <li>Bloom Time: Reduced by 5 seconds.</li> <li>Grind Size: Coarser by 2 increments.</li> </ul> <h1 id="processing-method-adjustments">Processing Method Adjustments</h1> <p>Processing significantly impacts bean composition. Natural, honey, and anaerobic coffees, rich in sugars, require longer bloom periods and additional pulses to evenly extract these complex flavors. Washed coffees, typically cleaner and less dense, are best brewed with shorter blooms and fewer pulses, maintaining clarity and brightness.</p> <h3 id="specifics-3">Specifics</h3> <p>Natural, Honey, Carbonic, Anaerobic:</p> <ul> <li>Bloom Ratio: Increased by 0.5 (minimum of 2.5).</li> <li>Bloom Time: Extended by 5 seconds (minimum of 45 seconds).</li> <li>Pulse Count: Increased by 1 to control extraction consistency.</li> </ul> <p>Washed, Double Fermentation, Wet-Hulled:</p> <ul> <li>Bloom Ratio: Decreased by 0.5.</li> <li>Bloom Time: Reduced by 5 seconds.</li> <li>Pulse Count: Decreased by 1.</li> </ul> <h1 id="freshness-factor">Freshness Factor</h1> <p>The age of roasted coffee profoundly affects extraction due to CO₂ levels. Freshly roasted beans (0-7 days) release considerable CO₂, necessitating increased bloom water ratios, longer bloom times, and finer grinds to ensure thorough extraction without bitterness. Conversely, older beans (&gt;20 days) benefit from shorter blooms, lower temperatures, and coarser grinds to avoid over-extraction and maintain desirable flavors.</p> <h3 id="specifics-4">Specifics</h3> <p>Fresh Coffee (0–7 days):</p> <ul> <li>Bloom Ratio: Increased by 0.5.</li> <li>Bloom Time: Extended by 5 seconds.</li> <li>Grind Size: Finer by 4 increments.</li> <li>Pulse temperatures decreased by 1°C per pulse to counter CO₂ resistance.</li> </ul> <p>Older Coffee (&gt;20 days):</p> <ul> <li>Bloom Ratio: Decreased by 0.5.</li> <li>Bloom Time: Reduced by 5 seconds.</li> <li>Grind Size: Coarser by 4 increments.</li> <li>Pulse temperatures increased by 1°C per pulse to improve extraction.</li> </ul> <h1 id="flavor-profile-targeting">Flavor Profile Targeting</h1> <p>Achieving specific tasting notes requires fine-tuning extraction parameters:</p> <ul> <li>Fruity and acidic notes: Higher temperatures and finer grinds enhance bright flavors.</li> <li>Nutty and chocolatey notes: Richer bodies are cultivated through lower brew ratios and coarser grinds.</li> <li>Floral and herbal notes: Delicate aromatics emerge clearly with increased bloom ratios.</li> <li>Sweet and heavy notes: Lower bloom ratios preserve syrupy, sweet profiles.</li> <li>Creamy textures: Lower temperatures ensure smooth, rounded mouthfeels.</li> </ul> <h3 id="specifics-5">Specifics</h3> <p>Fruity/Acidic Notes:</p> <ul> <li>Brew Ratio: Increased by 0.5 for brightness.</li> <li>Bloom Temperature: Raised by 2°C.</li> <li>Grind Size: Finer by 4 increments.</li> </ul> <p>Nutty/Chocolate Notes:</p> <ul> <li>Brew Ratio: Decreased by 0.5 for richer body.</li> <li>Grind Size: Coarser by 2 increments.</li> </ul> <p>Floral/Herbal Notes:</p> <ul> <li>Bloom Ratio: Increased by 0.5 for aromatic extraction.</li> <li>Grind Size: Coarser by 2 increments.</li> </ul> <p>Heavy Sweet Notes:</p> <ul> <li>Bloom Ratio: Reduced by 0.5 for syrupy texture.</li> <li>Grind Size: Finer by 2 increments.</li> </ul> <p>Creamy Notes:</p> <ul> <li>Bloom Temperature: Reduced by 2°C to preserve smoothness.</li> </ul> <h1 id="pulse-temperature-profiles">Pulse Temperature Profiles</h1> <p>Dynamic pulse temperatures optimize extraction across roast levels:</p> <ul> <li>Light roasts gradually increase temperature across pulses, enhancing complexity.</li> <li>Medium roasts maintain stable temperatures for balanced extraction.</li> <li>Dark roasts reduce temperatures progressively to avoid bitterness, enhancing depth.</li> </ul> <p>Final pulse temperatures further adjust to emphasize specific tasting notes—higher initial temperatures highlight bright, fruity notes, while lower final temperatures preserve sweetness and depth.</p> <h3 id="specifics-6">Specifics</h3> <p>Light Roasts: Gradually increase temperature from 90°C to 96°C.</p> <p>Medium Roasts: Maintain stable bloom temperature; adjust slightly for anaerobic or carbonic processes.</p> <p>Dark Roasts: Decrease temperature progressively from 91°C to 85°C to minimize bitterness.</p> <h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1> <p>The <a href="https://amzn.to/4j7ni2U">Fellow Aiden Precision Coffee Maker</a> is a great coffee brewer, giving you almost complete control of the brewing process. You can access the recipe generator here:</p> <p><a href="https://seanelvidge.com/brewcoffee">seanelvidge.com/brewcoffee</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="misc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Generate pour over brewing coffee reciepes for a given bean]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Waning Home Advantage in English League Football</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2025/Home_advantage_in_English_football/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waning Home Advantage in English League Football"/><published>2025-01-13T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-13T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2025/Home_advantage_in_English_football</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2025/Home_advantage_in_English_football/"><![CDATA[<p>For generations, “home advantage” has been a tenet of sports. The roar of the crowd, the familiarity of the pitch, the comfort of the home dressing room – all give the home team an edge. This is particularly true in English football. However, a look at the data spanning over a century of English football reveals an interesting trend: the home advantage is shrinking.</p> <p>Using my database of all English league results since 1888 (available <a href="https://github.com/seanelvidge/England-football-results">here</a>, and described <a href="https://seanelvidge.com/articles/2024/All_England_football_league_results/">here</a>) we can track the Home Win %, Draw %, and Away Win % from 1888 to the present day (at the time of writing, that is halfway through the 2024/2025 season, but the charts in this post should automatically update). The results are pretty clear:</p> <html> <div class="chart-container"> <canvas id="resultsChart"></canvas> </div> <img id="fallbackImage1" src="assets/img/home_advantage_trend_fallback.png" alt="Fallback image for home, draw, away % win" style="display: none; max-width: 100%;"/> <style>.chart-container{position:relative;width:100%;min-height:250px;height:50vh;max-height:80vh}</style> </html> <p>In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, home teams were dominant, boasting win percentages well above 60%. Away wins were a relative rarity, hovering around 20%. But as the decades have progressed, the lines have converged. Home win percentages have steadily declined, dipping towards 40% in recent years, while away wins have climbed, now consistently above 30% and with a clear upwards trajectory.</p> <p>It would be easy to assume that this trend is confined to the top tier of English football, where the largest investments in training facilities, player recruitment, and tactical analysis occur. However, if we look at the home win percentages across all four tiers of English football (where “Tier 1” is the highest tier, currently the Premier League and “Tier 4” is the lowest, EFL League Two) we can see that this is a league-wide phenomenon.</p> <html> <div class="chart-container"> <canvas id="divisionChart"></canvas> </div> <img id="fallbackImage2" src="assets/img/home_advantage_trend_fallback_by_division.png" alt="Fallback image for home win % by division" style="display: none; max-width: 100%;"/> </html> <p>As you can see, the decline in home win percentages is remarkably consistent across all levels of professional English football. While there are some minor variations between divisions, the overall trajectory is the same: downwards. This suggests that the factors driving the change are not unique to the top tier but are systemic throughout the entire football pyramid. Each division shows high home win % at the start of the time series (above 50%), but each division ends up closer to 40% by the end of the series.</p> <p>So, what’s driving this shift away from home dominance? Several factors are likely at play:</p> <ul> <li>Standardization of Playing Conditions: In the early days, pitch conditions varied wildly. Home teams were intimately familiar with their own, often quirky, pitches, giving them a distinct advantage. Over time, regulations and advancements in groundskeeping have led to more standardized, high-quality pitches across the league, leveling the playing field. This impact would be felt across all divisions.</li> <li>Improved Travel and Accommodation: Early football often involved arduous journeys for away teams, leaving them fatigued and less prepared. Modern transportation and improved accommodations have minimized the physical toll of travel, allowing away teams to arrive rested and ready to compete. Again, this is relevant to all levels of the game.</li> <li>Tactical Advancements and Analysis: The modern game is far more tactically sophisticated. Managers and analysts have access to vast amounts of data and video footage, allowing them to dissect opponents’ strengths and weaknesses, regardless of location. Away teams can now better prepare for the specific challenges posed by their opponents and their home stadiums. While the resources may be greater at the top, these advancements have filtered down through the divisions.</li> <li>Professionalization and Fitness: Players today are fitter, faster, and more technically skilled than ever before. This overall increase in athleticism can help away teams better cope with the pressures of playing in hostile environments, a trend seen across the footballing spectrum.</li> </ul> <h2 id="the-future-of-home-advantage">The Future of Home Advantage</h2> <p>Whilst home advantage may not be what it once was, it hasn’t disappeared entirely. The support of the home crowd can still provide a boost, and familiarity with the surroundings can offer a slight edge. However, the trend is undeniable. The gap between home and away performance is narrowing, and the English Football League, across all its divisions, is becoming increasingly competitive on all fronts.</p> <p>If we look to extrapolate the trends in the data we can try and estimate what will happen in the future, fitting lines of best fit to the data we can estimate that home advantage will stick around for quite a while yet!</p> <div class="chart-container"> <canvas id="finalTrendChart"></canvas> </div> <html> <script src="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/papaparse@5.3.0/papaparse.min.js"></script> <script src="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/chart.js"></script> <script src="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/chartjs-plugin-zoom"></script> <script>function showFallbackImages(){document.getElementById("resultsChart").style.display="none",document.getElementById("divisionChart").style.display="none",document.getElementById("fallbackImage1").style.display="block",document.getElementById("fallbackImage2").style.display="block"}function processData(t){const e={},a={};t.forEach(t=>{if(!t.Season||!t.Result)return;const o=t.Season,s=t.Tier,n=t.Result;e[o]||(e[o]={H:0,D:0,A:0,total:0}),e[o][n]++,e[o].total++,a[o]||(a[o]={}),s&&!a[o][s]&&(a[o][s]={H:0,D:0,A:0,total:0}),s&&(a[o][s][n]++,a[o][s].total++)});const o=Object.keys(e).sort().pop(),s=calculatePercentages(e,o),n=calculateDivisionPercentages(a);createResultsChart(s),createDivisionChart(n),createFinalTrendChart(s)}function calculatePercentages(t,e){const a=Object.keys(t).sort(),o=[],s=[],n=[],l=[],r=[],i=[],c=[];return a.forEach(a=>{const d=t[a],u=d.total,p=parseFloat((d.H/u*100).toFixed(2)),h=parseFloat((d.D/u*100).toFixed(2)),b=parseFloat((d.A/u*100).toFixed(2)),g=calculateStandardDeviation(d.H,u),f=calculateStandardDeviation(d.D,u),C=calculateStandardDeviation(d.A,u);a&&a<=e&&(c.push(a),o.push(p),s.push(h),n.push(b),l.push(g),r.push(f),i.push(C))}),{labels:c,datasets:[{label:"Home Win %",data:o,borderColor:"blue",backgroundColor:"transparent"},{label:"Draw %",data:s,borderColor:"green",backgroundColor:"transparent"},{label:"Away Win %",data:n,borderColor:"red",backgroundColor:"transparent"}]}}function calculateDivisionPercentages(t){const e=Object.keys(t).sort(),a={};return e.forEach(e=>{Object.keys(t[e]).forEach(o=>{if(o&&!a[o]){let t;t="1"===o?"red":"2"===o?"blue":"3"===o?"green":"4"===o?"purple":getRandomColor(),a[o]={label:`Division ${o}`,data:[],borderColor:t,backgroundColor:"transparent",errorBars:[]}}if(o){const s=t[e][o],n=s.total,l=parseFloat((s.H/n*100).toFixed(2));parseFloat((s.D/n*100).toFixed(2)),parseFloat((s.A/n*100).toFixed(2));a[o].data.push({x:e,y:l}),a[o].errorBars.push(calculateStandardDeviation(s.H,n))}})}),{labels:e,datasets:Object.values(a)}}function getRandomColor(){const t="0123456789ABCDEF";let e="#";for(let a=0;a<6;a++)e+=t[Math.floor(16*Math.random())];return e}function calculateStandardDeviation(t,e){const a=t/e;return 100*Math.sqrt(a*(1-a)/e)}function createResultsChart(t){const e=document.getElementById("resultsChart").getContext("2d");resultsChart=new Chart(e,{type:"line",data:t,options:{maintainAspectRatio:!1,plugins:{legend:{labels:{usePointStyle:!0}},zoom:{zoom:{wheel:{enabled:!1},pinch:{enabled:!0},mode:"xy"}},tooltip:{callbacks:{label:function(t){let e=t.dataset.label||"";return e&&(e+=": "),e+=Number(t.parsed.y).toFixed(1)+"%"},footer:function(t){t[0].dataset}}}},scales:{y:{beginAtZero:!0,title:{display:!0,text:"Percentage",font:{size:16}},ticks:{font:{size:14}}},x:{ticks:{callback:function(t){const e=this.getLabelForValue(t);if(e.endsWith("5")||e.endsWith("0"))return e.substring(0,4)},font:{size:14}},title:{display:!0,text:"Season",font:{size:16}}}}}})}function createDivisionChart(t){const e=document.getElementById("divisionChart").getContext("2d");divisionChart=new Chart(e,{type:"line",data:t,options:{maintainAspectRatio:!1,plugins:{legend:{labels:{usePointStyle:!0}},zoom:{zoom:{wheel:{enabled:!1},pinch:{enabled:!0},mode:"xy"}},tooltip:{callbacks:{label:function(t){let e=t.dataset.label||"";return e&&(e+=": "),e+=Number(t.parsed.y).toFixed(1)+"%"},footer:function(t){return`\xb1${t[0].dataset.errorBars[t[0].dataIndex].toFixed(2)}%`}}},title:{display:!0,text:"% Home Wins per Division"}},scales:{y:{beginAtZero:!0,title:{display:!0,text:"Percentage",font:{size:16}},ticks:{font:{size:14}}},x:{ticks:{callback:function(t){const e=this.getLabelForValue(t);if(e.endsWith("5")||e.endsWith("0"))return e.substring(0,4)},font:{size:14}},title:{display:!0,text:"Season",font:{size:16}}}}}})}function updateChartTheme(t){const e=t?"#242424":"#FFFFFF",a=t?"#FFFFFF":"#000000";resultsChart.options.plugins.legend.labels.color=a,resultsChart.options.scales.x.title.color=a,resultsChart.options.scales.x.ticks.color=a,resultsChart.options.scales.y.title.color=a,resultsChart.options.scales.y.ticks.color=a,resultsChart.options.backgroundColor=e,resultsChart.update(),divisionChart.options.plugins.legend.labels.color=a,divisionChart.options.scales.x.title.color=a,divisionChart.options.scales.x.ticks.color=a,divisionChart.options.scales.y.title.color=a,divisionChart.options.scales.y.ticks.color=a,divisionChart.options.backgroundColor=e,divisionChart.update()}const resultsUrl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/seanelvidge/England-football-results/main/EnglandLeagueResults.csv";let resultsChart,divisionChart;Papa.parse(resultsUrl,{download:!0,header:!0,dynamicTyping:!0,skipEmptyLines:!0,complete:function(t){if(!t||!t.data||0===t.data.length)return console.warn("No valid data returned. Showing fallback images."),void showFallbackImages();if(t.errors&&t.errors.length>0)return console.warn("Papa Parse encountered errors. Showing fallback images:",t.errors),void showFallbackImages();processData(t.data)},error:function(t){console.error("Error loading remote data",t),showFallbackImages()}});</script> <script>function linearRegression(e,t){const a=e.length;let r=0,n=0,l=0,o=0;for(let s=0;s<a;s++)r+=e[s],n+=t[s],l+=e[s]*t[s],o+=e[s]*e[s];const s=(a*l-r*n)/(a*o-r*r);return{slope:s,intercept:(n-s*r)/a}}function createFinalTrendChart(e){function t(e,t){const a=parseInt(e.substring(0,4),10)+t;return`${a}-${a+1}`}const a=e.labels,r=a.map((e,t)=>t),n=e.datasets[0].data,l=e.datasets[1].data,o=e.datasets[2].data,s=linearRegression(r,n),d=linearRegression(r,l),i=linearRegression(r,o),c=r[r.length-1],b=[];for(let e=0;e<=c+50;e++)b.push(e);const u=b.map(e=>{if(e<=c)return a[e];{const r=e-c;return t(a[c],r)}}),p=[],g=[],h=[];for(let e=0;e<b.length;e++){const t=b[e],a=s.slope*t+s.intercept,r=d.slope*t+d.intercept,n=i.slope*t+i.intercept,l=a+r+n,o=a/l*100,c=r/l*100,u=n/l*100;p.push(o),g.push(c),h.push(u)}const f={labels:u,datasets:[{label:"Home Win %",data:e.datasets[0].data.concat(Array(b.length-r.length).fill(null)),borderColor:"blue",backgroundColor:"transparent"},{label:"Draw %",data:e.datasets[1].data.concat(Array(b.length-r.length).fill(null)),borderColor:"green",backgroundColor:"transparent"},{label:"Away Win %",data:e.datasets[2].data.concat(Array(b.length-r.length).fill(null)),borderColor:"red",backgroundColor:"transparent"},{label:"Home Trend (Normalized)",data:p,borderColor:"blue",backgroundColor:"transparent",borderDash:[5,5],pointRadius:0},{label:"Draw Trend (Normalized)",data:g,borderColor:"green",backgroundColor:"transparent",borderDash:[5,5],pointRadius:0},{label:"Away Trend (Normalized)",data:h,borderColor:"red",backgroundColor:"transparent",borderDash:[5,5],pointRadius:0}]},C=document.getElementById("finalTrendChart").getContext("2d");finalTrendChart=new Chart(C,{type:"line",data:f,options:{maintainAspectRatio:!1,scales:{y:{beginAtZero:!0,title:{display:!0,text:"Percentage",font:{size:16}},ticks:{font:{size:14}}},x:{ticks:{font:{size:14},callback:function(e,t){return t%5==0?this.getLabelForValue(e):""}},title:{display:!0,text:"Season",font:{size:16}}}},plugins:{title:{display:!1,text:"Home/Draw/Away % with Normalized Trend to 100%"},tooltip:{callbacks:{label:function(e){let t=e.dataset.label||"";return t&&(t+=": "),t+=Number(e.parsed.y).toFixed(1)+"%"}}},legend:{labels:{usePointStyle:!0}},zoom:{zoom:{wheel:{enabled:!1},pinch:{enabled:!0},mode:"xy"}}}}})}let finalTrendChart;</script> </html>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="football"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An investigation in the trend of home advantage in English football]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Brewing the Perfect Coffee at Altitude</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2025/Brewing_coffee_at_altitude/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brewing the Perfect Coffee at Altitude"/><published>2025-01-09T17:06:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-09T17:06:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2025/Brewing_coffee_at_altitude</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2025/Brewing_coffee_at_altitude/"><![CDATA[<p>For those of us who consider coffee an essential part of our daily routine, the pursuit of the perfect cup is a never-ending quest. But did you know that your altitude can significantly impact your brew? This post is inspired by my new <a href="https://amzn.to/4j7ni2U">Fellows Aiden Precision Coffee Maker</a> which, on one of the first set up screens asks:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/fellows_coffee-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/fellows_coffee-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/fellows_coffee-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/fellows_coffee.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Perhaps that seems like an odd question, buf if you’ve ever tried recreating your favourite <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/8kBMHJEUhXWF1KvL9">Birmingham</a> coffee experience in <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/rfqUP96D2L4juCtT9">Boulder, Colorado</a> (which I have, many times!), you might have noticed something’s a bit “off”. Let’s dive into the science behind why:</p> <p>It all boils down to atmospheric pressure. The air around us exerts pressure, and this pressure decreases as we go higher in altitude. Why? Essentially, there’s less atmosphere above you pushing down.</p> <p>Water boiling occurs when the vapor pressure of the water (or really any liquid) equals the surrounding atmospheric pressure. So these changes in atmospheric pressure directly affects the boiling point of water. Lower atmospheric pressure at higher altitudes means water boils at a lower temperature.</p> <p>The relationship between pressure (P) and boiling point (T) can be approximated using the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clausius%E2%80%93Clapeyron_relation">Clausius-Clapeyron equation</a>:</p> \[\ln\left(\frac{P}{P_0}\right) = -\frac{\Delta H}{R}\left(\frac{1}{T} - \frac{1}{T_0}\right)\] <p>Where:</p> <ul> <li>\(P\): The vapor pressure of the liquid at the temperature of interest (in Pascals, Pa). This is what we want to find to determine the boiling point.</li> <li>\(P_0\): The vapor pressure at a known reference temperature (also in Pascals). For water, we often use standard atmospheric pressure (101325 Pa) and its corresponding boiling point of 100°C (373.15 Kelvin).</li> <li>\(\Delta H\): The enthalpy of vaporization (in Joules per mole, J/mol). This represents the energy needed to change one mole of liquid into vapor at a constant temperature. For water, \(\Delta H\) is approximately 40,700 J/mol.</li> <li>\(R\): The ideal gas constant (8.314 J/mol·K). This constant relates energy to temperature for gases.</li> <li>\(T\): The temperature in Kelvin (K) at which we want to find the vapor pressure (and ultimately, the boiling point).</li> <li>\(T_0\): The reference temperature in Kelvin (K). Again, for water, this is often 373.15 K.</li> </ul> <h2 id="birmingham-vs-boulder-a-tale-of-two-cities">Birmingham vs. Boulder: A Tale of Two Cities</h2> <p>Birmingham, UK, sits at a relatively low altitude (around 140 meters above sea level). Water here boils pretty close to 100°C. Boulder, Colorado, on the other hand, is nestled in the foothills of the Rocky Mountains at an elevation of roughly 1655 meters. This significant difference in altitude has a significant impact on the temperature water boils at.</p> <p>To use the Clausius-Clapeyron equation we first need to calculate atmospheric pressure in Boulder - there are various ways of doing this (getting progressively more difficult) but here it is sufficient to assume a ‘standard atmosphere’ where temperature decreasesd with altitude, and assume that our coffee machine is being used indoors where the temperature is about 20°C, then we can use:</p> \[P = P_0\cdot\exp\left(\frac{-gM(h - h_0)}{RT}\right)\] <p>Where:</p> <ul> <li>\(P\): The air pressure (Pa) at altitude \(h\) (this is the thing we want)</li> <li>\(P_0\): Air pressure at reference altitude \(h_0\) (as in the previous equation we will use sea level pressure of 101325 Pa)</li> <li>\(g\): Acceleration due to gravity (9.81 m/s²)</li> <li>\(M\): Molar mass of air (0.0289644 kg/mol)</li> <li>\(h\): Altitude (m) (Boulder is at 1,655m)</li> <li>\(h_0\): Reference altitude (m) (here we assume sea level, 0 m)</li> <li>\(R\): The universal gas constant (8.31432 J/(mol·K))</li> <li>\(T\): Temperature at altitude \(h\) (K) (must be in Kelvin, and so we use 293.15 K)</li> </ul> <p>Plugging those numbers in gives us:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} P &amp;=&amp; 101325\times\exp\left(\frac{-9.81\times 0.0289644\times (1655 - 0)}{8.31432\times 293.15}\right)\\ &amp;=&amp; 83546 \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>So the atmospheric pressure of Boulder is about 83500 Pa (you can also use this <a href="https://www.mide.com/air-pressure-at-altitude-calculator">online calculator</a> to be more accurate if you want to be, and this also provides more details on air pressure caclulations). Sub this value in (as \(P\)) into the Clausius-Clapeyroin equation and using our other reference values: \(P_0\) (101325 Pa), \(\Delta H\) (40700 J/mol), \(R\) (8.314 J/mol·K), and \(T_0\) (373.15 K) to get:</p> \[\ln\left(\frac{83500}{101325}\right) = -\left(\frac{40700}{8.314}\right)\times\left(\frac{1}{T} - \frac{1}{373.15}\right)\] <p>Solving the above equation for \(T\) requires a little bit of algebraic manipulation but you should end up with \(T \approx 367.7 K\). Which (by removing 273.15) gives a value of 94.55°C for the boiling point of water for Boulder.</p> <p><strong>Water boils at approximately 94.5°C in Boulder.</strong></p> <h2 id="why-it-matters-for-coffee">Why It Matters for Coffee</h2> <p>Coffee brewing is a delicate dance of temperature and extraction. Water acts as a solvent, pulling flavorful compounds from the coffee grounds. The ideal brewing temperature for most coffee lies between 90-96°C. But brewing in Boulder presents a unique challenge. With water boiling at a lower temperature, you have a smaller window to extract those desirable flavors before under-extraction occurs. This can result in a sour or weak cup of coffee.</p> <p>My tips for brewing at higher altitudes (but I am by no means an expert!) are:</p> <ul> <li>Grind finer: A finer grind increases the surface area of the coffee, allowing for better extraction at lower temperatures.</li> <li>Pre-infusion: Bloom your grounds with a small amount of hot water before brewing. This helps saturate the coffee evenly.</li> <li>Extend brew time: Slightly longer brew times can help compensate for the lower temperature.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="misc"/><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why your coffee tastes different in Boulder, CO compared to Birmingham, UK.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">All England football league results</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/All_England_football_league_results/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All England football league results"/><published>2024-12-28T10:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-28T10:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/All_England_football_league_results</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/All_England_football_league_results/"><![CDATA[<p>This article describes a plain text database of all England football (soccer) league results from 1888 to the present day (covering over 209,000 matches).</p> <p>You can access the latest database on its dedicated github page: <a href="https://github.com/seanelvidge/England-football-results/tree/main">England-football-results</a></p> <p>The database is updated roughly every two days (although I am looking for approaches to speed this up) for the top four tiers in England: Premier League, EFL Championship, EFL League One and EFL League Two. The motivation for making the database is that I do a lot of statistical analysis on various bits and pieces in football (you can see some <a href="https://seanelvidge.com/articles/tag/football/">here</a>), and not having an easy to read database really slows me down.</p> <p>The <a href="https://github.com/seanelvidge/England-football-results/tree/main">database</a> is a comma (“,”) delimited csv file with the following columns:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Column</th> <th>Details</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Date</td> <td>the day of the match (string; format “YYYY-MM-DD”)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Season</td> <td>the season the match took place in (string; format “YYYY/YYYY”)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>HomeTeam</td> <td>the home team name (string)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>AwayTeam</td> <td>the away team name (string)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Score</td> <td>the final score (string; format “X-Z”)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>hGoal</td> <td>number of goals scored by the home team (integer; “X” from the “Score” column)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>aGoal</td> <td>number of goals scored by the away team (integer; “Z” from the “Score” column)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Division</td> <td>name of the division the match was played in (string)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Tier</td> <td>numerical representation of the tier which the match was from: 1, 2, 3 or 4, where “1” is the top tier (currently the Premier League) (integer)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Result</td> <td>the result “H” (home win), “A” (away win), “D” (draw) (string)</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>The data from 1888 to 2016 is based on that from: James P. Curley (2016). engsoccerdata: English Soccer Data 1871-2016. http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13158</p> <p>Such a long database of results leads to some confusion around team names, the answer to the most common set of questions I have received in terms of team names:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accrington_F.C.">Accrington F.C.</a> is a different team to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accrington_Stanley_F.C.">Accrington Stanley</a>. Acrrington F.C. were one of the founder members of the Football League, but unfortunately were dissolved in 1896.</li> <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brighton_%26_Hove_Albion_F.C.">Brighton &amp; Hove Albion</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Brighton_Tower_F.C.">New Brighton Tower</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Brighton_A.F.C.">New Brighton</a> are all different clubs. New Brighton Tower were in existence from 1896-1901 and whilst Brighton &amp; Hove Albion were formed in 1901, the “spiritual” successor to New Brighton Tower, was New Brighton (1921-1983 and 1993-2012; originally formed by the relocation of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Liverpool_F.C._(1890s)">South Liverpool</a>)</li> <li>Burton <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burton_Swifts_F.C.">Swifts</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burton_Wanderers_F.C.">Wanderers</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burton_United_F.C.">United</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burton_Town_F.C.">Town</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burton_Albion_F.C.">Albion</a> are all different teams. Burton Swifts joined with Wanderers to form Burton United in 1901, which in 1924 merged with Burton Town and in 1950 merged with the newly formed Burton Albion.</li> <li>Whilst <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leeds_United_F.C.">Leeds Unitd</a> were formed following/replacing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leeds_City_F.C.">Leeds City</a> (and played in the same ground). No players or management from Leeds City moved to Leeds United so we treat them as separate football clubs.</li> <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middlesbrough_Ironopolis_F.C.">Middlesbrough Ironopolis</a> (1889-1894) is separate team from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middlesbrough_F.C.">Middlesbrough</a> (1876-).</li> <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotherham_County_F.C.">Rotherham County</a> merged with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotherham_Town_F.C._(1899)">Rotherham Town</a> in 1925 to form <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotherham_United_F.C.">Rotherham United</a>.</li> <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wigan_Athletic_F.C.">Wigan Athletic</a> were formed (1932) a year after <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wigan_Borough_F.C.">Wigan Borough</a> were wound up (1931) and we treat them separately. Wigan Athletic was the sixth attempt to create a stable football club in Wigan following the dissolving of Wigan A.F.C., <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wigan_County_F.C.">County</a> (1897-1900), <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wigan_United_A.F.C.">United</a> (1896-1914), <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wigan_Town_A.F.C.">Town</a> (1905-1908) and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wigan_Borough_F.C.">Borough</a> (1920-1931).</li> </ul> <p>Hopefully there are lots of fun things you can do with this, please let me know about any of them! A couple of simple examples:</p> <ul> <li>You can use the form on this site to work out a league table for any given season and division or for any arbitrary date range, from 1888 to present (remembering before 1981 there was only <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_points_for_a_win">2 points for a win</a> in English football): <a href="https://seanelvidge.com/leaguetable">https://seanelvidge.com/leaguetable</a></li> <li>To find the Head-to-Head statistics of any two clubs who have played in the English Football League visit: <a href="https://seanelvidge.com/h2h">https://seanelvidge.com/h2h</a> <ul> <li>This url can have the team names passed directly into the url, e.g. to get the head-to-head statistics of Arsenal v Chelsea visit: <a href="https://seanelvidge.com/h2h?team1=Arsenal&amp;team2=Chelsea">https://seanelvidge.com/h2h?team1=Arsenal&amp;team2=Chelsea</a></li> </ul> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="football"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A plain text set of all England football (soccer) league results from 1888 to present.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How aerodynamic is Santa</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/How_aerodynamic_is_Santa/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How aerodynamic is Santa"/><published>2024-12-19T14:31:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-19T14:31:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/How_aerodynamic_is_Santa</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/How_aerodynamic_is_Santa/"><![CDATA[<p>Santa is at the top of multiple engineering disciplines (see his production line for presents and ability to deliver them all). However one that is often overlooked is the space-domain. The United States’ North American Aerospace Defense Command (NORAD) not only continuously tracks 32,000 objects in space to avoid collisions, but also Santa’s global progress in delivering presents on Christmas Eve (https://www.noradsanta.org/en/). From NORAD’s tracks, we can see that he travels at 6.25 km/s (14,000 mph) over oceans (close to the speed of satellites in Low Earth Orbit at 7.7 km/s). However, he travels more slowly, at only 1.4 km/s (3,000 mph) while over the densely populated UK. His route perfectly optimised for reducing atmospheric drag.</p> <p>Whilst travelling over oceans he doesn’t need to be at low altitudes (no presents to deliver) so he takes advantage of the thinner atmosphere at higher altitudes. Also, delivering at night-time allows him to both avoid sleeping children and at the same time take advantage of the lower thermospheric densities, as the thermosphere cools and contracts while the Sun isn’t heating it. However, over populated areas, he travels more slowly in the lower, denser atmosphere, allowing more accurate present delivery while experiencing less heating due to the atmospheric drag.</p> <p>Another optimization Santa has made is in the design of his Sleigh and selection of Reindeer as the method of driving the Sleigh. In the atmospheric drag equation, there is a term known as the coefficient of drag, effectively how well something slips through the atmosphere. Smaller, pointier objects have lower coefficients of drag, think about arrows compared to parachutes. Reindeer have pointy snouts and present a relatively low cross-sectional area for their strength, allowing them to convert their power to speed. Meanwhile having nine reindeer in a 1-2-2-2-2 formation helps to efficiently cut into the air, and make it turbulent before the sleigh travels through, making it experience less drag, just like a cyclist in a peloton. However, Rudolph being at the front takes the brunt of this force due to atmospheric drag, with the majority of the kinetic energy turning into heat energy, leading to his red nose.</p> <p>Whilst we are not sure if Santa has yet upgraded his Sleigh to using the latest SANTA-NAV (GPS) technology, or whether he uses HF communications to keep in touch with the North Pole, we do know that on Christmas Eve, and throughout the Christmas period, the Space Environment research group at the University of Birmingham (SERENE) will be working with space weather centres around the world to help deliver 24/7 forecasting of the conditions in Earth’s upper atmosphere and its impacts on global position systems, HF communications, atmospheric drag and the need for satellite manoeuvres.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="spaceWeather"/><category term="misc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Santa is at the top of many engineering disciplines - his production line for presents, for example. However one that is often overlooked is the space-domain (Redirect to University of Birmingham News page)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Levelling the Playing Field, Adjusting Goal Records in International Football</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/Adjusted_England_Goals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Levelling the Playing Field, Adjusting Goal Records in International Football"/><published>2024-11-20T17:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-20T17:13:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/Adjusted_England_Goals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/Adjusted_England_Goals/"><![CDATA[<p>In recent years, we’ve witnessed a surge in international football records being shattered. Modern players are scoring at unprecedented rates, and while this is undoubtedly exciting for fans, it raises an important question: Are today’s goal-scoring feats truly comparable to those of past legends?</p> <p>The landscape of international football has evolved significantly. The expansion of FIFA membership has introduced many new, smaller nations into the competitive arena. This influx has led to more matches where traditional football powerhouses face off against developing teams, often resulting in lopsided scorelines. Consequently, contemporary players have more opportunities to inflate their goal tallies against weaker opposition.</p> <p>This shift poses a challenge when attempting to compare the goal-scoring records of current players with those from previous eras. The legends of the past often played fewer matches against a more consistent level of competition, making their goal tallies a reflection of performances against relatively equal opponents.</p> <p>So, how can we level the playing field and make fair comparisons across different football eras?</p> <h2 id="introducing-a-weighted-goal-system">Introducing a Weighted Goal System</h2> <p>To address this disparity, I embarked on a project to adjust goal records by accounting for the relative strength of the opposition. The idea is to assign a weighting to each goal based on the difficulty of scoring against a particular team at the time of the match. This method aims to provide a more nuanced evaluation of a player’s goal-scoring achievements.</p> <h3 id="utilizing-elo-ratings">Utilizing Elo Ratings</h3> <p>The foundation of this approach lies in the Elo rating system, a method originally devised for ranking chess players but now widely adopted across various sports, including football. Elo ratings provide a dynamic measure of a team’s strength, updating after each match based on the result and the quality of the opposition.</p> <p>By leveraging historical Elo ratings, we can assess the relative strength of any two teams at the time they played. This allows us to calculate a weighting factor for each goal scored, reflecting the challenge posed by the opponent.</p> <h3 id="the-weighting-formula">The Weighting Formula</h3> <p>The weighting for each goal is determined using the following formula:</p> \[\text{Weight} = 1 - k\times\frac{E-O}{E}\] <p>Where, \(E\) is the Elo rating of England before the match, \(O\) is the Elo rating of the opposition before the match and \(k\) a scaling constant that adjusts the sensitivity of the weighting to the difference in Elo ratings.</p> <p>This formula adjusts the weight of a goal based on how much stronger or weaker the opposition is relative to England:</p> <ul> <li>If England faces a stronger team (\(O &gt; E\)), the weighting increases above 1, acknowledging the greater difficulty.</li> <li>If England faces a weaker team (\(O &lt; E\)), the weighting decreases below 1, reflecting the relatively easier challenge.</li> <li>The constant \(k\) controls how much the difference in ratings affects the weighting.</li> </ul> <h3 id="interpreting-the-weighting">Interpreting the Weighting</h3> <p>Adjusting the \(k\) value alters the impact of the opposition’s strength:</p> <ul> <li>A higher \(k\) value (e.g., 2) amplifies the effect, giving more weight to goals against stronger teams and less to those against weaker ones.</li> <li>A lower \(k\) value (e.g., 1) minimizes the effect, resulting in a more uniform weighting across different opponents.</li> </ul> <p>By experimenting with different \(k\) values, we can fine-tune the system to balance fairness and sensitivity, ensuring that exceptional performances against top-tier teams are appropriately recognized while maintaining a reasonable value for consistent scoring against all opponents.</p> <p>For the rest of this post we use a value of \(k=2\).</p> <h3 id="results">Results</h3> <p>When I last wrote a post similar to this, Wayne Rooney had just <a href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2015/Rooney-50/">broke the England National team goal record with 50 goals</a>. Since then Kane has broke this record again (at the time of writing) with 69 goals. Using the above approach the updated top 10 of England goal scorers are (the “Ranking” is based on the weighted goals column):</p> <style>table{border-collapse:collapse;width:50%;margin:20px auto}th,td{border:1px solid black;padding:8px;text-align:left}th{cursor:pointer;background-color:#f4f4f4}</style> <table id="footballTable"> <thead> <tr> <th onclick="sortTable('footballTable', 0)">Ranking</th> <th onclick="sortTable('footballTable', 1)">Name</th> <th onclick="sortTable('footballTable', 2)">Goals</th> <th onclick="sortTable('footballTable', 3)">Weighted Goals</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>1</td> <td>Harry Kane</td> <td>69</td> <td>45</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2</td> <td>Gary Lineker</td> <td>48</td> <td>37</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3</td> <td>Bobby Charlton</td> <td>49</td> <td>36</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4</td> <td>Jimmy Greaves</td> <td>44</td> <td>35</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5</td> <td>Wayne Rooney</td> <td>53</td> <td>34</td> </tr> <tr> <td>6</td> <td>Michael Owen</td> <td>40</td> <td>30</td> </tr> <tr> <td>7</td> <td>Alan Shearer</td> <td>30</td> <td>23</td> </tr> <tr> <td>8</td> <td>Tom Finney</td> <td>30</td> <td>23</td> </tr> <tr> <td>9</td> <td>Nat Lofthouse</td> <td>30</td> <td>22</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10</td> <td>Frank Lampard</td> <td>29</td> <td>21</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <script>function sortTable(e,r){const s=document.getElementById(e),t=Array.from(s.rows).slice(1),n=!isNaN(t[0].cells[r].innerText);let o=t.sort((e,s)=>{return(n?+e.cells[r].innerText:e.cells[r].innerText.toLowerCase())>(n?+s.cells[r].innerText:s.cells[r].innerText.toLowerCase())?1:-1});const c="asc"===s.dataset.sortOrder?"desc":"asc";"desc"===c&&o.reverse(),s.dataset.sortOrder=c,o.forEach(e=>s.tBodies[0].appendChild(e))}</script> <p>You can see that whilst Kane is still number 1 - his number of goals are significantly less. (Note that the adjusted number of goals here have been rounded to the nearest goal for ease of reading).</p> <p>As may be expected Kane has the biggest change between actual goals scored (69) and the weighted number of goals (45) with a difference of 24, perphaps reaffirming the theory that modern day players are scoring a significant amount of their goals against weaker opposition than in the past. Gary Lineker moves from 4th in the all time list to 2nd.</p> <p>At the other end of the table we end up with a number of people (41) who (because of the rounding as well) move from having scored at least 1 for England to being on 0 goals, but only four who go from more than 1 to zero:</p> <table style="border-collapse: collapse; width: 50%;"> <thead> <tr> <th style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">Name</th> <th style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">Goals</th> <th style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">Weighted Goals</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">Tammy Abraham</td> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">3</td> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">0</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">Paul Ince</td> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">2</td> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">0</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">Tyrone Mings</td> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">2</td> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">0</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">James Ward-Prowse</td> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">2</td> <td style="border: 1px solid black; padding: 8px;">0</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Unfortuntaely Tammy Abraham’s 3 goals for England were scored against very much weaker opposition in the form of Montenegro (England won 7-0 on 14/11/19), Andorra (England won 0-5 on 09/10/21) and San Marino (England won 0-10 on 15/11/21).</p> <p>If you want to have a look at the data you can access it all <a href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/assets/files/england_elo_goal_data.csv">here</a>) (which also includes the “Adjusted Total” which weights Friendlies as 0.5 and “finals” as 2x (as per the description <a href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2015/Rooney-50/">here</a>).</p> <h2 id="data">Data</h2> <p>If you want to have a look at the data in a little more detail (but without downloading the whole datefile above) the below is a sortable table for England players with at least 40 caps):</p> <style>table{border-collapse:collapse;width:90%;margin:20px auto}th,td{border:1px solid black;padding:8px;text-align:left}th{cursor:pointer;background-color:#f4f4f4}</style> <table id="dataTable"> <thead> <tr> <th onclick="sortTable('dataTable', 0)">Name</th><th onclick="sortTable('dataTable', 1)">Caps</th><th onclick="sortTable('dataTable', 2)">Total Goals</th><th onclick="sortTable('dataTable', 3)">Goals per Cap</th><th onclick="sortTable('dataTable', 4)">Weighted Goals</th><th onclick="sortTable('dataTable', 5)">Weighted Goals per Cap</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr><td>Peter Shilton</td><td>125</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Wayne Rooney</td><td>120</td><td>53</td><td>0.44</td><td>34</td><td>0.28</td></tr> <tr><td>David Beckham</td><td>115</td><td>17</td><td>0.15</td><td>12</td><td>0.10</td></tr> <tr><td>Steven Gerrard</td><td>114</td><td>21</td><td>0.18</td><td>13</td><td>0.11</td></tr> <tr><td>Bobby Moore</td><td>108</td><td>2</td><td>0.02</td><td>1</td><td>0.01</td></tr> <tr><td>Ashley Cole</td><td>107</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Bobby Charlton</td><td>106</td><td>49</td><td>0.46</td><td>36</td><td>0.34</td></tr> <tr><td>Frank Lampard</td><td>106</td><td>29</td><td>0.27</td><td>21</td><td>0.20</td></tr> <tr><td>Billy Wright</td><td>105</td><td>3</td><td>0.03</td><td>2</td><td>0.02</td></tr> <tr><td>Harry Kane</td><td>103</td><td>69</td><td>0.67</td><td>45</td><td>0.44</td></tr> <tr><td>Kyle Walker</td><td>93</td><td>1</td><td>0.01</td><td>1</td><td>0.01</td></tr> <tr><td>Bryan Robson</td><td>90</td><td>26</td><td>0.29</td><td>18</td><td>0.20</td></tr> <tr><td>Michael Owen</td><td>89</td><td>40</td><td>0.45</td><td>30</td><td>0.34</td></tr> <tr><td>Kenny Sansom</td><td>86</td><td>1</td><td>0.01</td><td>1</td><td>0.01</td></tr> <tr><td>Gary Neville</td><td>85</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Ray Wilkins</td><td>84</td><td>3</td><td>0.04</td><td>3</td><td>0.04</td></tr> <tr><td>John Stones</td><td>83</td><td>3</td><td>0.04</td><td>2</td><td>0.02</td></tr> <tr><td>Raheem Sterling</td><td>82</td><td>20</td><td>0.24</td><td>14</td><td>0.17</td></tr> <tr><td>Rio Ferdinand</td><td>81</td><td>3</td><td>0.04</td><td>2</td><td>0.02</td></tr> <tr><td>Jordan Henderson</td><td>81</td><td>3</td><td>0.04</td><td>2</td><td>0.02</td></tr> <tr><td>Gary Lineker</td><td>80</td><td>48</td><td>0.60</td><td>37</td><td>0.46</td></tr> <tr><td>John Barnes</td><td>79</td><td>11</td><td>0.14</td><td>8</td><td>0.10</td></tr> <tr><td>John Terry</td><td>78</td><td>6</td><td>0.08</td><td>5</td><td>0.06</td></tr> <tr><td>Stuart Pearce</td><td>78</td><td>5</td><td>0.06</td><td>4</td><td>0.05</td></tr> <tr><td>Terry Butcher</td><td>77</td><td>3</td><td>0.04</td><td>2</td><td>0.03</td></tr> <tr><td>Tom Finney</td><td>76</td><td>30</td><td>0.39</td><td>23</td><td>0.30</td></tr> <tr><td>David Seaman</td><td>75</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Joe Hart</td><td>75</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Sol Campbell</td><td>73</td><td>1</td><td>0.01</td><td>1</td><td>0.01</td></tr> <tr><td>Jordan Pickford</td><td>73</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Gordon Banks</td><td>73</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Alan Ball</td><td>72</td><td>8</td><td>0.11</td><td>6</td><td>0.08</td></tr> <tr><td>Martin Peters</td><td>67</td><td>20</td><td>0.30</td><td>14</td><td>0.21</td></tr> <tr><td>Paul Scholes</td><td>66</td><td>14</td><td>0.21</td><td>11</td><td>0.17</td></tr> <tr><td>Tony Adams</td><td>66</td><td>5</td><td>0.08</td><td>4</td><td>0.06</td></tr> <tr><td>Dave Watson</td><td>65</td><td>4</td><td>0.06</td><td>3</td><td>0.05</td></tr> <tr><td>Harry Maguire</td><td>64</td><td>7</td><td>0.11</td><td>4</td><td>0.06</td></tr> <tr><td>Alan Shearer</td><td>63</td><td>30</td><td>0.48</td><td>23</td><td>0.37</td></tr> <tr><td>Kevin Keegan</td><td>63</td><td>21</td><td>0.33</td><td>15</td><td>0.24</td></tr> <tr><td>Ray Wilson</td><td>63</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>David Platt</td><td>62</td><td>27</td><td>0.44</td><td>20</td><td>0.32</td></tr> <tr><td>Emile Heskey</td><td>62</td><td>7</td><td>0.11</td><td>5</td><td>0.08</td></tr> <tr><td>Chris Waddle</td><td>62</td><td>6</td><td>0.10</td><td>5</td><td>0.08</td></tr> <tr><td>Declan Rice</td><td>62</td><td>5</td><td>0.08</td><td>4</td><td>0.06</td></tr> <tr><td>Emlyn Hughes</td><td>62</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td></tr> <tr><td>Gary Cahill</td><td>61</td><td>5</td><td>0.08</td><td>4</td><td>0.07</td></tr> <tr><td>James Milner</td><td>61</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Ray Clemence</td><td>61</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Marcus Rashford</td><td>60</td><td>17</td><td>0.28</td><td>14</td><td>0.23</td></tr> <tr><td>Peter Beardsley</td><td>59</td><td>9</td><td>0.15</td><td>7</td><td>0.12</td></tr> <tr><td>Des Walker</td><td>59</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Phil Neville</td><td>59</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Jimmy Greaves</td><td>57</td><td>44</td><td>0.77</td><td>35</td><td>0.61</td></tr> <tr><td>Jermain Defoe</td><td>57</td><td>20</td><td>0.35</td><td>10</td><td>0.18</td></tr> <tr><td>Paul Gascoigne</td><td>57</td><td>10</td><td>0.18</td><td>7</td><td>0.12</td></tr> <tr><td>Gareth Southgate</td><td>57</td><td>2</td><td>0.04</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td></tr> <tr><td>Johnny Haynes</td><td>56</td><td>18</td><td>0.32</td><td>14</td><td>0.25</td></tr> <tr><td>Joe Cole</td><td>56</td><td>10</td><td>0.18</td><td>6</td><td>0.11</td></tr> <tr><td>Stanley Matthews</td><td>54</td><td>11</td><td>0.20</td><td>9</td><td>0.17</td></tr> <tr><td>Kieran Trippier</td><td>54</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td></tr> <tr><td>Glen Johnson</td><td>54</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td></tr> <tr><td>Glenn Hoddle</td><td>53</td><td>8</td><td>0.15</td><td>6</td><td>0.11</td></tr> <tr><td>Gareth Barry</td><td>53</td><td>3</td><td>0.06</td><td>2</td><td>0.04</td></tr> <tr><td>Paul Ince</td><td>53</td><td>2</td><td>0.04</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>David James</td><td>53</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Trevor Francis</td><td>52</td><td>12</td><td>0.23</td><td>9</td><td>0.17</td></tr> <tr><td>Teddy Sheringham</td><td>51</td><td>11</td><td>0.22</td><td>9</td><td>0.18</td></tr> <tr><td>Phil Neal</td><td>50</td><td>5</td><td>0.10</td><td>3</td><td>0.06</td></tr> <tr><td>Geoff Hurst</td><td>49</td><td>24</td><td>0.49</td><td>18</td><td>0.37</td></tr> <tr><td>Ron Flowers</td><td>49</td><td>10</td><td>0.20</td><td>8</td><td>0.16</td></tr> <tr><td>Eric Dier</td><td>49</td><td>3</td><td>0.06</td><td>3</td><td>0.06</td></tr> <tr><td>Colin Bell</td><td>48</td><td>9</td><td>0.19</td><td>8</td><td>0.17</td></tr> <tr><td>Jimmy Dickinson</td><td>48</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Theo Walcott</td><td>47</td><td>8</td><td>0.17</td><td>5</td><td>0.11</td></tr> <tr><td>Trevor Brooking</td><td>47</td><td>5</td><td>0.11</td><td>5</td><td>0.11</td></tr> <tr><td>Mick Channon</td><td>46</td><td>21</td><td>0.46</td><td>17</td><td>0.37</td></tr> <tr><td>Gary Stevens</td><td>46</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Mark Wright</td><td>45</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td></tr> <tr><td>Bukayo Saka</td><td>43</td><td>12</td><td>0.28</td><td>6</td><td>0.14</td></tr> <tr><td>Phil Foden</td><td>43</td><td>4</td><td>0.09</td><td>3</td><td>0.07</td></tr> <tr><td>Martin Keown</td><td>43</td><td>2</td><td>0.05</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td></tr> <tr><td>Chris Woods</td><td>43</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Jimmy Armfield</td><td>43</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Peter Crouch</td><td>42</td><td>22</td><td>0.52</td><td>14</td><td>0.33</td></tr> <tr><td>Danny Welbeck</td><td>42</td><td>16</td><td>0.38</td><td>9</td><td>0.21</td></tr> <tr><td>Tony Woodcock</td><td>42</td><td>16</td><td>0.38</td><td>11</td><td>0.26</td></tr> <tr><td>Steve Coppell</td><td>42</td><td>7</td><td>0.17</td><td>5</td><td>0.12</td></tr> <tr><td>Phil Thompson</td><td>42</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td><td>1</td><td>0.02</td></tr> <tr><td>David Batty</td><td>42</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Owen Hargreaves</td><td>42</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Mick Mills</td><td>42</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Paul Robinson</td><td>41</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Bob Crompton</td><td>41</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0</td><td>0.00</td></tr> <tr><td>Jude Bellingham</td><td>40</td><td>6</td><td>0.15</td><td>5</td><td>0.13</td></tr> <tr><td>Phil Jagielka</td><td>40</td><td>3</td><td>0.07</td><td>2</td><td>0.05</td></tr> </tbody> </table>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><category term="football"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By weighting international goals by strength of the opposition we can compare goal scoring prowess across the decades.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Solar Storms are Like Buses You Wait 20 Years for One, and Then Two Come at Once!</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/Solar_storms_are_like_buses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Solar Storms are Like Buses You Wait 20 Years for One, and Then Two Come at Once!"/><published>2024-10-11T14:31:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-11T14:31:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/Solar_storms_are_like_buses</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/Solar_storms_are_like_buses/"><![CDATA[<p>This was the second time this year they have been broadly visible across the UK, with the last major display occurring on the evening of May 10th, 2024. For many, seeing these incredible lights twice in a single year is almost unheard of, and for good reason: before 2024, the UK hadn’t experienced a space weather event of these magnitudes, in over two decades.</p> <p>What has caused this sudden surge in activity? The answer lies in the Sun’s solar cycle, which is rapidly approaching the peak of its activity, and, just like waiting for a bus, after 20 years of relative calm, the UK has now seen two major solar storms in the space of six months.</p> <h2 id="solar-maximum-the-driver-behind-the-lights">Solar Maximum: The Driver Behind the Lights</h2> <p>At the heart of this increased auroral activity is the Sun itself. The Sun goes through cycles of roughly 11 years, moving from periods of quiet (solar minimum) to periods of high activity (solar maximum). We’re currently approaching solar maximum, and this is why we’re seeing more frequent and powerful solar storms.</p> <p>These storms occur when the Sun releases huge quantities matter and magnetic field in the form of a coronal mass ejection (CME) which are also very often associated with solar flares. When these high-speed and high-energy CMEs reach Earth, they can interact and disturb our planet’s magnetic field, causing the stunning lights of the aurora. During solar maximum, the Sun produces more of these storms, leading to auroras that are brighter, more widespread, and visible at lower latitudes—like the UK.</p> <h2 id="what-makes-these-storms-so-special">What Makes These Storms So Special?</h2> <p>Solar storms are typically classified according to the NOAA Space Weather Scale which, for geomagnetic storms, run from G1 (minor) to G5 (extreme), whilst the storm back in May was classified as a G5 (extreme) storm last night the storm peaked at a G4 (severe) event. For context, the last time the UK saw storms of this ‘size’ was over 20 years ago, in October 2003.</p> <p>What makes these storms particularly fascinating is that they push the auroral oval, the region around the poles where the Northern Lights occur, further south. Normally, the UK is too far from the poles to regularly see auroras, but during a G4 or G5 storm, the lights can be visible much further south than the usually are.</p> <h2 id="the-smartphone-effect">The Smartphone Effect</h2> <p>However this was still a relatively mild storm, and can be expected to occur on average about once every 3 or 4 years. One thing that has been particularly different this time around (for both last night and the storm in May), however, is the number of pictures flooding social media. Thanks to the widespread use of smartphones equipped with high-quality cameras, capturing the aurora has never been easier. Modern smartphones now have the ability to take long-exposure shots, which allows them to capture the faint light of the aurora in ways the naked eye cannot. As a result, these natural light shows are being documented and shared like never before, over the coming months and year it may make it feel as if the auroras are more frequent than they might have seemed during previous solar cycles.</p> <h2 id="serene-understanding-space-weather">SERENE: Understanding Space Weather</h2> <p>While the visual spectacle of an aurora is captivating, there’s serious science behind these storms. The Space Environment and Radio Engineering (SERENE) group at the University of Birmingham is at the forefront of research into space weather and its effects on Earth. As a world-class research team, SERENE focuses on understanding the impacts of solar storms and helping society prepare for the disruptions they can cause.</p> <p>Space weather doesn’t just create auroras; it can also affect critical systems such as communications, GPS, satellite orbits and even the power grid. SERENE’s work is vital for mitigating the risks posed by these powerful geomagnetic storms. Their research is ensuring that as we enjoy the beauty of the Northern Lights, we’re also better equipped to protect the technology that supports modern life.</p> <h2 id="looking-ahead-more-auroras-to-come">Looking Ahead: More Auroras to Come?</h2> <p>As we approach the peak of the solar cycle, we can expect more opportunities to witness auroras in the UK. Solar storms will continue to erupt from the Sun and head toward Earth, and if the conditions are right (including cloud-free skies!), we could see even more stunning displays over the next couple of years. For those eager to catch the lights, staying tuned to space weather forecasts during this period of increased activity is key.</p> <p>The next time you see those vibrant reds and greens shimmering in the night sky, you’ll know that it’s not just a stroke of luck - it’s the Sun, cycling through its periodic bursts of activity. And thanks to research groups like SERENE, we can enjoy the beauty of the aurora with the peace of mind that we’re ready for whatever space weather may bring.</p> <p>Originally available from: <a href="https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/news/2024/solar-storms-are-like-buses-you-wait-20-years-for-one-and-then-two-come-at-once" target="\_blank">https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/news/2024/solar-storms-are-like-buses-you-wait-20-years-for-one-and-then-two-come-at-once</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="spaceWeather"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This week, across much of the world including the UK, the majestic aurora borealis, or Northern Lights, were once again visible to us.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The M69 Derby</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/The_M69_Derby/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The M69 Derby"/><published>2024-09-21T06:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-21T06:44:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/The_M69_Derby</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/The_M69_Derby/"><![CDATA[<p>This weekend I watched Coventry City FC vs Leicester City FC in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M69_derby" target="\_blank">“M69” derby (formerly the “A46” derby)</a>. It was a great game, but I’ve always found the name a bit odd, but then it isn’t the only football match referred to by a road name, but there seems to be no consistent reason why we do or do not.</p> <p>Since the naming of these derbys is essentially arbitrary I’ve decided that a match between two teams is the “something” derby if more than half the journey (by road) between the two teams stadia is on one road.</p> <p>For all English Premier League, Championship, League 1, League 2 and Scottish Premier League teams that results in the following matrix of derby names</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/derbydata-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/derbydata-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/derbydata-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/derbydata.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Which gives rise to a lot of potential derby’s, most of which would be called the “M1” or “M6” derby. To narrow it down, only unique road matches will be called derby’s (e.g. the only appearance of the M69 in the table is between Cov and Leicester; green in the previous image).</p> <ul> <li>The A19 Derby: Newcastle United v Middlesbrough</li> <li>The A23 Derby: Brighton &amp; Hove Albion v Crawley Town</li> <li>The A4040 Derby: Aston Villa v West Bromwich Albion</li> <li>The A59 Derby: Harrogate Town v Accrington Stanley</li> <li>The A6010 Derby: Manchester City v Salford City</li> <li>The A630 Derby: Sheffield United v Rotherham United</li> <li>The A66 Derby: Middlesbrough v Carlisle United</li> <li>The M23 Derby: Crystal Palace v Crawley Town</li> <li>The M27 Derby: Southampton v Portsmouth</li> <li>The M55 Derby: Blackpool v Preston North End</li> <li>The M69 Derby: Coventry City v Leicester City</li> </ul> <p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tees%E2%80%93Wear_derby">Tees–Wear derby</a> between Middlesbrough and Sunderland has been called the A19 derby, but our research shows it would be better for Newcastle v Middlesborough. Also the “M27 Derby” as defined above between Southampton and Portsmouth is more commonly called the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Coast_derby" target="\_blank">South Coast Derby</a>.</p> <p>If you want to download the Spreadsheet with all the data in, <a href="/assets/files/football_derby_data.csv">it is available here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="football"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some football matches are named after the roads which connect them, lets find them all.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rules of Acquisition</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/Rules_of_Acquisition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rules of Acquisition"/><published>2024-09-21T06:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-21T06:44:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/Rules_of_Acquisition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/Rules_of_Acquisition/"><![CDATA[<p>I am a big Star Trek fan and also have been enjoying the recent explosion of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large_language_model" target="\_blank">Large Language Models (LLMs)</a>, so I thought I would come up with a way they could be combined.</p> <p>The ‘Rules of Acquisition’ are a collection of sayings of which the <a href="https://memory-alpha.fandom.com/wiki/Ferengi" target="\_blank">Ferengi</a> society is based:</p> <blockquote> <p>Every Ferengi business transaction is governed by these rules to ensure a fair and honest deal for all parties concerned.<br/> (DS9: “The Maquis, Part I”)</p> </blockquote> <p>According to various sources, by the mid-22nd century there were 173 rules (<a href="https://memory-alpha.fandom.com/wiki/Acquisition_(episode)" target="\_blank">ENT: “Acquisition”</a>), by the 2370s there were 285 (<a href="https://memory-alpha.fandom.com/wiki/Rules_of_Acquisition_(episode)" target="\_blank">DS9: “Rules of Acquisition”</a>, <a href="https://memory-alpha.fandom.com/wiki/Body_Parts_(episode)" target="\_blank">“Body Parts”</a>; <a href="https://memory-alpha.fandom.com/wiki/False_Profits_(episode)" target="\_blank">VOY: “False Profits”</a>), and 289 by the 2380s (<a href="https://memory-alpha.fandom.com/wiki/Old_Friends,_New_Planets_(episode)" target="\_blank">LD: “Old Friends, New Planets”</a>).</p> <p>The exact rules appear fairly randomly throughout the Star Trek canon, scattered throughout a number of episodes (predominatly in <a href="https://memory-alpha.fandom.com/wiki/Star_Trek:_Deep_Space_Nine" target="\_blank">Star Trek Deep Space 9</a>). Two excellent wikis exist to document the vast Star Trek universe, <a href="https://memory-alpha.fandom.com/wiki/Portal:Main" target="\_blank">Memory Alpha</a> (using information from all released television series and feature films) and <a href="https://memory-beta.fandom.com/wiki/Main_Page" target="\_blank">Memory Beta</a> (using information from all TV, films and licensed Star Trek works, including novels, comic books, RPG sourcebooks, video games and any other licensed works).</p> <p>In the “primary” canon, <a href="https://memory-alpha.fandom.com/wiki/Rules_of_Acquisition" target="\_blank">52 of the 289 rules were defined</a> and in the extended canon <a href="https://memory-beta.fandom.com/wiki/Ferengi_Rules_of_Acquisition" target="\_blank">144 of the 285 rules were defined</a> (although Rule #2 is defined twice, in different ways).</p> <p>In September 2024 OpenAI released their <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-openai-o1-preview/" target="\_blank">“o1-preview” model</a> which was “trained to spend more time thinking through problems before they respond, much like a person would. Through training, they learn to refine their thinking process, try different strategies, and recognize their mistakes”. It seems like a very powerful model so I decided to put it to the test…</p> <p>I fed it the complete biographical information of the Ferengi’s, their biology, psychology (greed and self preservation), societal information and culture (profit and loss, beliefs, rituals and diplomacy) which are well defined, and referenced <a href="https://memory-beta.fandom.com/wiki/Ferengi" target="\_blank">here</a>. Along with that I provided the 144 existing rules from the wider canon and asked it to fill in the missing rules.</p> <p>And what a wonderful job it did! The complete list is below, merging the ChatGPT-derived rules along with the existing canon (with those by ChatGPT clearly highlighted) but some of my favourites it came up with are:</p> <p>#12 “Anything worth doing is worth doing for profit.”</p> <p>#24: “Never mix business with pleasure unless it enhances profit.”</p> <p>#28: “Morality is always negotiable in the pursuit of profit.”</p> <p>#80: “If it works, sell it; if it doesn’t, sell it as an antique.”</p> <p>#96: “For every opportunity, there’s an equal and opposite opportunity—exploit both.”</p> <p>#114: “The small print holds the biggest profits.”</p> <p>#132: “A lie isn’t a lie until someone else knows the truth.”</p> <p>#161: “Never work for free, unless there’s future profit.”</p> <h2 id="complete-list-of-the-rules-of-acquisition">Complete List of the Rules of Acquisition</h2> <p>Note: if the source is not ChatGPT then these rules come from the <a href="https://memory-beta.fandom.com/wiki/Ferengi_Rules_of_Acquisition" target="\_blank">Ferengi Rules of Acquisition by Memory Beta</a>, which contains more details including links to the source material/epsiode guide.</p> <table border="1" class="dataframe"> <thead> <tr style="text-align: left;"> <th>Rule Number</th> <th>Rule</th> <th>Source</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>1</td> <td>Once you have their money... you never give it back.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "The Nagus", PRD episode: "First Con-tact"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2</td> <td>Money is everything.</td> <td>ST - Strange New Worlds 9 short story: "The Last Tree on Ferenginar: A Ferengi Fable From the Future"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3</td> <td>Never spend more for an acquisition than you have to.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "The Maquis, Part II"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4</td> <td>Sedition and treason are always profitable.</td> <td>ST video game: Star Trek Online</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5</td> <td>Always exaggerate your estimates.</td> <td>SCE eBook: Cold Fusion</td> </tr> <tr> <td>6</td> <td>Never allow family law stand in the way of opportunity.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "The Nagus"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>7</td> <td>Keep your ears open.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "In the Hands of the Prophets"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>8</td> <td>Small print leads to large risk.</td> <td>DS9 reference: The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition</td> </tr> <tr> <td>9</td> <td>Opportunity plus instinct equals profit.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "The Storyteller"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10</td> <td>Greed is eternal.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Prophet Motive"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>11</td> <td>Opportunity waits for no one—seize it quickly.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>12</td> <td>Anything worth doing is worth doing for profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>13</td> <td>Anything worth doing is worth doing for money.</td> <td>Legends of the Ferengi (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>14</td> <td>Sometimes the quickest way to find profits is to let them find you.</td> <td>Fortune of War (TTN novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>15</td> <td>Dead men close no deals.</td> <td>Demons of Air and Darkness (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>16</td> <td>A deal is a deal... until a better one comes along.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>17</td> <td>A contract is a contract is a contract... but only between Ferengi</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Body Parts"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>18</td> <td>A Ferengi without profit is no Ferengi at all.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Heart of Stone", DS9 - The Dog of War comic: "Issue 3"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>19</td> <td>Satisfaction is not guaranteed.</td> <td>Legends of the Ferengi (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>20</td> <td>He who dives under the table today lives to profit tomorrow.</td> <td>Ferenginar: Satisfaction is Not Guaranteed (DS9 novella)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>21</td> <td>Never place friendship above profit.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Rules of Acquisition", PRD episode: "First Con-tact"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>22</td> <td>A wise man can hear profit in the wind.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Rules of Acquisition"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>23</td> <td>Nothing is more important than your health... except for your money.</td> <td>ENT episode: "Acquisition"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>24</td> <td>Never mix business with pleasure unless it enhances profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>25</td> <td>There's no profit in altruism.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>26</td> <td>Customers are like latinum; treasure them and they'll return.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>27</td> <td>There's nothing more dangerous than an honest businessman.</td> <td>Legends of the Ferengi (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>28</td> <td>Morality is always negotiable in the pursuit of profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>29</td> <td>What's in it for me?</td> <td>Highest Score (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>30</td> <td>"Confidentiality equals profit."</td> <td>DS9 - The Badlands novel: Part IV</td> </tr> <tr> <td>31</td> <td>Never make fun of a Ferengi's mother. Insult something he cares about instead.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "The Siege", Elite Force II</td> </tr> <tr> <td>32</td> <td>Enemies are potential customers—never burn a bridge.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>33</td> <td>It never hurts to suck up to the boss.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Rules of Acquisition"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>34</td> <td>War is good for business.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Destiny"; The 34th Rule (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>35</td> <td>Peace is good for business.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Destiny"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>36</td> <td>Too many partners dilute the profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>37</td> <td>The early investor reaps the most interest.</td> <td>ST novella: Reservoir Ferengi</td> </tr> <tr> <td>38</td> <td>Knowledge is power; power yields profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>39</td> <td>Don't tell customers more than they need to know.</td> <td>Ascendance (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>40</td> <td>She can touch your lobes but never your latinum.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>41</td> <td>Profit is its own reward.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>42</td> <td>What's mine is mine, and what's yours is negotiable.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>43</td> <td>Feed your greed, but not enough to choke it.</td> <td>The Buried Age (TNG novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>44</td> <td>Never confuse wisdom with luck.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>45</td> <td>Expand or die.</td> <td>ENT episode: "Acquisition"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>46</td> <td>Make your own opportunities when none arise.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>47</td> <td>Don't trust a man wearing a better suit than your own.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Rivals"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>48</td> <td>The bigger the smile, the sharper the knife.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Rules of Acquisition"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>49</td> <td>Age and treachery will always overcome youth and skill.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>50</td> <td>Gratitude is a profitable emotion—encourage it in others.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>51</td> <td>Reward those who contribute to your wealth.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>52</td> <td>Never ask when you can take.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>53</td> <td>Never trust anybody taller than you.</td> <td>Mission Gamma: Twilight (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>54</td> <td>Rate divided by time equals profit. (Also known as "The Velocity of Wealth.")</td> <td>Raise the Dawn (Typhon Pact novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>55</td> <td>Take joy from profit, and profit from joy.</td> <td>Worlds of Deep Space Nine: Bajor: Fragments and Omens (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>56</td> <td>Only negotiate when you're certain to profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>57</td> <td>Good customers are as rare as latinum—treasure them.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Armageddon Game"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>58</td> <td>There is no substitute for success.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>59</td> <td>Free advice is seldom cheap.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Rules of Acquisition"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>60</td> <td>Keep your lies consistent.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>61</td> <td>Never buy what you can acquire by other means.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>62</td> <td>The riskier the road, the greater the profit.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Rules of Acquisition"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>63</td> <td>Work is the best therapy-at least for your employees.</td> <td>"Over a Torrent Sea" (TTN novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>64</td> <td>The customer is always right—until you get their money.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>65</td> <td>Win or lose, there's always Hupyrian beetle snuff</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>66</td> <td>Someone's always got bigger ears.</td> <td>What Happens Now (Star Trek: The Last Generation #3, TNG comic)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>67</td> <td>Breaking even is a sign of failure.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>68</td> <td>Risk doesn't always equal reward.</td> <td>Star Trek Online</td> </tr> <tr> <td>69</td> <td>Ferengi are not responsible for the stupidity of other races.</td> <td>Balance of Power (TNG novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>70</td> <td>Secure the payment before delivering the product.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>71</td> <td>Close the deal first; details can be settled later.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>72</td> <td>Trust is a commodity best sold, not given.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>73</td> <td>Time spent talking is time away from profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>74</td> <td>Knowledge equals profit.</td> <td>VOY episode: "Inside Man"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>75</td> <td>Home is where the heart is... but the stars are made of latinum.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Civil Defense"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>76</td> <td>Every once in a while, declare peace. It confuses the hell out of your enemies.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "The Homecoming"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>77</td> <td>If you break it, I'll charge you for it!</td> <td>Star Trek Online</td> </tr> <tr> <td>78</td> <td>When the boss is wrong, pretend to agree; then profit from his mistake.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>79</td> <td>Beware of the Vulcan greed for knowledge.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>80</td> <td>If it works, sell it; if it doesn't, sell it as 'vintage'.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>81</td> <td>There's a customer born every minute—find them.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>82</td> <td>The flimsier the product, the higher the price.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>83</td> <td>Quick profit is the best profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>84</td> <td>A friend is a customer waiting to happen.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>85</td> <td>Never let the competition know what you're thinking.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>86</td> <td>Sentiment is the enemy of profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>87</td> <td>Learn the customer's weaknesses, so that you can better take advantage of him.</td> <td>Highest Score (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>88</td> <td>It ain't over 'til its over.</td> <td>Ferenginar: Satisfaction is Not Guaranteed (DS9 novella)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>88</td> <td>Vengeance will cost you everything.</td> <td>The Poisoned Chalice (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>89</td> <td>Ask not what your profits can do for you, but what you can do for your profits.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>89</td> <td>[It is] better to lose some profit and live than lose all profit and die.</td> <td>"Best Tools Available" (DS9 short story)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>90</td> <td>Never tell the truth when a good lie will do.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>91</td> <td>Your boss is only worth what he pays you.</td> <td>"Old Friends, New Planets"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>92</td> <td>There are many paths to profit.</td> <td>Highest Score (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>93</td> <td>Latinum lasts longer than wisdom.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>94</td> <td>Females and finances don't mix.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Ferengi Love Songs"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>95</td> <td>Expand or die.</td> <td>DS9 novel: Legends of the Ferengi, VOY episode: "False Profits"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>96</td> <td>For every opportunity, there's an equal and opposite opportunity—exploit both.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>97</td> <td>Enough... is never enough.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>98</td> <td>Every man has his price.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "In the Pale Moonlight"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>98</td> <td>If you can't take it with you, don't go.</td> <td>I, Q (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>99</td> <td>Trust is the biggest liability of all.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>100</td> <td>When it's good for business, tell the truth.</td> <td>Ascendance (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>101</td> <td>Profit trumps emotion.</td> <td>The Long Mirage (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>102</td> <td>Nature decays, but latinum lasts forever.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "The Jem'Hadar"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>103</td> <td>Sleep can interfere with opportunity.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Rules of Acquisition"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>104</td> <td>Faith moves mountains... of inventory.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>105</td> <td>Don't trust anyone who trusts too easily.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>106</td> <td>There is no honor in poverty.</td> <td>Sacraments of Fire (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>107</td> <td>First to the market gets the biggest profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>108</td> <td>A woman wearing clothes is like a man without any profits.</td> <td>DS9 Novel</td> </tr> <tr> <td>108</td> <td>Hope doesn't keep the lights on.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>109</td> <td>Dignity and an empty sack is worth the sack.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Rivals"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>110</td> <td>Exploitation begins at home.</td> <td>VOY episode: "False Profits"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>111</td> <td>Treat people in your debt like family... exploit them.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Past Tense, Part I"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>112</td> <td>Never have sex with the boss' sister.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Playing God"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>113</td> <td>Always have sex with the boss.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>114</td> <td>The small print holds the biggest profits.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>115</td> <td>Let nothing distract you from the pursuit of profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>116</td> <td>There's always a loophole—find it.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>117</td> <td>You can't free a fish from water.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>118</td> <td>Never settle for less than your worth.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>119</td> <td>A customer's appearance can be deceiving; assess their wealth carefully.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>121</td> <td>Everything is for sale, even friendship.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>122</td> <td>Never Sleep with the bosses sister</td> <td>"Playing God" (DS9 episode)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>123</td> <td>Even a blind man can recognize the glow of Latinum.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>124</td> <td>Let others keep their pride; you keep their latinum.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>125</td> <td>You can't make a deal if you're dead.</td> <td>"The Siege of AR-558" (DS9 episode)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>126</td> <td>Double-check your profits.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>127</td> <td>Neutrality sells to all sides.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>129</td> <td>Fear of loss motivates customers—use it.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>130</td> <td>Opportunities are never missed—only seized by others.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>131</td> <td>Information is the greatest commodity.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>132</td> <td>A lie is as profitable as the truth.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>133</td> <td>Blame shrewdly to protect your interests.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>134</td> <td>Profit above all else, even friendship.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>135</td> <td>Listen to secrets, but never repeat them.</td> <td>Ascendance (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>136</td> <td>Seek profit in every situation.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>137</td> <td>The closer to the source, the greater the profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>138</td> <td>Everything is negotiable—absolutely everything.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>139</td> <td>Wives serve, brothers inherit.</td> <td>"Necessary Evil" (DS9 episode)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>140</td> <td>Your profit margin is the true measure of success.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>141</td> <td>Only fools pay retail.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>142</td> <td>You can never know too much about your customers.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>143</td> <td>Risk is the price of opportunity.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>144</td> <td>There's nothing wrong with charity... as long as it winds up in your pocket.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>145</td> <td>A convincing lie is as good as the truth.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>146</td> <td>Necessity breeds profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>147</td> <td>People love the bartender.</td> <td>Fearful Symmetry (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>148</td> <td>Always negotiate from a position of strength.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>149</td> <td>Everything has a price—find it.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>150</td> <td>Respect is good; latinum is better.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>151</td> <td>Even when you're a customer, sell yourself.</td> <td>The Long Mirage (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>153</td> <td>Sell the sizzle, not the steak.</td> <td>"Deep Space Mine" (DS9 comic)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>154</td> <td>Pain is temporary; profit is eternal.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>155</td> <td>Every being is a potential customer.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>156</td> <td>Don't invest in what you don't understand.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>158</td> <td>Fair play is seldom profitable.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>161</td> <td>Never work for free unless there's future profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>162</td> <td>Even in the worst of times someone turns a profit.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book), DS9 video game: Harbinger</td> </tr> <tr> <td>163</td> <td>The secret of business is to know something others don't.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>164</td> <td>Use others' resources whenever possible.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>166</td> <td>When profits wane, raise your prices.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>167</td> <td>Time is latinum; don't waste either.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>168</td> <td>Whisper your way to success.</td> <td>"Treachery, Faith, and the Great River" (DS9 episode)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>169</td> <td>Competition breeds innovation—and profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>170</td> <td>Secure the contract before revealing the cost.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>171</td> <td>Family is important, but profit is paramount.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>172</td> <td>Desire fuels profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>173</td> <td>A deal in hand is worth two in negotiation.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>174</td> <td>If it sells once, it will sell again.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>175</td> <td>Value is determined by what someone will pay.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>176</td> <td>Never reveal your profit margin.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>177</td> <td>Know your enemies... but do business with them always.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>178</td> <td>The customer is always right—especially when they're wrong.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>180</td> <td>A bribe opens more doors than an honest plea.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>181</td> <td>Not even dishonesty can tarnish the shine of profit.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>182</td> <td>Details are profitable; read the fine print.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>183</td> <td>When life hands you ungaberries, make detergent.</td> <td>Hollow Men (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>184</td> <td>A Ferengi waits to bid until his opponents have exhausted themselves.</td> <td>Balance of Power (TNG novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>185</td> <td>Every rose has its profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>187</td> <td>Profit often hides in unlikely places.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>188</td> <td>Not even dishonesty can tarnish the shine of profit.</td> <td>Star Trek Online</td> </tr> <tr> <td>189</td> <td>Let others keep their reputation. You keep their money.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>190</td> <td>Hear all, trust nothing.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Call to Arms"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>191</td> <td>Neither time nor latinum waits for anyone.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>192</td> <td>Never cheat a Klingon... unless you're sure you can get away with it.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>193</td> <td>It's never too late to fire the staff.</td> <td>Cathedral (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>193</td> <td>Trouble comes in threes.</td> <td>Star Trek Online</td> </tr> <tr> <td>194</td> <td>It's always good business to know about new customers before they walk in your door.</td> <td>"Whispers" (DS9 episode)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>195</td> <td>Watch your expenses; small leaks sink big ships.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>197</td> <td>An inventive excuse can nullify a bad contract.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>198</td> <td>Every bargain has a hidden cost.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>199</td> <td>Location, location, location.</td> <td>The Soul Key (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>200</td> <td>A Ferengi chooses no side but his own.</td> <td>(DS9 novel: Ferenginar: Satisfaction is Not Guaranteed)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>201</td> <td>Diversify your investments.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>202</td> <td>The justification for profit is profit.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>203</td> <td>New customers are like razor-toothed gree worms. They can be succulent, but sometimes they bite back.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Little Green Men"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>204</td> <td>Only a Ferengi truly understands another Ferengi.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>205</td> <td>Without customers, there is no profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>207</td> <td>A Tribble Always Means Customer Satisfaction</td> <td>Adventures RPG: Tribble Player Character Supplement</td> </tr> <tr> <td>208</td> <td>Sometimes, the only thing more dangerous than a question is an answer.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Ferengi Love Songs"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>209</td> <td>An empty account can't fund ventures.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>210</td> <td>Deep pockets attract deep profits.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>211</td> <td>Employees are the rungs on the ladder of success. Don't hesitate to step on them.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Bar Association"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>212</td> <td>A good lie is easier to believe than the truth.</td> <td>Star Trek Online</td> </tr> <tr> <td>213</td> <td>Personal relations should serve business goals.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>214</td> <td>Never begin a (business) negotiation on an empty stomach.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "The Maquis, Part I"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>215</td> <td>Contracts between friends must be written doubly tight.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>216</td> <td>Never gamble with a telepath.</td> <td>DS9 novel: The Laertian Gamble</td> </tr> <tr> <td>217</td> <td>You can't free a fish from water.</td> <td>"Past Tense, Part I" (DS9 episode)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>218</td> <td>Sometimes what you get free costs entirely too much.</td> <td>Baby on Board (DS9 Malibu Comics)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>219</td> <td>Possession is eleven-tenths of the law!</td> <td>TNG novel: Balance of Power</td> </tr> <tr> <td>220</td> <td>Those who own nothing have nothing to lose.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>221</td> <td>Latinum can't buy happiness, but it can lease it.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>222</td> <td>Knowledge is profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>223</td> <td>Beware the man who doesn't take time for Oo-mox.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>224</td> <td>Your greatest enemy could be your greatest asset.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>225</td> <td>Profit is the noblest pursuit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>226</td> <td>Honesty is a luxury for those who can afford it.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>227</td> <td>If that's what's written, then that's what's written.</td> <td>Star Trek Online</td> </tr> <tr> <td>228</td> <td>A satisfied customer is good; a dependent customer is better.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>229</td> <td>Latinum lasts longer than lust.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Ferengi Love Songs"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>230</td> <td>Opportunities expire—act swiftly.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>231</td> <td>When profits are at stake, listen carefully.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>232</td> <td>Need creates demand; demand creates profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>233</td> <td>Find the need, then fill it—for a price.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>234</td> <td>Latinum can't buy love, but it can rent it for a while.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>235</td> <td>Duck; death is tall.</td> <td>Mission Gamma: Twilight (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>236</td> <td>You can't buy fate.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>237</td> <td>Negotiation is preferable to confrontation.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>238</td> <td>Another's honor can be your profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>239</td> <td>Never be afraid to mislabel a product.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Body Parts"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>240</td> <td>Time, like latinum, is a highly limited commodity.</td> <td>Star Trek Online</td> </tr> <tr> <td>241</td> <td>Greed is a universal constant—capitalize on it.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>242</td> <td>More is good... all is better.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>243</td> <td>Always leave yourself an out.</td> <td>Sacraments of Fire (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>244</td> <td>Time invested wisely yields profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>245</td> <td>Too many customers? Raise your prices.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>246</td> <td>Secrecy is profitable.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>247</td> <td>A customer's deception is a seller's opportunity.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>248</td> <td>The definition of insanity is trying the same failed scheme &amp; expecting different results</td> <td>Department of Temporal Investigations 3: Shield of the Gods (novel) pg 11</td> </tr> <tr> <td>249</td> <td>Bankruptcy can be a strategic move.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>250</td> <td>There's always profit in chaos.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>251</td> <td>Guarantees are for the seller, not the buyer.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>252</td> <td>If you can't sell it, don't buy it.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>253</td> <td>Beware of beneficiaries bearing gifts.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>254</td> <td>Maximize profit with minimal effort.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>255</td> <td>A wife is luxury... a smart accountant a neccessity.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>256</td> <td>A genuine smile can close a deal.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>257</td> <td>When the messenger comes to appropriate your profits, kill the messenger.</td> <td>False Profits (VOY episode)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>258</td> <td>Family ties are secondary to profit opportunities.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>259</td> <td>Opportunity, not intelligence, leads to wealth.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>260</td> <td>Life is finite; profit is infinite.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>261</td> <td>A wealthy man can afford anything except a conscience.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>263</td> <td>Never allow doubt to tarnish your lust for latinum.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "Bar Association"</td> </tr> <tr> <td>264</td> <td>A friendly façade can conceal sharp intent.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>265</td> <td>Trust no one wearing better shoes than you.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>266</td> <td>When in doubt, lie.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>267</td> <td>If you believe it, they believe it.</td> <td>Taking Wing (DS9 novel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>268</td> <td>When uncertain, charge extra.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>269</td> <td>It's easier to ask forgiveness than permission—especially after the profit is made.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>270</td> <td>If you can acquire it for free, do so.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>271</td> <td>Always have an escape plan.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>272</td> <td>Always inspect the merchandise before making a deal.</td> <td>Star Trek Online</td> </tr> <tr> <td>273</td> <td>Wealth attracts attention; use it wisely.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>274</td> <td>Fear can be a profitable motivator.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>275</td> <td>Revenge is unprofitable.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>279</td> <td>Never lose sight of profit—the ultimate goal.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>280</td> <td>If it ain't broke, don't fix it.</td> <td>DS9 novel: Ferenginar: Satisfaction is Not Guaranteed)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>283</td> <td>Rules can be bent—not broken—to serve profit.</td> <td>ChatGPT</td> </tr> <tr> <td>284</td> <td>Deep down, everyone's a Ferengi.</td> <td>The Ferengi Rules of Acquisition (DS9 reference book)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>285</td> <td>No good deed ever goes unpunished.</td> <td>DS9 episode: "The Collaborator"</td> </tr> </tbody> </table>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="misc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The (complete) Rules of Acquisition, 1 to 285.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Space weather can affect our daily lives — we need a better warning system</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/A_new_space_weather_warning_system/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Space weather can affect our daily lives — we need a better warning system"/><published>2024-06-11T14:31:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-11T14:31:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/A_new_space_weather_warning_system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/articles/2024/A_new_space_weather_warning_system/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/nature_SpWx-Warning-Map-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/nature_SpWx-Warning-Map-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/nature_SpWx-Warning-Map-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/nature_SpWx-Warning-Map.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </figure> </div> </div> <p>In May, millions of people were dazzled by the vibrant hues of the aurora borealis and australis — the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-01432-7" target="\_blank">northern and southern lights</a>. The product of a large solar storm, curtains of green, red and purple light rippled across the night sky in regions where the spectacle is seldom seen. I saw them for the first time in the United Kingdom, from my back garden just outside Birmingham. More displays are expected in the coming months as solar activity starts to reach its peak.</p> <p>But what most people didn’t see were the repercussions — and the preparations that went on behind the scenes to mitigate them. Radio communications systems experienced blackouts; Starlink, the satellite Internet provider, faced outages; and disruptions to global navigation satellite systems caused problems for sectors reliant on positioning. Meanwhile, flights were re-routed and electric grids were safeguarded.</p> <p>This illustrates a dilemma faced by space-weather scientists such as myself: how can we issue and communicate effective warnings when even such a significant storm changes little in most people’s lives? I think part of the problem lies in how we classify space weather. Current systems are simplistic; space weather is not.</p> <p>Geomagnetic storms are classified using scales developed by the US National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in collaboration with the space-weather community. The geomagnetic storm scale (G-scale), solar radiation storm scale (S-scale) and radio blackout scale (R-scale) range from one to five, with five denoting an extreme event.</p> <p>These scales have been invaluable in highlighting the risk of space weather to industries and governments, but they are due a refresh. The geomagnetic storm that caused the May auroras was classified as G5, or ‘extreme’. However, the effects of a solar storm are challenging to quantify. This storm was triggered by a rapid sequence of at least seven coronal mass ejections — massive bursts of solar matter and magnetic fields expelled from the surface of the Sun. As these collided with Earth’s magnetic field, they compressed and disturbed it, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-00007-1" target="\_blank">triggering geomagnetic storms</a>.</p> <p>But many factors, including the speed, mass, duration and magnetic orientation of coronal mass ejections, influence a storm’s impact. In terms of peak geomagnetic activity, the May storm was a 1-in-10-year event. What set this storm apart was its prolonged duration. Geomagnetic disturbances remained high for 24 hours, making it more like a 1-in-75-year event. Auroras were visible for longer, allowing more people to witness them.</p> <p>Such details make it hard to convey the risks of space weather without overstating or understating them. If an event such as that seen in May, deemed ‘extreme’, results in minimal obvious disruption, how should the risks of an even stronger 1-in-100-year storm be conveyed?</p> <p>A superstorm is a looming reality. Costs could reach billions of dollars. Electric grids could be disrupted, causing local blackouts. Satellites, and the essential systems they support, could be impaired. Radio signals, crucial for aviation, maritime operations and emergency services, would be disrupted. For example, in October 2003, geomagnetic storms affected satellite communications, GPS systems and power supplies in Europe, North America and Africa.</p> <p>To communicate the severity of truly extreme storms, scientists need to rethink the classification scales. Some researchers suggest extending severity levels to six and above. Others propose covering more phenomena, including the D-Scale (radiation dose rate) and the T-Scale (radio-wave propagation through Earth’s upper atmosphere).</p> <p>My preferred approach is to shift to a ‘traffic light’ model of warnings for specific sectors. For example, yellow space-weather warnings could alert industries, such as aviation and agriculture, that might be affected by minor geomagnetic storms. An orange warning might require users, such as power grid and radar operators, to consider taking pre-emptive action to protect their services and prepare for interruptions. A red warning would signal that dangerous space weather is expected, with potentially significant impacts requiring immediate action, and power companies, satellite operators and emergency services must implement contingency plans without delay.</p> <p>Such a system would quickly alert those who should be most concerned. It could accommodate uncertainties by allowing for updates and escalations in warnings as data become available. For example, a geomagnetic event might start with a yellow warning (high impact, but unlikely) when a coronal mass ejection is first observed. It could be upgraded to orange or red if the probability of disruption increases with further modelling and data. Its reach could easily be expanded by adding sectors to the warning list.</p> <p>A unified approach to refining space weather reporting and response strategies is crucial, and space weather centres worldwide must come together to discuss and agree on an updated approach. They must ensure that terms such as ‘extreme’ are not misused and that these align with events that truly warrant attention and action, and that industries and the public are adequately prepared for the real risks.</p> <p>As we navigate the peak of the solar cycle, it is important to acknowledge that space weather affects our daily lives. By refining classification and reporting systems, scientists can better align public perception with reality, ensuring that we are neither crying wolf nor caught unprepared.</p> <p>Nature 630, 271 (2024)</p> <p>doi: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-024-01715-z" target="\_blank">https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-024-01715-z</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="spaceWeather"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Categorizing geomagnetic storms on a scale of one to five leaves no room for once-a-century superstorms]]></summary></entry></feed>