<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-08-02T22:41:51+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sean Elvidge</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Rooney Scores 50 goals for England – the data</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2015/Rooney-50/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rooney Scores 50 goals for England – the data"/><published>2015-09-11T23:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-09-11T23:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2015/Rooney-50</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2015/Rooney-50/"><![CDATA[<p>Wayne Rooney has broken the England football goal scoring record with 50 goals. A lot of discussion has therefore been about if he is the greatest English attacker of all time or not. Let’s look at the data.</p> <p>The main argument against Rooney being the greatest is his lack of World Cup Finals goals (1; at the 2014 finals). A comment which is also often made is about the number of “friendly” goals scored. Lineker (with a total of 48 goals for England, 3rd in the all time list) was recently voted as England’s greatest attacker in a BBC poll, managed 10 goals in World Cup finals (including the 1986 Golden Boot).</p> <p>So what if we weight goals differently? What if we make friendly goals worth 0.5 a goal, and “finals” goals (i.e. the World Cup Finals and European Championships Finals) as times 2? What does that do to the all time scoring list?</p> <p>(Here I count goals in the old “Home Championship” as ‘1’ (i.e. the same as World Cup and European qualifiers). Although there is an argument to be had that it should be weighted more heavily since it was <strong>the</strong> international competition for England before the World Cup got “big” (~pre-1950s). However, for now I’ll leave its weighting as ‘1’.)</p> <p>In that adjusted table we get the following:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center">Ranking</th> <th style="text-align: center">Name</th> <th style="text-align: center">Adjusted Goals</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> <td style="text-align: center">Wayne Rooney</td> <td style="text-align: center">49</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> <td style="text-align: center">Gary Lineker</td> <td style="text-align: center">46</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> <td style="text-align: center">Bobby Charlton</td> <td style="text-align: center">43</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> <td style="text-align: center">Michael Owen</td> <td style="text-align: center">39</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> <td style="text-align: center">Jimmy Greaves</td> <td style="text-align: center">34.5</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> <td style="text-align: center">Alan Shearer</td> <td style="text-align: center">34. 5</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>You can see that Rooney is still number 1 - despite down weighting the friendly goals.</p> <p>But okay, perhaps you think friendlies shouldn’t count at all and only competitive fixtures should be counted (the ‘Adjusted Goals’ column is if we again weight finals goals more heavily, the first ranking column is for the ‘non-adjusted’ goals):</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center">Ranking</th> <th style="text-align: center">Name</th> <th style="text-align: center">Goals</th> <th style="text-align: center">Adjusted Goals</th> <th style="text-align: center">Adjusted Ranking</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> <td style="text-align: center">Wayne Rooney</td> <td style="text-align: center">36</td> <td style="text-align: center">42</td> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> <td style="text-align: center">Stephen Bloomer</td> <td style="text-align: center">28</td> <td style="text-align: center">28</td> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> <td style="text-align: center">Bobby Charlton</td> <td style="text-align: center">27</td> <td style="text-align: center">32</td> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> <td style="text-align: center">Michael Owen</td> <td style="text-align: center">26</td> <td style="text-align: center">32</td> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> <td style="text-align: center">Gary Lineker</td> <td style="text-align: center">24</td> <td style="text-align: center">34</td> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> <td style="text-align: center">Jimmy Greaves</td> <td style="text-align: center">23</td> <td style="text-align: center">24</td> <td style="text-align: center">8</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Again, Rooney comes top for both the usual and adjusted goal tallies. (One way) to knock Rooney off that top spot (if you particularly want to for some reason) is to look at the ‘goals per cap ratio’. To use this stat we have to set a cap limit because of the people who didn’t play very much. For example, Albert Allen, Francis Bradshaw, John Veitch, John Yates and Rev. Walter Gilliat who were all capped once by England, and each scored a hattrick on their one, and only, appearance for England. This gives them a rather impressive 3 goals per cap ratio. If we only consider players who have at least 40 caps then:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center">Ranking</th> <th style="text-align: center">Name</th> <th style="text-align: center">Goals per cap</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> <td style="text-align: center">Jimmy Greaves</td> <td style="text-align: center">0.77</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> <td style="text-align: center">Gary Lineker</td> <td style="text-align: center">0.6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> <td style="text-align: center">Peter Crouch</td> <td style="text-align: center">0.52</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> <td style="text-align: center">Geoff Hurst</td> <td style="text-align: center">0.49</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> <td style="text-align: center">Alan Shearer</td> <td style="text-align: center">0.48</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> <td style="text-align: center">Wayne Rooney</td> <td style="text-align: center">0.47</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Finally, if you again weighted the goals (since Crouch scored 12 of his 22 goals in friendlies) you would find the order is Greaves, Lineker, Hurst, Shearer, Rooney (Crouch drops from 3rd to 8th).</p> <p>I am not going to make any conclusions about if Rooney is England’s greatest attacker or not, that is up to you! All the data I’ve used in this post was collected from <a href="https://www.englandstats.com/">englandstats.com</a> and is accurate as of today (11th September, 2015). If you want to play around with the data I’ve collated all the stats (player names, caps, minutes played and goals scored (separated into individual competitions)) into an Excel file available <a href="assets/files/england_goal_data.xlsx">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics,football"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Data analysis of Wayne Rooney's 50 goals for England]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Safe Reboot of Locked Linux Machine</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2015/safe-reboot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Safe Reboot of Locked Linux Machine"/><published>2015-03-20T15:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-03-20T15:29:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2015/safe-reboot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2015/safe-reboot/"><![CDATA[<p>The magic SysRq (system request) allows you to access a low-level message system in the kernel. This will work as long as there hasn’t been a kernel panic, and can provide you with a way of rescuing the system. To access the key combination you need to hold <strong>Alt + SysRq + Command</strong> where command is the specific feature you want to access. The SysRq key is usually the same as the Print Screen key. A table of the available commands are found at the table at the bottom of this article, but the main one you will probably use is:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Alt + SysRq + REISUB              <span class="o">(</span>slowly <span class="nb">type </span>the R E I S U B<span class="o">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This will kill all process except init, sync the mounted file systems, remount the file systems in read-only mode and reboot the system. There are a few ways to try and remember the order REISUB, the one I use is “Reboot Even If System Utterly Broken”, you could also just remember that it is ‘BUSIER’ backwards. Hope it comes in handy, here is the table of all the commands:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Command</th> <th>Description</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>0-9</td> <td>Set the console log level, i.e., change the type of kernel messages that are output</td> </tr> <tr> <td>b</td> <td>Immediately reboot the system, without unmounting or syncing filesystems</td> </tr> <tr> <td>c</td> <td>Perform a system crash. A crashdump will be taken if configured.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>d</td> <td>Display all currently held locks</td> </tr> <tr> <td>e</td> <td>Send the SIGTERM signal to all processes except init (PID 1)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>g</td> <td>Emergency support for switching back to the kernel’s framebuffer console</td> </tr> <tr> <td>h</td> <td>Output a terse help document to the console</td> </tr> <tr> <td>i</td> <td>Send the SIGKILL signal to all processes except init</td> </tr> <tr> <td>j</td> <td>Forcibly “Just thaw it” – filesystems frozen by the FIFREEZE ioctl</td> </tr> <tr> <td>k</td> <td>Kill all processes on the current virtual console</td> </tr> <tr> <td>l</td> <td>Shows a stack backtrace for all active CPUs</td> </tr> <tr> <td>m</td> <td>Output current memory information to the console</td> </tr> <tr> <td>n</td> <td>Reset the nice level of all high-priority and real-time tasks</td> </tr> <tr> <td>o</td> <td>Shut off the system</td> </tr> <tr> <td>p</td> <td>Output the current registers and flags to the console</td> </tr> <tr> <td>q</td> <td>Display all active high-resolution timers and clock sources</td> </tr> <tr> <td>r</td> <td>Switch the keyboard from raw mode</td> </tr> <tr> <td>s</td> <td>Sync all mounted filesystems</td> </tr> <tr> <td>t</td> <td>Output a list of current tasks and their information to the console</td> </tr> <tr> <td>u</td> <td>Remount all mounted filesystems in read-only mode</td> </tr> <tr> <td>v</td> <td>Forcefully restores framebuffer console</td> </tr> <tr> <td>w</td> <td>Display list of blocked tasks</td> </tr> <tr> <td>y</td> <td>Show global CPU registers (SPARC-64 specific)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>z</td> <td>Dump the ftrace buffer</td> </tr> <tr> <td>w</td> <td>Display list of blocked tasks</td> </tr> <tr> <td>y</td> <td>Show global CPU registers (SPARC-64 specific)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>z</td> <td>Dump the ftrace buffer</td> </tr> </tbody> </table>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="linux"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to safely reboot a locked linux machine]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quick way to remove X Server for running a headless server</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2014/remove-X-server/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quick way to remove X Server for running a headless server"/><published>2014-05-10T07:35:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-05-10T07:35:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2014/remove-X-server</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2014/remove-X-server/"><![CDATA[<p>I use my Raspberry Pi as a headless server so do not need anything that relies on X11, this is a quick way to get rid of everything that depends on X11 to save some space.</p> <p>Although you can get Raspberry Pi OSs which are very minimal (i.e. do not start with the X Server) I’ve found that <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.com/software/">Raspbian</a> is the most stable (Debian-based) OS for the Raspberry Pi, and so that is what I use. It is also really easy to set up to use as a headless server.</p> <p>Flash the OS to your SD card, boot your Raspberry Pi with it and as long as you have a wired internet connection to it, no need to use a screen. Simply SSH into the machine with the username ‘pi’ and password ‘raspberry’ (if you aren’t sure what the IP address of your Pi is you can either look on your router or I find using the Android App <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.overlook.android.fing">Fing</a> the easiest way).</p> <p>The first time you login you may want to run the Raspbian config programme:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>raspi-config
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Now the quick way to remove X11:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>apt-get remove <span class="nt">--auto-remove</span> <span class="nt">--purge</span> libx11-.<span class="k">*</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>The ‘–purge’ command in apt-get will remove everything which is associated with libx11, a nice quick way to save a load of space. If you so wish you can always check if a particular package is installed or not with:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>apt-cache policy package
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Where package is the package you want to check if it is installed or no. If it is installed the version number will be returned if not you will some text including the line ‘Installed: (none)’.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="linux"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Remove X Server]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Files and Folders Lowercase</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/making-lowercase/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Files and Folders Lowercase"/><published>2013-10-21T12:32:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-10-21T12:32:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/making-lowercase</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/making-lowercase/"><![CDATA[<p>Very occasionally I want to make all the files and folders of a particular directory lowercase (usually when porting an existing directory structure from Windows to Linux) this is how I do it.</p> <p>You could set up some form of recursive renaming script in a similar fashion to my post on <a href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2011/batch-process-in-bash/">Batch Process in Bash</a>. But it is much nicer to do it in just the one line, assume we want to change all the file and folder names inside the folder ‘/home/sean/windows/’:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>find /home/sean/windows/ <span class="nt">-depth</span> <span class="nt">-exec</span> rename <span class="s1">'s/(.*)\/([^\/]*)/$1\/\L$2/'</span> <span class="o">{}</span> <span class="se">\;</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Job done!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="linux"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to make all files lowercase]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Variance in TV Viewing Figures</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/variance-in-tv/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Variance in TV Viewing Figures"/><published>2013-04-16T09:52:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-04-16T09:52:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/variance-in-tv</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/variance-in-tv/"><![CDATA[<p>It is a fairly safe assumption that viewing figures for TV shows typically drop over time. But what I was thinking about this morning is how many people just turn on the TV and watch whatever is on, is that something we can work out from TV videwing figures?</p> <p>To start with lets consider “Grey’s Anatomy”. The viewing figure data is from <a href="http://abcmedianet.com/web/homepage/default.aspx" target="_blank">ABC Medianet</a> and initially we just plot the number of viewers per episode which results in the below graph.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/overall2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/overall2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/overall2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/overall2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The first thing to notice in the above plot, is the large spike of around 38 million viewers for episode 24. This is caused by being the lead out show after Super Bowl XL. The brown circles plotted represent the start of a new season, as very often a new season (with the associated advertising) leads to a bump in viewing figures.</p> <p>We can also see from the plot that over time the number of viewers for the show has steadily decreased. And the red and blue curves are polynomial fits to the data to try and track that change in viewers. The red curve ignores the viewing figure from after the Super Bowl, treating it as an outlier. To look at the variation in users we can subtract the overall trend of viewers from the data and just look at the “noise”.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/data-minus-trend-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/data-minus-trend-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/data-minus-trend-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/data-minus-trend.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>However, this “noise” also contains the trend of an increase in viewers at the start of a new season and this diminishing over the season. To try and remove this we look at the Hilbert-Huang transform of the data minus the trend, breaking the curve into 7 intrinsic mode functions (IMF):</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/IMFs-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/IMFs-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/IMFs-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/IMFs.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>What we discover in the 4th IMF is the following trend, made larger below so it is more visible, with the red vertical lines indicating where a new season begins.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/EMD-Season-Start-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/EMD-Season-Start-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/EMD-Season-Start-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/EMD-Season-Start.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>You can see that the peaks do not always match where a season begins (which was also reflected in the very first plot), but very often they do. This means that we can now plot the true “fluctuations” in viewer numbers by subtracting the above graph from our “noise” graph.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/viewer-noise-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/viewer-noise-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/viewer-noise-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/viewer-noise.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>It looks like, in this plot, that the noise in viewing figures is decreasing over time. However since we know that there is a decreasing number of viewers we calculate the normalised standard deviation for each season. This is done by finding the standard deviation of a season and dividing it by the range of viewers for that season. This is presented in the table below.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>| Season Number | Standard Deviation (Millions) | Range of Viewers (Million) | (Standard Deviation / Range ) <span class="se">\*</span> 100 (%) |
| :-----------: | :---------------------------: | :------------------------: | :--------------------------------------: |
|       1       |             1.19              |            5.97            |                  19.99                   |
|       2       |             1.71              |            9.72            |                  17.60                   |
|       3       |             1.82              |            8.88            |                  20.45                   |
|       4       |             1.39              |            6.82            |                  20.31                   |
|       5       |             1.43              |            5.36            |                  26.76                   |
|       6       |             1.34              |            7.16            |                  18.70                   |
|       7       |             1.09              |            5.19            |                  21.10                   |
|       8       |             0.66              |            3.93            |                  16.88                   |
|       9       |             0.59              |            3.56            |                  16.67                   |
</code></pre></div></div> <p>The percentage column has a mean value of 19.83% itself with a standard deviation of 3.06%. So we can conslude that the standard deviation of the noise in viewers is about 20% of the range of viewers. Is this a “standard value”? Or is it somehow tied to Grey’s Anatomy?</p> <p>Below I have generated the same plots as above for the shows ‘How I Met Your Mother’ and ‘Desperate Housewives’ which can be seen in the following galleries:</p> <p>How I Met Your Mother:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/himym-viewing-figures-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/himym-viewing-figures-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/himym-viewing-figures-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/himym-viewing-figures.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/himym-data-minus-trend-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/himym-data-minus-trend-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/himym-data-minus-trend-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/himym-data-minus-trend.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/himym-IMFS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/himym-IMFS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/himym-IMFS-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/himym-IMFS.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/himym-emd-composition-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/himym-emd-composition-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/himym-emd-composition-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/himym-emd-composition.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/himym-noise-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/himym-noise-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/himym-noise-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/himym-noise.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Desperate Housewives:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/dh-viewing-figures-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/dh-viewing-figures-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/dh-viewing-figures-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/dh-viewing-figures.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/dh-data-minus-trend-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/dh-data-minus-trend-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/dh-data-minus-trend-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/dh-data-minus-trend.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/dh-IMFs-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/dh-IMFs-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/dh-IMFs-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/dh-IMFs.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/dh-emd_composition-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/dh-emd_composition-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/dh-emd_composition-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/dh-emd_composition.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/dh-noise_in_viewers-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/dh-noise_in_viewers-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/dh-noise_in_viewers-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/dh-noise_in_viewers.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Desperate Housewives shows a similar pattern to Grey’s Anatomy in terms of the overall viewing figure trend. Increasing initially and then dropping off. ‘How I Met Your Mother’, however, shows a different pattern. Although there are less viewers, the numbers remain fairly constant throughout the show.</p> <p>From the above analysis we get a standard deviation (as a percentage of the range of viewers) as 17.17% (with a standard deviation of ~2.82%) for Desperate Housewives and 21.90% (standard deviation of 2.95%) for How I Met Your Mother.</p> <p>So the three values we’ve got are 19.83%, 17.17% and 21.90%. Giving an average of 19.63%, well three examples are enough for me! It certainly hints at the fact that the spread of noise in viewing figures is independent of the show, and may be a fact of TV viewing figures.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How many people just turn on How does Grey's Anatomy viewing figures vary over time?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Velocity Required for Loop-the-Loop</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/loop-the-loop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Velocity Required for Loop-the-Loop"/><published>2013-02-21T16:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-02-21T16:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/loop-the-loop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/loop-the-loop/"><![CDATA[<p>In this post we are going to work out (approximately) the minimum speed required to complete a loop-the-loop, we’ll do this via an energy argument. However, for ease, we are going to ignore friction! First we need to find the minimum speed required at the top of the loop.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/loop-the-loop-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/loop-the-loop-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/loop-the-loop-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/loop-the-loop.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>To get the minimum required speed to make the loop-the-loop, at the top of the loop we require the normal force (\(N\)) to be \(0\). Equating the forces at the top of the loop we have the weight of the car (\(mg\)) plus the normal force (\(N\)) equal to the centrifugal force (\(F\)), which is given by \(F=\frac{mv^2}{r}\) where \(r\) is the radius of the circle. Thus,</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} \frac{mv_t^2}{r} &amp;=&amp; N+mg, \\ \frac{v_t^2}{r} &amp;=&amp; g,\\ v_t^2 &amp;=&amp; gr,\\ v_t &amp;=&amp; \sqrt{gr}. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>Giving us a minimum velocity at the top of the loop, \(v_t\). We now proceed with the energy argument.</p> <p>The total energy at the top of the loop is equal to the potential energy at the top plus the kinetic energy at the top, respectively these are:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} PE_t &amp;=&amp; mgh = 2mgr,\\ KE_t &amp;=&amp; \frac{1}{2}mv_t^2 = \frac{1}{2}mgr. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>Thus the total energy at the top is:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} E_t &amp;=&amp; 2mgr+\frac{1}{2}mgr,\\ &amp;=&amp; \frac{5}{2}mgr. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>We now find the total energy at the bottom, since there is no potential energy, this is simply the kinetic energy,</p> \[E_b = \frac{1}{2}mv_b^2.\] <p>Where \(v_b\) is the speed we are looking for. With our assumptions, the energy at the top (\(E_t\)) equals the energy at the bottom (\(E_b\)) giving</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} E_b &amp;=&amp; E_t,\\ \frac{1}{2}mv_b^2 &amp;=&amp; \frac{5}{2}mgr,\\ mv_b^2 &amp;=&amp; 5mgr,\\ v_b^2 &amp;=&amp; 5gr,\\ v_b &amp;=&amp; \sqrt{5gr}. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>Thus we have found the speed required to complete a loop the loop of radius \(r\). For example, if the loop had a 4 metre diameter (2 metre radius) then the velocity required to complete the loop would be \(v = \sqrt{5\times g\times 2}=\sqrt{10g}\approx 9.9\).</p> <p>For convience we can approximate \(\sqrt{5gr}\) as:</p> \[\sqrt{5\times 9.81\times r}=\sqrt{49.05r}\approx 7\sqrt{r}.\]]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is the velocity required to complete a loop-the-loop]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s Snowing Outside</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/snowing-outside/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It’s Snowing Outside"/><published>2013-01-19T16:35:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-01-19T16:35:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/snowing-outside</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2013/snowing-outside/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m sitting in my office, at home, watching the snow falling outside and it got me thinking….</p> <p>As is well known, chemically, water is made from hydrogen and oxygen (H2O), specifically, each water molecule is made from two hydrogen atoms bonded with an oxygen atom. In this bonding there are two left over pairs of electrons, and the whole molecule creates a rough tetrahedron.</p> <p>“Luckily” (from the point of view of this post) when dealing with hexagonal ice (ice Ih) (i.e. natural ice /snow) we get a perfect tetrahedron (see here and here for more details of this), hence the six-fold symmetry in snowflakes.</p> <p>Now we know this, we can work out just how unique the snow outside is, or the ice in your cup (perhaps you’re reading this in a warmer climate!) is. How many possible ways are there to create a tetrahedral structure like hexagonal ice?</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/water_molecule-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/water_molecule-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/water_molecule-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/water_molecule.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>With a little bit of thinking, and twisting the above image in your head, hopefully you’ll agree with me that there are 6 ways of arranging the water molecule in the ‘ice tetrahedron’. However, not every one of these possibilities is possible. Read the Wikipedia page on hydrogen bonds and then you’ll see that in fact only \(\frac{3}{2}\)  possible orientations are allowed. That is, for a crystal of N molecules, there are \(\left(\frac{3}{2}\right)^N\) ways to arrange the molecules inside that crystal.</p> <p>So, let us consider a snowball, say of 3 cm radius. How many molecules are there in that much snow?</p> <p>There are a number of ways of arriving at the number of molecules, but I’m going to go for the way which came to me first (rather than perhaps the best / most elegant solution (not that I know what that is!)). I considered the snow as water (because I know the molar mass of water!), so for that we just need to know the density of snow. Not so easy, it depends on various factors; as you have no doubt experienced, new snow feels a lot less dense then snow that has been sitting around for a week. Typically the densities vary between 8% and 50% the density of water. Once the snow is on the ground it settles under its own weight to a density of around 30%. Since the snow that got me thinking about this is fairly new, we’ll go for a density of 20%. That means 30 cm of snow would make 6 cm of water.</p> <p>So our 3 cm radius snow ball has a volume of \(\approx 113\,cm^3\) which would be \(22.6\, cm^3\) of water. A cubic centimetre of water weights 1 grams so the water content of our snowball would weigh 22.6 g.</p> <p>The molar mass of water is \(18.01528\, g\cdot mol^{-1}\) so there is</p> \[22.6 \times\frac{1}{18.01528}\approx 1.25 \mbox{ moles}.\] <p>Multiplying this number by Avogadro’s number (\(6.02\times 10^{23}\)) yields the number of molecules in the snowball:</p> \[1.25 \times 6.02\times 10^{23} \approx 7.5\times 10^{23}.\] <p>That means the possible number of orientations of the water molecules is</p> \[\left(\frac{3}{2}\right)^{7.5\times 10^{23}} \approx 10^{10^{23}}.\] <p>So how big is that number? Well it is stupidly big. We estimate that there is something like \(10^{80}\) atoms in the universe which isn’t even close to that number. So it is safe to say that every snowball that has ever been made, or ever will be made by people all over the Earth for the rest of the history of this planet, will always have a unique arrangements of water molecules!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Investigating the number of unique snowballs]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Crawshaw Method (for Quadratics)</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/the-Crawshaw-method/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crawshaw Method (for Quadratics)"/><published>2012-05-01T20:49:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-05-01T20:49:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/the-Crawshaw-method</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/the-Crawshaw-method/"><![CDATA[<p>Something all High School students (and above) need to know is how to factorize quadratic equations. However I am amazed how few people know a decent (and easy) way of doing this!</p> <p>I’ll keep this as simple as possible, and just show you how to use the method.</p> <p>First we consider a simple case (and sadly this is where a lot of the problems arise from!), we want to factorize the quadratic equation,</p> \[x^2+5x+6.\] <p>Now, as far as I know, it is universally taught that to factorize this you have to “find” two numbers that times together to make \(+6\) (the constant term) and add to make \(+5\) (the linear term). This is pretty easy, we choose the numbers \(+2\) and \(+3\), and then we simply write down the answer,</p> \[x^2+5x+6=(x+2)(x+3).\] <p>Easy.</p> <p>The problem is when you arrive at a question like,</p> \[3x^2-7x-6.\] <p>If we proceed in the same way as we were `taught’ above we need to find two numbers which times together to make \(-6\) and add to make \(-7\). We then need to try and work out what on Earth to do with these numbers, the problem is, it is not in any way obvious and quite a lot of guess work, or at least trial and error, is required.  The answer we would be looking for was</p> \[3x^2-7x-6=(3x+2)(x-3).\] <p>I think what is clear is that we need a concise, dare I say easy, method to solve any quadratic equation.</p> <p>Let me introduce the <em>Crawshaw method</em>.</p> <p>We first will apply the method to the ‘easy’ quadratic formula (the method is identical for all quadratics), you only need to remember that \(x=1x\), only we don’t write the \(1\). So the quadratic to solve is \(x^2+5x+6\).</p> <p>The first step of the method tells us that we need to find two numbers which add together to make \(+5\) and times to make \(1\times 6=6\), that is, the coefficient of the quadratic term (\(1\)) multiplied by the constant term (\(6\)). These numbers are \(2\) and \(3\).</p> <p>The second step is to rewrite the linear term as a combination of the numbers we have just found. So for this question the linear term is \(+5x\) the numbers we found were \(2\) and \(3\) so we will replace \(+5x\) in the quadratic with \(+2x+3x\). So our quadratic is now:</p> \[x^2+2x+3x+6.\] <p>Which is of course the exact same equation but now we can continue with the method.</p> <p>We now draw an imaginary line down the middle of the equation:</p> \[x^2+2x\quad/\quad+3x+6.\] <p>Next we factorize the left hand side, getting:</p> \[x(x+2)\quad/\quad+3x+6.\] <p>We then need to factorize the right hand side, but making sure that the bracket terms are the same, i.e.</p> \[x(x+2)\quad/\quad+3(x+2).\] <p>Then finally we get our two brackets (for the factorized answer) as the one bracket we already have, and the two terms that are on the outside of the brackets (i.e. in this case \(x\) and \(+3\)). Thus our answer becomes</p> \[(x+2)(x+3).\] <p>This method does seem more difficult for this ‘easy’ equation (i.e. one where the coefficient of the quadratic term is \(1\)) but the beauty of the Crawshaw method is that it works exactly the same for all quadratic equations.</p> <p>Now let us consider the second equation, that is \(3x^2-7x-6\). We approach it in exactly the same way.</p> <p>First find two numbers which times together to make \(3\times -6 = -18\) (that is the coefficient of the quadratic term multiplied by the constant term) and add together to make \(-7\). Such numbers are \(-9\) and \(+2\). So we now rewrite the linear term with these numbers (i.e. replacing \(-7x=-9x+2x\)) so we get:</p> \[3x^2-9x+2x-6.\] <p>Now we draw an imaginary line down the middle and factorize both sides of the equation:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} 3x^2-9x \quad &amp;/&amp; \quad 2x-6,\\ 3x(x-3) \quad &amp;/&amp; \quad +2(x-3). \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>So we then have our factorized solution,</p> \[3x^2-7x-6=(3x+2)(x-3).\] <p>See, wasn’t that easier?</p> <p>I present to you, the Crawshaw method.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to solve quadratic equations using the Crawshaw method]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Short History of Nearly Everything - Some Corrections</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/a-short-history/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Short History of Nearly Everything - Some Corrections"/><published>2012-03-31T12:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-03-31T12:38:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/a-short-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/a-short-history/"><![CDATA[<p>I have just finished the book “A Short History of Nearly Everything” by Bill Bryson and I thought it was absolutely fantastic. There were a couple of mistakes that I noticed (and I am sure others that I did not - by ‘noticed’ I mean ‘didn’t believe the numbers and so checked them out’) that I thought I should correct. This post just provides a few scientific corrections, and is meant in <strong>no way as disrespect to what I believe to be a truly brilliant book</strong>.</p> <blockquote> <p>On a diagram of the solar system to scale, with Earth reduced to about the diameter of a pea, Jupiter would be over a thousand feet away and Pluto would be a mile and a half distant (and about the size of a bacterium, so you wouldn’t be able to see it anyway).</p> </blockquote> <p>Okay, assume that the radius of a pea is about \(4\) millimetres, or \(4 \times 10^{-3}\) metres. The mean radius of the Earth is \(6.371 \times 10^3\) metres, or the peas radius is \(\frac{1}{1592750000}\) of the Earth’s. We will use this fraction as the scale for the rest of the system. The distance between the Earth and Jupiter is \(5.808\) AU so on our scale that turns out to be \(1790\) feet. Pluto (which is \(32.15\) AU away) would be \(1.88\) miles away. So in this sense Bryson underestimated their distances (slightly). However, as for the size of Pluto, it has a mean radius of \(1.173 \times 10^6\) metres, so on our scale that would become \(7.4 \times 10^{-4}\) metres, i.e. a total diameter of 1.5 millimetres, very visible and about 75 times larger than a median bacterium!</p> <blockquote> <p>Protons are so small that a little dib of ink like the dot on this i can hold something in the region of 500,000,000,000 of them, rather more than the number of seconds contained in half a million years.</p> </blockquote> <p>I think the approximate size of a ‘dot’ is about \(0.5\) millimetres, so that means the area, in metres, of such a dot is: \(\pi\cdot 0.00025^2=1.963\times 10^{-7}\). The size of a proton is \(8.77 \times 10^{-16}\) metres, and so the number of protons that would fit in such a dot is \(223,887,732\). Or \(2233\) times less than the Bryson stated number. As for the number of seconds in half a million years: \(1 \mbox{ year } = 31556926 \mbox{ seconds}\) and \(500,000 \mbox{ years } = 15,800,000,000,000 \mbox{ seconds}\). Quite a lot more than what was stated, in fact, \(500,000,000,000\) seconds is only 15844 years.</p> <blockquote> <p>Even so, it [the Voyager spacecraft] took them nine years to reach Uranus and a dozen to cross the orbit of Pluto.</p> </blockquote> <p>Actually, Voyager 1 never got to Uranus nor cross the orbit of Pluto, only Voyager 2 did.</p> <blockquote> <p>[Betelgeuse is] fifty thousand light years away.</p> </blockquote> <p>Betelgeuse is around \(643 \pm 143\) light years away.</p> <blockquote> <p>It is thought that our entire planet may contain, at any given moment, fewer than twenty francium atoms.</p> </blockquote> <p>There is almost certainly a lot more than twenty francium atoms, according to <a href="https://perey.org/genealogy/MP%202.pdf">Adloff and Kauffman</a>, there is 550 grams in the Earth’s crust.</p> <blockquote> <p>It took thousands of workers to clear 1.8 billion tonnes of debris from the 6.5 hectares of the World Trade Center site.</p> </blockquote> <p>1.8 million tonnes.</p> <blockquote> <p>It rises exponentially, so that a 7.3 quake is fifty ties more powerful than a 6.3 earthquake and 2,500 time more powerful than a 5.3 earthquake.</p> </blockquote> <p>Exactly what the mistake is here depends slightly on what you interpret the word <em>powerful</em> means. The <em>size</em> of an earthquake increases by a factor of 10 as magnitude increases by one whole number. So a magnitude 7.3 earthquake is <strong>10 times</strong> larger than a 6.3, and <strong>100 times</strong> larger than 5.3. The amount of <em>energy released</em> increases by a factor of 31.6 \(\left(10^{1.5}\right)\). So a 7.3 earthquake releases roughly 32 times more energy than a magnitude 6.3; and about 1,000 times more energy than a 5.3.</p> <blockquote> <p>It has been calculated that if you sunk a well to the center [of the Earth] and dropped a brick into it, it would take only 45 minutes for it to hit the bottom.</p> </blockquote> <p>The terminal velocity of an object falling through the air is the maximum speed that the object will reach when the resistance of the medium through which it falls (in this case, air) prevents further acceleration. This velocity depends on various factors, including the mass and aerodynamic properties of the object (such as its shape and surface area), as well as the density of the air. For a brick, calculating its terminal velocity involves considering its drag coefficient, cross-sectional area perpendicular to the direction of motion, and mass. Using sensible estimates for this value we could calculate the terminal velocity of a house brick to be approximately 45 meters per second. Given that the Earth’s radius is approximately 6371 km, the brick would take about 39 hours to fall to the centre (given all the other difficulties with this thought experiment!).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some corrections in A Short History of Nearly Everything]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1 = 2</title><link href="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/1-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1 = 2"/><published>2012-02-17T14:07:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-02-17T14:07:00+00:00</updated><id>https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/1-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanelvidge.github.io/blog/2012/1-2/"><![CDATA[<p>Many people have seen “proofs” that \(1 = 2\). However there are always a rather obvious fallacy - a division by 0.</p> <p>A classic such example is:</p> \[\begin{eqnarray*} a &amp;=&amp; b, \\ a^2 &amp;=&amp; ab, \\ a^2 - b^2 &amp;=&amp; ab - b^2, \\ (a+b)(a-b) &amp;=&amp; b(a-b), \\ (a+b) &amp;=&amp; b, \\ a+a &amp;=&amp; a, \\ 2a &amp;=&amp; a, \\ 2 &amp;=&amp; 1. \end{eqnarray*}\] <p>This is a decent “trick” to show people, but as I said above, the mistake simply comes from the division by 0 on the 5th line.</p> <p>However, here is a different “proof”, can you see the mistake?</p> <p>Consider the equation, \(2=x^{x^{x^{\ldots}}}\), with an infinite number of \(x\)’s. If we add some brackets to the equation we get, \(2=x^{\left(x^{x^{\ldots}}\right)}\) and then we can substitute the first equation in to get:</p> \[2=x^2.\] <p>So \(x=\sqrt{2}\), and hence</p> \[2=\sqrt{2}^{\sqrt{2}^{\sqrt{2}^{\ldots}}}.\] <p>Then if we repeat the exact same above process with the equation \(4=x^{x^{x^{\ldots}}}\) we see that \(4=x^4\) and so again \(x=\sqrt{2}\). So this time,</p> \[4=\sqrt{2}^{\sqrt{2}^{\sqrt{2}^{\ldots}}}.\] <p>And so \(2=4\) and thus \(1=2\)!</p> <p>Where is the mistake?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1 = 2]]></summary></entry></feed>